<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Gend Soc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Gend Soc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GAS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spgas</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Gender &#x00026; Society</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0891-2432</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6187074</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0891243218783670</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0891243218783670</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Re-Understanding Religion and Support for Gender Equality in Arab
Countries</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Glas</surname><given-names>Saskia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0891243218783670"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spierings</surname><given-names>Niels</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scheepers</surname><given-names>Peer</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="aff1-0891243218783670">Radboud University, the Netherlands</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-0891243218783670">Saskia Glas, Radboud University, Nijmegen,
6500 HE, the Netherlands; e-mail: <email>s.glas@ru.nl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>686</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2018 by The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">Sociologists for Women in
Society</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which
permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work
without further permission provided the original work is attributed as
specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Much is said about Middle Eastern and North African (MENA) publics opposing
gender equality, often referring to patriarchal Islam. However, nuanced
large-scale studies addressing which specific aspects of religiosity affect
support for gender equality across the MENA are conspicuously absent. This study
develops and tests a gendered agentic socialization framework that proposes that
MENA citizens are not only passively socialized by religion but also have agency
(within their religiosity). This disaggregates the influence of religiosity,
highlights its multifacetedness, and theorizes the moderating roles that gender
and sociocognitive empowerment play via gendered processes of agentic
dissociations. Using 15 World Values Surveys and multilevel models, our analyses
show that most dimensions of religiosity fuel opposition to gender equality.
However, the salience of religion in daily life is found to increase women&#x02019;s
support for gender equality and cushion the negative impact of religious service
attendance. Also, gender and education moderate the impacts of several
religiosity dimensions; for instance, women&#x02019;s (initially greater) support for
gender equality more sharply declines with increased service attendance than
men&#x02019;s. Altogether, this study finds that religious socialization is multifaceted
and gendered, and that certain men and women are inclined and equipped to
deviate from dominant patriarchal religious interpretations.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Middle East and North Africa</kwd><kwd>gender equality</kwd><kwd>public opinion</kwd><kwd>Islam</kwd><kwd>agency</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="award1-0891243218783670"><funding-source id="funding1-0891243218783670"><institution-wrap><institution>Nederlandse Organisatie voor Wetenschappelijk
Onderzoek</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003246</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id rid="funding1-0891243218783670">406-16-517</award-id></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Arab Middle Eastern and North African (MENA) publics report one of the world&#x02019;s lowest
rates of support for gender equality (<xref rid="bibr39-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Norris 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bibr42-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Price 2016</xref>), and, consequently, the Arab MENA
shows relatively large political and socioeconomic inequalities between men and women
(<xref rid="bibr41-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Paxton, Kunovich, and Hughes
2007</xref>). Thorough knowledge of what drives the MENA publics&#x02019; resistance to
gender equality is thus pivotal to address real-world inequalities. However, previous
public opinion research and Western public debates explain opposition to gender equality
in the MENA by pointing rather unidimensionally to Muslims&#x02019; (vs. non-Muslims&#x02019;)
patriarchal religious socialization (<xref rid="bibr2-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Alexander and Welzel 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr22-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Inglehart and Norris 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr32-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Lussier and Fish 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bibr36-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Moaddel 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bibr47-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Rizzo, Meyer, and Ali 2007</xref>).
This narrative breathes Orientalism: a homogenous MENA &#x0201c;other&#x0201d; characterized by
irrationality, oppression, passiveness, and, most of all, patriarchal Islam is opposed
to &#x0201c;the self,&#x0201d; the progressive, active, secular West (<xref rid="bibr1-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Abu-Lughod 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bibr28-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Korteweg 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bibr48-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Said 1979</xref>), without acknowledging or theorizing
how religiosity is a multifaceted and gendered force.</p><p>The present study aims to understand relations between religiosity and support for gender
equality in the Arab MENA in a more sophisticated manner by developing and testing new
theoretical notions of &#x0201c;agentic socialization.&#x0201d; These notions build on multidisciplinary
insights from classic sociology, in-depth qualitative studies, and feminist scholarship
(e.g., <xref rid="bibr6-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Avishai and Irby 2017</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr12-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Charrad 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr16-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Elder, Johnson, and Crosnoe
2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr52-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Sewell 1992</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr57-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Spierings 2015</xref>). The
agentic socialization framework rejects claims that MENA inhabitants are solely and
uniformly passively socialized to oppose gender equality. Instead, it proposes that MENA
citizens have agency&#x02014;even within dominant patriarchal socialization&#x02014;and that
socialization processes are gendered (see also <xref rid="bibr38-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Moghissi 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr44-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Read and Bartkowski 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bibr61-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Zion-Waldoks 2015</xref>). The framework thus stresses
that women and men might &#x0201c;live&#x0201d; their religion differently and have the ability to
bargain with their religion and interpret it in ways that deviate from the dominant
patriarchal mainstream (<xref rid="bibr20-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Hall
1997</xref>; <xref rid="bibr24-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Kandiyoti
1988</xref>; <xref rid="bibr45-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldo
2014</xref>).</p><p>In applying our framework, we propose that religious socialization may be gendered and
particularly women may be more inclined to make up their own minds on gender equality
and religion and that sociocognitive empowerment may equip people to agentically deviate
from patriarchal religious interpretations. We thus theorize specifically how gender and
education shape religious reinterpretations. This implies that relations between
people&#x02019;s religiosity and their support for gender equality differ by gender and
education, which we test empirically (<xref rid="bibr27-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Khurshid 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bibr43-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Prickett 2015</xref>).</p><p>To understand how religion can be both a source of emancipatory reinterpretations and
patriarchal socialization, we argue that it is necessary to take a more refined approach
to individual-level religiosity than to focus on differences between Muslims and
non-Muslims, as is done in most MENA public opinion studies (e.g., <xref rid="bibr2-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Alexander and Welzel 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr32-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Lussier and Fish 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bibr42-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Price 2016</xref>). We therefore disaggregate the
concept of religion and conceptualize it multidimensionally. Sociology of religion
scholars have shown that religiosity is indeed multidimensional and complex, identifying
among others: communal practices (e.g., attending religious services), doctrinal beliefs
(e.g., textualism), devotion (e.g., religious self-perception), and salience (e.g.,
religion-driven daily choices) (<xref rid="bibr14-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Cornwall et al. 1986</xref>; <xref rid="bibr25-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Kellstedt et al. 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bibr58-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Stark and Glock 1968</xref>). Appreciating these distinctions allows us to address
more precisely in which ways religiosity might have different implications for women and
more highly educated citizens than for men and lower educated citizens. Altogether, our
research question reads: To what extent are different dimensions of religiosity related
to support for gender equality in the Arab MENA, and how do these relations differ for
women and more highly educated individuals?</p><sec id="section1-0891243218783670"><title>Religious Socialization Reconsidered</title><sec id="section2-0891243218783670"><title>The Agentic Socialization Framework</title><p>Our agentic socialization framework aims to understand support for gender
equality in the Arab MENA in a nuanced manner by refining and integrating
classic sociological frames and gender theories (<xref rid="bibr1-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Abu-Lughod 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bibr6-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Avishai and Irby 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bibr16-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Elder, Johnson, and Crosnoe
2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr24-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Kandiyoti
1988</xref>; <xref rid="bibr28-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Korteweg
2008</xref>; <xref rid="bibr52-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Sewell
1992</xref>; <xref rid="bibr58-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Stark and
Glock 1968</xref>). At its core, the framework emphasizes that MENA citizens
are embedded in dominantly patriarchal religious structures, but that
socialization processes within those structures differ between men and women.
Moreover, citizens have the agency to reinterpret their religion; women and men
in the MENA are not solely passively socialized to follow prevailing religious
interpretations but can give alternative, progressive meanings to their
religiosity that are more conducive to support for gender equality.</p><p>Our framework departs from life course theory (<xref rid="bibr16-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Elder, Johnson, and Crosnoe 2003</xref>) and
agency-structure duality&#x02019;s (<xref rid="bibr52-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Sewell 1992</xref>) assertion that people are always embedded in
spatio-temporal contexts with pre-existing (socially constructed) structures
that shape their lives. Here we focus on the established patriarchal
interpretations of religion in which MENA citizens are embedded from birth and
childhood on (<xref rid="bibr3-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Al-Hibri
1982</xref>; <xref rid="bibr35-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Mir-Hosseini 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bibr38-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Moghissi 2011</xref>). Integration in and
socialization by these pre-existing religious structures shape MENA citizens&#x02019;
lives, including the meanings they attach to gender. In other words, the more
integrated individuals are in this patriarchal religion in general, the less
likely they are to support gender equality. Simultaneously, these theories
propose that people have the agency to construct their own lives within their
contexts rather than to merely reproduce patriarchal interpretations from
generation to generation (<xref rid="bibr16-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Elder, Johnson, and Crosnoe 2003</xref>, 11).</p><p>Regarding agency and gender, Kandiyoti proposed in her influential work that
women use strategies to maneuver specific patriarchal contexts (1988, 275). In
the following debate, some argued that women&#x02019;s agency is found in resisting
religion, which equates agency to secularism and thus denies religious women
their agency while still conceptualizing religion as a unidimensional force that
singularly oppresses women (<xref rid="bibr1-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Abu-Lughod 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bibr28-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Korteweg 2008</xref>). Other scholars emphasized &#x0201c;illiberal agency,&#x0201d; which
claims that religious women might exercise agency in actively being orthodox
even when that reinforces patriarchal religious structures (<xref rid="bibr5-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Avishai 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bibr33-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Mahmood 2005</xref>). This
position has been criticized for stretching &#x0201c;agency&#x0201d; so far that it becomes a
hollow term (<xref rid="bibr38-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Moghissi
2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr45-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldo
2014</xref>).</p><p>In our framework, we transcend both views and integrate them into contemporary
sociological theories. Our premise is that people are indeed&#x02014;to different
degrees&#x02014;socialized by patriarchal religious structures, but that people embedded
in these patriarchal religious structures have the agency to subvert dominant
religious interpretations to promote their (gendered) interests (see also <xref rid="bibr28-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Korteweg 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bibr45-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldo 2014</xref>).
Paradoxically, dominant patriarchal religious structures thus provide the very
conditions for agentic <italic>re-</italic>interpretations of religion (<xref rid="bibr23-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Jansen 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bibr35-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Mir-Hosseini 2006</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr43-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Prickett 2015</xref>).
Religious MENA citizens&#x02014;especially women&#x02014;thus should not be considered to be
solely passively socialized by patriarchal religious structures but capable of
actively negotiating religious meanings attached to gender by drawing on
alternative religious and secular sources (<xref rid="bibr44-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Read and Bartkowski 2000</xref>).</p><p>This framework signifies &#x0201c;religion&#x0201d; as dynamic and negotiable, allowing room to
advance support for gender equality but simultaneously as containing rigid
oppressive structures that socialize citizens into patriarchal worldviews. To
understand how religious socialization shapes people&#x02019;s support for gender
equality in negotiable ways, we argue that religiosity needs to be
conceptualized in a multidimensional way because different manifestations of
individual-level religiosity have different implications regarding socialization
and negotiability, as will be theorized more concretely below.</p><p>In line with classic and more contemporary distinctions, we firstly differentiate
between (external) religious practices and (internal) religious beliefs (see
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0891243218783670">Figure 1</xref>) (<xref rid="bibr14-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Cornwall et al. 1986</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr20-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Hall 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bibr25-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Kellstedt et al. 1996</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr58-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Stark and Glock
1968</xref>). We further subdivide religious practices into two categories:
private religious behaviors that are acted out without others, and communal
practices, such as attending religious services, that imply exposure to the
institutional patriarchal establishment&#x02019;s home (<xref rid="bibr4-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Aune 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bibr35-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Mir-Hosseini 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bibr40-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Nyhagen 2017</xref>).
Concerning religious beliefs, a further distinction can be made as well.
Doctrinal beliefs stipulate the interpretation of one&#x02019;s religion, whereas
affective beliefs relate to feelings of attachment to religion regardless of the
specific content of those beliefs. Affective beliefs encompass a more general
and abstract attachment to religion in and of itself (&#x0201c;devotion&#x0201d;) and feelings
that religion specifically guides daily life choices (&#x0201c;salience&#x0201d;). Below, we
apply our theoretical framework to communal practices (attendance), doctrinal
beliefs (textualism), and affective beliefs (devotion and salience), the
dimensions we could incorporate empirically.</p><fig id="fig1-0891243218783670" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1:</label><caption><p>Conceptual Scheme of Religiosity</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0891243218783670-fig1"/></fig></sec><sec id="section3-0891243218783670"><title>Multidimensional Religious Socialization</title><p>Whereas previous quantitative MENA studies have predominantly drawn on
unidimensional socialization perspectives (e.g., <xref rid="bibr2-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Alexander and Welzel 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr22-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Inglehart and Norris
2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr32-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Lussier and
Fish 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bibr42-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Price
2016</xref>), our multidimensional framework emphasizes that different
dimensions of religiosity link differently to socialization and support for
gender equality. First, attending religious services entails exposure to the
MENA&#x02019;s structural &#x0201c;ruling patriarchal establishment,&#x0201d; which generally preaches
gendered worldviews of men and women being complementary and hierarchically
related (<xref rid="bibr3-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Al-Hibri
1982</xref>, ix; <xref rid="bibr11-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Bolzendahl
and Myers 2004</xref>). Frequent attendance therefore is expected to
increase the likelihood that such messages will be internalized, corroding
support for gender equality (<xref rid="bibr21-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Hervieu-L&#x000e9;ger 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bibr59-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Sumerau 2012</xref>). Second, doctrinal
beliefs are expected to influence support for gender equality (<xref rid="bibr3-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Al-Hibri 1982</xref>; <xref rid="bibr30-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Kucinskas 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bibr37-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Moghadam 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bibr57-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Spierings 2015</xref>). The
doctrinal belief we specifically focus on is &#x0201c;textualism&#x0201d; (<xref rid="bibr45-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldo 2014</xref>): the belief that
religious texts have one static literalist meaning&#x02014;voiced by the
institutionalized patriarchy&#x02014;instead of a spirit to be interpreted in light of
the time they were written (<xref rid="bibr34-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Masoud, Jamal, and Nugent 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bibr38-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Moghissi 2011</xref>). For example, the Quran
and Hadith can be interpreted textually, or literally, as a point-blank
condemnation of taking your own life,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn1-0891243218783670">1</xref></sup> while contextualists have proposed more lenient conclusions based on the
current rapid expansions of Muslim-majority countries&#x02019; populations (<xref rid="bibr54-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Shapiro 2013</xref>).
Textualist readings generally oppose gender equality. For instance, interpreting
the Quran&#x02019;s proclamations on inheritance textually stipulates that women&#x02019;s
shares should literally be half of men&#x02019;s (4:11, Khan trans.). Contextual
interpretations stress an emancipatory spirit as women are allocated more than
the nothing they generally had in the seventh century before Islam (<xref rid="bibr35-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Mir-Hosseini 2006</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr51-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Selim 2003</xref>).
Altogether, we thus expect that: The frequency of communal religious service
attendance and holding textualist beliefs are negatively related to support for
gender equality (<italic>Hypothesis 1</italic>).</p><p>Drawing attention to affective beliefs, our framework however suggests that
religiosity might actually fuel support for gender equality. Counter to
doctrinal beliefs, religious affect does not reflect a certain (patriarchal)
<italic>content</italic> of beliefs, but rather it reflects on the
attachment to religion in and of itself, to the main undercurrents of religion.
These main religious tenets of monotheistic religions have been argued to
involve benevolent traits related to mercy, generosity, and fairness (<xref rid="bibr50-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz and Huismans
1995</xref>). Bloom, Arikan, and Courtemanche&#x02019;s review (<xref rid="bibr10-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, 205), for
instance, points out that &#x0201c;the major religious traditions all emphasize
compassion.&#x0201d; Regarding Islam, one of the five pillars, <italic>Zakat</italic>,
specifically concerns charity, and the Quran designates Allah as
<italic>al-Rahman</italic> (Most Merciful) and <italic>al-Rahim</italic>
(Compassionate). Similarly, <xref rid="bibr17-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">El Fadl (2001</xref>, 9) has illustrated the Islamic ethos as one of
general egalitarianism: &#x0201c;Islam rejects elitism and emphasizes that truth is
equally accessible to all Muslims regardless of race, class, or gender.&#x0201d;
Altogether, we hypothesize that: The stronger peoples&#x02019; affective religious
beliefs (devotion and salience), the higher their support for gender equality
(<italic>Hypothesis 2</italic>).</p></sec><sec id="section4-0891243218783670"><title>Gendered Socialization and Agentic Reinterpretation</title><p>As our agentic socialization framework proposes that citizens are not uniformly
passively sculpted by dominant religious interpretations, but that socialization
processes may differ for different societal groups, the impact of individuals&#x02019;
religiosity may vary with their gender and education (<xref rid="bibr27-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Khurshid 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bibr45-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldo 2014</xref>). Several mechanisms lead
us to expect that religiosity&#x02019;s impact on support for gender equality is
gendered, including women&#x02019;s personal interests and the gender conservative
socialization in the MENA region overall (<xref rid="bibr11-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Bolzendahl and Myers 2004</xref>). Concerning
people&#x02019;s interests, gender equality is generally considered to be more in the
direct interest of women than men. Currently men benefit from being designated
head of households with greater legal rights. Therefore, women may be more
inclined to diverge from patriarchal religious messages and seek or accept
alternative interpretations that allow them more rights, as several in-depth
studies have shown (<xref rid="bibr23-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Jansen
2004</xref>; <xref rid="bibr34-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Masoud,
Jamal, and Nugent 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bibr38-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Moghissi 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr43-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Prickett 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bibr44-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Read and Bartkowski 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bibr45-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldo 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bibr51-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Selim 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr61-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Zion-Waldoks 2015</xref>).
Women may also be socialized differently than men. While men tend to be taught
to be aggressive, competitive, household leaders, women&#x02019;s socialization
accentuates their supposedly emotional, affectionate, caring, gentle, and
overall benevolent nature (<xref rid="bibr19-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Gonzalez 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr31-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Lueptow, Garovich-Szabo, and Lueptow 2001</xref>). Women&#x02019;s socialization
into benevolence&#x02014;apart from religious benevolence&#x02014;has been shown to translate to
greater social compassion and support for gender equality (<xref rid="bibr15-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Eagly et al. 2004</xref>). Both gendered
interests and gendered socialization thus lead us to expect that women will
support gender equality more than men, but also that religion&#x02019;s impact will vary
between women and men. Still, as <xref rid="bibr32-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Lussier and Fish (2016</xref>, 35) note,
&#x0201c;surprisingly little has been written about the intersection between sex and
religious identification with regard to attitudes about gender inequality.&#x0201d;</p><p>Filling this lacuna, first we propose that the gender gap in support for gender
equality will close with stronger integration in the established religious
patriarchy. Low integration in institutionalized religion&#x02014;that is, not
frequenting services and not adhering to strict textualism&#x02014;is expected to
bolster space to deviate from patriarchal religious interpretations. Given
gendered socialization and interests, we then propose that especially women will
use that space (<xref rid="bibr11-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Bolzendahl
and Myers 2004</xref>), whereas men have no incentive to reinterpret their
religion on top of their more conservative socialization.</p><p>However, stronger integration in the institutional patriarchy&#x02014;with its
authoritative truth-claims of the proper interpretation of religion&#x02014;is expected
to leave little wiggle room for those agentic deviations. Religious service
attendance and textualism thus are expected to shrink spaces that particularly
women use, impeding especially women&#x02019;s propensity to benevolent
reinterpretations. At the same time, it is also theoretically possible that, for
instance, women who frequent services represent a selective group that is more
gender conservative even before attendance. Still, here it should be noted again
that intergenerational transmissions of religiosity and the structural character
of religious institutions render this possibility less likely. Also, the most
conservative women might not attend services because there are no facilities or
because they believe they should pray at home. Not attending services is thus
not one-to-one translated to being less conservative, which is also illustrated
by the fact that a substantial number of women attend services at least once a
week, but even more do so less often.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn2-0891243218783670">2</xref></sup> Moreover, a wealth of ethnographic research in this area shows that even
if attendance is partly a process of self-selection, it seems unlikely that
women&#x02019;s gender attitudes also are unaffected by attendance (see <xref rid="bibr8-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Bartkowski and Read
2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr43-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Prickett
2015</xref>; <xref rid="bibr44-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Read and
Bartkowski 2000</xref>). Several studies have even pointed out that women
who attend religious services start off more progressive but amend their views
following service attendance (see <xref rid="bibr13-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Chong 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bibr18-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Griffith 1997</xref>). Altogether, we expect
that, compared to men&#x02019;s, women&#x02019;s initially greater support for gender equality
will be more sharply reduced when they attend services and adhere to textualist
beliefs, narrowing the gender gap in support for gender equality. Or formulated
in more technical terms: Negative relationships between religious service
attendance and textualism and support for gender equality are stronger for women
than men (<italic>Hypothesis 3</italic>).</p><p>Women&#x02019;s reinterpretations are however not expected to be stonewalled by all
dimensions of religiosity, drawing our attention to affective beliefs. Affective
religious beliefs&#x02014;feelings of attachment to religion rather than particular
beliefs regarding its proper content&#x02014;are expected to enlarge room for
reinterpretations as they are disconnected from the institutional religious
patriarchy and, as noted, may inspire interpreting religion benevolently.
Women&#x02019;s socialization into compassion and incentives to reinterpret their
religion are expected to drive women especially to make good use of affective
beliefs&#x02019; space for renegotiations (<xref rid="bibr43-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Prickett 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bibr44-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Read and Bartkowski 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bibr45-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldo 2014</xref>). We thus
expect that: Affective religious beliefs are positively related to support for
gender equality especially among women rather than among men (<italic>Hypothesis
4</italic>).</p><p>Agentic socialization also draws attention to being better equipped to diverge
from patriarchal religious socialization, which might have particular
implications for the role of education. As others have argued, more highly
educated people&#x02019;s cognitive skills allow them to reconcile more easily seemingly
contradictory views such as strongly religious and feminist ones (<xref rid="bibr37-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Moghadam 2013</xref>). Also,
their advantaged social position implies that the more highly educated are more
likely to encounter divergent views on (religious interpretations of) gender
norms, increasing their awareness of alternatives (<xref rid="bibr53-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Shamaileh 2016</xref>). Because of these
resources, more highly educated people are expected to deviate from patriarchal
religious interpretations more often, provided space for such renegotiations
exists. Thus, among those who are less integrated in the institutional religious
patriarchy, the more highly educated are expected to support gender equality
more. However, this educational gap in support for gender equality will close
with greater service attendance and textualism. In technical terms: Negative
relations between religious service attendance and textualism and support for
gender equality are stronger among the more highly educated than the lower
educated (<italic>Hypothesis 5</italic>).</p><p>Still, as seen, affective religious beliefs do not imply integration in the
institutional religious patriarchy and are expected to inspire benevolent
reinterpretations. Following their greater cognitive skills and awareness of
alternatives, especially more highly educated people are expected to use this
space and renegotiate religious meanings of gender (<xref rid="bibr37-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Moghadam 2013</xref>). Particularly the more
highly educated may thus translate affective beliefs into support for gender
equality: Affective religious beliefs are positively related to support for
gender equality especially among the more highly educated rather than the lower
educated (<italic>Hypothesis 6</italic>).</p><p>Finally, regarding the different dimensions of religiosity, our agentic
socialization framework also proposes that citizens can reinterpret their
religion in its own terms. Greater religious affect might make people rethink,
contest, or buffer some dominant oppressive religious interpretations, as
affective beliefs are expected to create knowledge of and adherence to
religion&#x02019;s main benevolent messages (<xref rid="bibr10-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Bloom, Arikan, and Courtemanche 2015</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr50-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz and Huismans
1995</xref>). For instance, attachment to the general notion of &#x0201c;love thy
neighbor&#x0201d; could be expected to make more devoted people less passively receptive
to patriarchal views voiced in services. Similarly, considering the benevolent
side of religion, it is expected that when religion is more saliently guiding
people&#x02019;s daily life choices, textualism is translated less strongly to judging
others, including prescribing how women should behave. We thus expect that:
Relations between attending religious services and textualism and support for
gender equality are weaker with higher levels of religious affect, that is,
devotion and salience (<italic>Hypothesis 7</italic>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="section5-0891243218783670"><title>Methods</title><p>This study uses the MENA subset of the World Values Survey. Of these, 15 surveys
(2001-2014) included the items needed. They represent 12 countries: Algeria (2x),
Bahrain, Egypt, Iraq, Jordan (2x), Lebanon, Libya, Morocco (2x), Palestine, Saudi
Arabia, Tunisia, and Yemen. All surveys target representativeness for the population
of 18 years and older, using stratified random sampling. These data are
representative regarding gender and age for most populations, and sometimes for
education and regional distributions as well.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn3-0891243218783670">3</xref></sup> The initial dataset contained 20,254 respondents; after listwise deletion
19,009 respondents (94 percent) remained. <xref rid="table1-0891243218783670" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents the descriptive
statistics.</p><table-wrap id="table1-0891243218783670" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1:</label><caption><p>Descriptive Statistics of All (Prestandardized) Variables</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0891243218783670-table1"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min.</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max.</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Dependent variable</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Support for gender equality</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.10</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Religion variables</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Religious service attendance<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0891243218783670">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Textualism<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0891243218783670">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Devotion<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0891243218783670">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Salience<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0891243218783670">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Agency variables</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Men</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Women</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Education<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0891243218783670">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Control variables</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Denomination</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Muslim</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Non-Muslim</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Age<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0891243218783670">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Age<sup>2,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0891243218783670">*</xref></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">324</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,649</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1566.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1199.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Marital status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Not married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Separated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Widowed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Employment status</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Full-time employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Part-time employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Self-employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Retired</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Homemaker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Student</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Non-employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Robustness check variables</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Prayer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,456</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Prayer WVS 4<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0891243218783670">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,132</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Prayer WVS 5<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0891243218783670">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,067</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Prayer WVS 6<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn3-0891243218783670">*</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,257</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Particularism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,959</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Not particularistic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;Particularistic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-0891243218783670"><p>NOTE: Min. = minimum; Max. = maximum; SD = standard deviation.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn2-0891243218783670"><p>SOURCE: WVS.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn3-0891243218783670"><label>*</label><p>Variable is z-scored for analyses.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="section6-0891243218783670"><title>Support for Gender Equality</title><p>We operationalize support for gender equality using three widely used items on
gender equality in the public sphere in particular. The three items asked
respondents to which extent they agreed with the statements: &#x0201c;On the whole, men
make better political leaders than women do&#x0201d; (four-point scale), &#x0201c;A university
education is more important for a boy than for a girl&#x0201d; (four-point scale), and
&#x0201c;When jobs are scarce, men should have more right to a job than women&#x0201d;
(three-point scale) (e.g., <xref rid="bibr9-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Blaydes and Linzer 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bibr29-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Kostenko, Kuzmuchev, and Ponarin 2016</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr42-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Price 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bibr56-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Spierings 2014</xref>). Factor
analyses showed that these items tap into the same underlying factor overall and
in 16 of 17 surveys separately,<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn4-0891243218783670">4</xref></sup> indicating measurement equivalency (<xref rid="bibr60-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Van de Vijver and Leung 1997</xref>). All
items were recoded so that higher scores indicate greater support for gender
equality. To approximate a normal distribution, we took the square root of the
mean scores of the three items, weighted by their factor loadings to create the
index <italic>support for gender equality.</italic> For ease of interpretation,
the final scale was rescaled to run from 0 to 100. The descriptive analyses
present a simple summed scale, as is mentioned.</p></sec><sec id="section7-0891243218783670"><title>Religiosity</title><p>We measure the <italic>frequency of religious service attendance</italic> with
the question &#x0201c;Apart from weddings and funerals, about how often do you attend
religious services these days?&#x0201d; (never, less than once a year, once a year, only
on holy days, once a month, once a week, more than once a week). The scores were
rescaled to a continuous variable ranging from 0 to 1.</p><p>Textualism&#x02014;interpreting religious texts statically and literally instead of
contextually&#x02014;is measured by the proxy of respondents&#x02019; views regarding the
justifiability of euthanasia and suicide. As noted in the theory section, taking
your own life (by euthanasia or suicide) is textually prohibited but
contextually permitted, making these measurements useful proxies for textualism
(<xref rid="bibr54-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Shapiro 2013</xref>).
These measurements, however, only pertain to one particular issue (i.e., taking
one&#x02019;s own life). Had the data permitted it, it would have been ideal to include
other issues or a more direct measurement, although we have no strong reason to
expect that being a textualist on other issues relates differently to support
for gender equality. Moreover, as discussed below, in our robustness tests we
included particularism as an alternative measurement of doctrinal beliefs, which
was measured unrelated to specific issues, and it is similarly related to
support for gender equality. To operationalize <italic>textualism</italic>, we
averaged the two 10-point items and rescaled it to a continuous variable ranging
from 0 to 1. Higher values signal greater textualism. As the distributions of
the two scales were similar, respondents were included if they had a valid score
on at least one indicator.</p><p>Concerning affective beliefs, we distinguished devotion and salience (see <xref rid="bibr58-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Stark and Glock 1968</xref>).
<italic>Devotion</italic>&#x02014;an abstract attachment to religion itself&#x02014;is
measured using two items that have been shown to tap the same concept before
(<xref rid="bibr56-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Spierings 2014</xref>):
(a) &#x0201c;Independently of whether you attend religious services or not, would you
say you are&#x0201d; a religious person (scored as 1), not a religious person, or a
convinced atheist (following <xref rid="bibr46-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Rizzo, Abdel-Latif, and Meyer [2007]</xref>, the last two are both scored
0); and (b) &#x0201c;Here is a list of qualities that children can be encouraged to
learn at home. Which, if any, do you consider to be especially important?&#x0201d;
Respondents who chose &#x0201c;religious faith&#x0201d; were considered to be more devoted (1)
than others (0). The scores of respondents with at least one valid answer were
averaged to the scale &#x0201c;devotion.&#x0201d;</p><p><italic>Salience</italic>&#x02014;a specific attachment to religion as a guide in (daily)
life&#x02014;was measured by another two items: &#x0201c;How important is God in your life?&#x0201d;
(ten-point scale, 0 to 1), and &#x0201c;For each of the following, indicate how
important it is in your life. Would you say religion is very important (1),
rather important, not very important, or not at all important (0)?&#x0201d; If at least
one item was answered validly, scores were averaged to the continuous scale
&#x0201c;salience.&#x0201d;</p><p>Our measurements of devotion and salience are less distinct from each other than
the theoretical concepts, as there are no data available on the salience of
religion in <italic>specific daily</italic> life choices. However, empirically
devotion and salience are not very strongly related and do not cause
multicollinearity issues (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/0891243218783670">online Appendix 1</ext-link>). We thus include both in our analyses to make
our results as nuanced and informative as possible.</p></sec><sec id="section8-0891243218783670"><title>Gender and Education</title><p>To study the gendered effects of religiosity, we measure respondents&#x02019;
<italic>gender</italic> as observed by the interviewer (0: woman; 1: man).
<italic>Education</italic>, the second moderator, includes four categories
across surveys: &#x0201c;no formal education completed&#x0201d; (0); &#x0201c;complete elementary&#x0201d; and
&#x0201c;incomplete secondary&#x0201d; (combined into &#x0201c;elementary,&#x0201d; 0.33); &#x0201c;complete secondary&#x0201d;
and &#x0201c;incomplete university education&#x0201d; (combined into &#x0201c;secondary,&#x0201d; 0.67); and
&#x0201c;complete university education and higher&#x0201d; (1).</p></sec><sec id="section9-0891243218783670"><title>Control Variables</title><p>Denomination, age, marital status, and employment status are included as control
variables. Respondents&#x02019; self-reported denomination, distinguishing between
Muslims and non-Muslims, is controlled in our models, and we also established
our results are substantially similar when we estimate models for Muslims
separately. The Bahrain 2014 survey does not include denomination, but virtually
all native Bahrainis are Muslim and considered as such here. Unfortunately, a
more refined distinction among either Muslims or non-Muslims was not available
in the majority of the surveys; comparing Muslims and non-Muslims does make our
results comparable to other studies (e.g., <xref rid="bibr32-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Lussier and Fish 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bibr39-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Norris 2009</xref>).
<italic>Age</italic> is a continuous scale; respondents under 18 were
excluded as they were not sampled in all surveys. Age squared is included to
capture important life course effects. Marital status is distinguished by four
groups: married, widowed, separated, and never married. Employment status
encompasses &#x0201c;fulltime employed,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;part-time employed,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;self-employed,&#x0201d;
&#x0201c;retired,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;homemaker,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;student,&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;non-employed&#x0201d; (including &#x0201c;unemployed&#x0201d;
and &#x0201c;other non-employed&#x0201d;).</p></sec><sec id="section10-0891243218783670"><title>Analytic Strategy</title><p>Our data have to be modeled using multilevel models to control for clustered
observations within country-years and countries; one-level models would deflate
our p-values and increase the chance of type I errors. Random intercepts are
included at the higher levels (country-time; country).<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn5-0891243218783670">5</xref></sup> This takes into account the clustered structure of the data and prevents
us from drawing false positive conclusions. To further increase the rigor of our
tests we also conducted various robustness checks, which we briefly discuss
after our main results as they yielded similar findings.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section11-0891243218783670"><title>Support for Gender Equality in the New Millennium</title><p>How supportive of gender equality (focused on equal participation in the public
sphere) are MENA publics in the new millennium? <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0891243218783670">Figure 2</xref> presents the mean scores on the
three items used to measure support for gender equality (without taking their square
root) and shows that respondents score an average of 36 out of 100 in the WVS data.
As a point of reference, when we analyze all countries included in the most recent
WVS wave, the MENA region has the lowest pooled average in the WVS. It is several
points below that of the next United Nations&#x02013;defined regions&#x02014;Southern Asia and West
Africa&#x02014;and substantially below the total sample average. Still, we also see
considerable differences within the MENA region; for instance, women&#x02019;s average
support is 43, while men&#x02019;s is less than 30.</p><fig id="fig2-0891243218783670" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2:</label><caption><p>Mean Support for Public Gender Equality per Gender per Survey (N =
19,009)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0891243218783670-fig2"/></fig></sec><sec id="section12-0891243218783670"><title>Explaining Support for Gender Equality</title><p><xref rid="table2-0891243218783670" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents the
multilevel regression results for support for gender equality. Model 1 includes all
direct effects of religiosity (Hypotheses 1 and 2); in Models 2 and 3, the
moderations between religiosity and gender and education are added, respectively
(Hypotheses 3 through 6); Model 4 includes interaction terms between the different
dimensions of religiosity themselves (Hypothesis 7). All models include the control
variables, which relate to support for gender equality as expected (see <xref rid="bibr32-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Lussier and Fish 2016</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr42-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Price 2016</xref>); for
instance, education has a clear positive impact, and women tend to be considerably
more supportive of gender equality: more than 15 points on a scale ranging from 0 to
100.</p><table-wrap id="table2-0891243218783670" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2:</label><caption><p>Multilevel analyses of support for public gender equality (N = 19,009)</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0891243218783670-table2"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 1</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 2</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 3</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Model 4</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Religious service attendance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;1.12</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;0.56</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;1.13</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;1.16</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Women</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;0.86</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;0.61</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Devotion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Salience</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.42</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Textualism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;0.88</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;0.97</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;0.92</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;0.81</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Women</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">&#x02642;</xref></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Devotion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Salience</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Devotion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;0.62</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;0.59</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;0.56</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Women</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;1.12</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salience</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;1.53</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x02212;0.32</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Women</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2.70</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">*</xref>Education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn4-0891243218783670">&#x02640;</xref></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender: Women (ref. = men)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>15.46</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>15.65</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>15.35</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>15.50</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3.24</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3.22</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3.25</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3.23</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denomination: Muslim (ref. = non-Muslim)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;4.83</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;4.90</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;4.95</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;4.87</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" rowspan="1">Marital status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Not married</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Separated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2.73</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2.70</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2.76</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2.69</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Widowed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" rowspan="1">Employment status</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Part-time employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Self-employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;2.24</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;2.29</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;2.29</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;2.27</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Retired</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Homemaker</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;5.08</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;5.31</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;4.92</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;5.07</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Student</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Non-employed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;1.23</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x02212;1.14</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intercept</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>34.73</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>34.58</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>34.86</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>34.71</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<italic>Variance</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Country-year</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">38.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">38.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">37.4</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">38.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Individual</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">473.0</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">471.1</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">472.6</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">472.8</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn4-0891243218783670"><p>NOTE: Bold coefficients indicate significance at &#x003b1; = 0.05, italics at &#x003b1; =
0.10. *, <sup>&#x02640;</sup>, and <sup>&#x02642;</sup> indicate parameter is only
significant in the Muslim subsample, female subsample, or male
subsample, respectively.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn5-0891243218783670"><p>SOURCE: WVS.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="section13-0891243218783670"><title>Multidimensional Religiosity</title><p>Model 1 suggests that religiosity mostly fuels opposition to gender equality.
MENA inhabitants who attend religious services more frequently, who interpret
their religion textually, and who are more devoted, all oppose gender equality
more. However, the salience of religious beliefs is the exception to the rule,
as it shows no clear significant relationship to support for gender equality.
Additional analyses indicate this is partly due to contradictory effects in
different contexts (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/0891243218783670">online Appendix 2</ext-link>). Altogether, these results support hypothesis
1 and lead us to reject hypothesis 2.</p></sec><sec id="section14-0891243218783670"><title>Gender and Education</title><p>Turning our attention to Model 2, we should first repeat that, as expected
following gendered socialization and gendered interests, women&#x02019;s support for
gender equality overall is far greater than men&#x02019;s, as is the case after taking
religiosity and other factors into account (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0891243218783670">Figure 2</xref>). Thus, women can and do
interpret gender equality differently from men, &#x0201c;even&#x0201d; in patriarchal MENA
countries (<xref rid="bibr11-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Bolzendahl and
Myers 2004</xref>).</p><p>Model 2 furthermore shows that several dimensions of religiosity also are
differently related to support for gender equality for women and men. First,
service attendance is associated with a sharper decline in support for gender
equality among women than among men. As expected, when women do not attend
religious services, they are more supportive of gender equality than men (about
50 vs. 35), but service attendance reduces women&#x02019;s support with (&#x02212;0.56 &#x02212; 0.86)
&#x02212;1.42, while it only reduces men&#x02019;s with &#x02212;0.56. These findings provide support
for hypothesis 3, but only partially, as a similar effect is not found for
textualism. Face-to-face exposure to members of the religious patriarchy voicing
authoritative messages thus probably shrinks spaces for emancipatory
reinterpretations that especially women are initially inclined to use, reducing
the gender gap in support.</p><p>Second and interestingly, religious salience turns out to be negatively related
to support for gender equality among men (&#x02212;1.53), but actually
<italic>increases</italic> support for gender equality among women (&#x02212;1.53 +
2.70 = 1.17), as is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3-0891243218783670">Figure 3</xref>. So, women who are more
affectively attached to their religion support gender equality more, while among
men the stronger believers support gender equality less. We did not find this
for devotion; thus, only partial support is found for hypothesis 4. These
findings illustrate that among women, salience&#x02014;that is, the importance of
religion in daily life&#x02014;is the religiosity dimension that also functions as a
help, not a hurdle, to support for gender equality.</p><fig id="fig3-0891243218783670" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3:</label><caption><p>Gendered Relations between Salience and Support for Gender Equality (N =
19,009)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0891243218783670-fig3"/></fig><p>Relations between several religiosity indicators and support for gender equality
also are moderated by educational attainment. Model 3 first indicates that the
negative impact of religious service attendance strengthens when education
increases. As expected, more highly educated individuals&#x02019; initially more
progressive views are reduced more sharply when they frequently partake in
religious services (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4-0891243218783670">Figure
4</xref>). The same is not found for textualism, however; hypothesis 5 is
thus only partially supported. Model 3 furthermore shows that, among women, the
negative impact of salience, but not devotion, is weakened by education; these
findings support hypothesis 6, but only in one specific case. Overall, Models 2
and 3 suggest that while womanhood and education form a buffer against the
impact of one&#x02019;s own beliefs, socialization via religious services reduces the
room for agentic reinterpretations deviating from societally dominant norms,
diminishing women&#x02019;s and more highly educated citizens&#x02019; initially greater support
for gender equality.</p><fig id="fig4-0891243218783670" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4:</label><caption><p>Religious Service Attendance and Support for Gender Equality per
Education Level (N = 19,009)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0891243218783670-fig4"/></fig></sec><sec id="section15-0891243218783670"><title>Interdependent Religiosity</title><p>Finally, Model 4 shows that salience and devotion weaken the impact of service
attendance and textualism, respectively.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn6-0891243218783670">6</xref></sup> For instance, across the MENA, people who attend services (one standard
deviation) more often show increased opposition to gender equality, with 1.2
points, as compared to citizens for whom religion is averagely salient. All
other things being equal, among individuals for whom religion and God are more
important in their lives (salience) the impact of attending religious services
is only (1.16 &#x02212; 0.42) 0.7. Not all expected interaction effects were found to be
statistically significant, but they were all in the expected direction. These
findings thus provide some support for hypothesis 7; the patriarchal influence
of doctrinal religious beliefs and communal practices seems to be mitigated by
having stronger affective religious beliefs (i.e., salience or devotion). What
is more, all results together pinpoint religious salience as the only dilutor of
service attendance&#x02019;s impact, emphasizing that the influence of exposure to the
institutional religious patriarchy may not be buffered by womanhood or
education, but it is by (affective) religion itself.</p></sec><sec id="section16-0891243218783670"><title>Robustness Tests</title><p>We conducted additional analyses as robustness checks. As mentioned above, we
estimated our models on subsamples (only Muslims, women, and men) and within
individual country-years; divergent results are indicated in <xref rid="table2-0891243218783670" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/0891243218783670">Appendix 2</ext-link>. We also varied the inclusion and operationalization
of the religiosity variables by including respondents with missing scores on
denomination and service attendance (classifying them as a separate group);
additionally distinguishing between the nonreligious and religious non-Muslims;
and including prayer and particularism, although then many cases have to be
excluded from the analyses.<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn7-0891243218783670">7</xref></sup></p><p>Our main results are robust for each of these alternatives. For instance, our
additional measurements of religiosity relate to support for gender equality as
expected, which provides further support for hypothesis 1 in particular (see
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/suppl/10.1177/0891243218783670">online Appendix 3</ext-link>). As individual prayer is not significantly
related to support for gender equality, it seems that it is the actual exposure
to others in services that serves a patriarchal socialization function, and not
practicing religion in and of itself. Moreover, particularism shows a clear
negative relation with support for gender equality, which further supports our
conclusion that adherence to orthodox doctrinal beliefs diminishes support for
gender equality&#x02014;also when the measure is not focused on one particular issue (as
textualism was).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section17-0891243218783670"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study addressed relations between different dimensions of religiosity and
support for gender equality, and how they differed for women and more highly
educated individuals in the Arab MENA. We did so based on a newly developed agentic
and gendered socialization framework, which we tested on data from 15 WVS surveys
from between 2001 and 2014. At its core, the agentic and gendered socialization
framework proposes that while MENA citizens are embedded in dominantly patriarchal
religious structures, they are not solely or uniformly passively socialized by
religiosity, as previous large-scale studies implied (cf. <xref rid="bibr22-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Inglehart and Norris 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr42-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Price 2016</xref>). Instead, the
framework proposes that religious socialization is gendered and that people can
reinterpret their religion and thus actively deviate from patriarchal
interpretations (<xref rid="bibr16-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Elder, Johnson,
and Crosnoe 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr24-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Kandiyoti 1988</xref>; <xref rid="bibr28-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Korteweg 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bibr45-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Rinaldo 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bibr52-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Sewell
1992</xref>).</p><p>This framework implies that a disaggregated, multidimensional conceptualization of
religiosity is needed, instead of focusing on differences between Muslims and
non-Muslims, as previous studies have done (e.g., <xref rid="bibr22-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Inglehart and Norris 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr32-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Lussier and Fish 2016</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr39-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Norris 2009</xref>). This is
because rigid patriarchal religious structures obstruct support for gender equality
while other dimensions of religiosity stimulate emancipatory advancements (see <xref rid="bibr14-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Cornwall et al. 1986</xref>; <xref rid="bibr20-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Hall 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bibr40-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Nyhagen 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bibr58-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Stark and Glock 1968</xref>).
Indeed, our results consistently showed that while religious service attendance,
textualism, and devotion decreased support for gender equality, the salience of
religious beliefs in life choices had no singularly negative impact. Among women we
even found that religious salience <italic>increases</italic> support for gender
equality (cf. <xref rid="bibr49-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Scheepers,
Gijsberts, and Hello 2002</xref>). Moreover, even though religious salience does
not consistently fuel support for gender equality (as was expected), it was the only
moderator in our analyses that buffered the negative impact of exposure to the
institutional patriarchy in religious services. All in all, these findings showed
that most but not all dimensions of religiosity serve patriarchal socialization, and
that using religion as a guideline in daily life is thus the main (or only)
safeguard to the patriarchal influence of exposure to religious institutions.
Translating findings from in-depth qualitative studies, religious salience thus
seems to be the key to reinterpreting religion along more emancipatory lines (e.g.,
<xref rid="bibr4-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Aune 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bibr23-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Jansen 2004</xref>; <xref rid="bibr35-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Mir-Hosseini 2006</xref>).</p><p>At the core of our framework are genderedness and agency. Consequently, we also
proposed that relations between religiosity and support for gender equality vary
between different societal groups. Indeed, religious service attendance was more
strongly negatively related to support for gender equality among women and more
highly educated individuals, as service attendance reduced women&#x02019;s and more highly
educated citizens&#x02019; initially greater support (see <xref rid="bibr31-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Lueptow, Garovich-Szabo, and Lueptow 2001</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr37-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Moghadam 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bibr61-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Zion-Waldoks 2015</xref>). So it
seems that among those who have the space to deviate from dominant patriarchal
interpretations, that is, those exposed less to patriarchal religious institutions,
especially women and more highly educated individuals use that space to
progressively reinterpret their religion (<xref rid="bibr3-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Al-Hibri 1982</xref>; <xref rid="bibr38-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Moghissi 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr43-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Prickett 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bibr44-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Read and Bartkowski 2000</xref>).</p><p>Also, the negative impact of (internal) religious beliefs, particularly religious
salience, was weaker among women and more highly educated individuals. Again it
seems that given the space for renegotiations, women and more highly educated
individuals more often seek or accept emancipatory reinterpretations of their
religion conducive to support for gender equality, as suggested by previous
qualitative studies (<xref rid="bibr7-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Avishai,
Jafar, and Rinaldo 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bibr24-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Kandiyoti 1988</xref>; <xref rid="bibr27-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Khurshid 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bibr43-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Prickett 2015</xref>). Women and more highly
educated citizens thus tend to be at the forefront of renegotiating the
religiosity&#x02013;gender inequality coupling.</p><p>Based on this summary of results, two core contributions of this study to the
literature can be highlighted. First, we have shown that religiosity is a medley.
Previous quantitative studies mainly studied denomination (e.g., <xref rid="bibr2-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Alexander and Welzel 2011</xref>;
<xref rid="bibr22-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Inglehart and Norris
2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr32-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Lussier and
Fish 2016</xref>), while we theorized a more fine-grained and gendered version
of religion&#x02019;s relation to support for gender equality. We showed in greater detail
how (disaggregated) religiosity works and that it is not always a hindrance to
support for gender equality in the MENA. Especially, religious salience (among
women) cushions the blow to support for gender equality of other religiosity
dimensions.</p><p>Second, previous public opinion studies focused on patriarchal socialization,
implying that individuals in the MENA are passive beings (see <xref rid="bibr48-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Said 1979</xref>; <xref rid="bibr57-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Spierings 2015</xref>). This study provided
evidence that people who are more inclined (women) and sociocognitively better
equipped (higher educated) can and do cushion patriarchal interpretations of their
religiosity. Future research would do well to not only consider MENA citizens as
unilaterally passively socialized but also as active agents in a gendered
context.</p><p>Other important avenues for future research can be derived from some of the
challenges we faced, particularly regarding data availability. First, despite taking
considerable steps forward, we were unable to tap into every form of religious
socialization. For instance, no data were available on religious socialization in
schools or parental homes. The socialization processes in these domains may be
similar to religious socialization that our data did cover, but that remains an
empirical question to tackle in future research. Second, panel data provide more
insights into the assumed causality of religious socialization, but such data are
currently unavailable. Consequently, we could not empirically show that women&#x02019;s and
more highly educated citizens&#x02019; support for gender equality is reduced <italic>due
to</italic> service attendance, instead of women and more highly educated
citizens who attended services being more conservative from the start. However,
there are distinct reasons to assume some causality; MENA citizens are embedded in
religious structures by birth, and previous studies have proposed religious
socialization processes are ever-present, implying that religious socialization
predates people forming their opinions on gender equality. Moreover, our models
controlled for core variables linked to religiosity and gender equality attitudes,
such as education (<xref rid="bibr2-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Alexander and
Welzel 2011</xref>; <xref rid="bibr4-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Aune
2015</xref>).</p><p>Third, some indicators of religiosity leave room for improvement. For instance,
textualism could not be measured directly. We expect that other aspects of
textualism would provide similar results&#x02014;an expectation supported by our results
concerning particularism&#x02014;but further empirical study is welcome. Similarly,
regarding salience we had no measures on the importance of religion in
<italic>specific daily</italic> choices (<xref rid="bibr49-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Scheepers, Gijsberts, and Hello 2002</xref>).
However and if anything, most likely this has led to an
<italic>under</italic>estimation of salience&#x02019;s relation to support for gender
equality.</p><p>Finally, we recommend that future researchers look into different domains of support
for gender equality. Although our theory predicts roughly similar patterns, only
empirical study can verify this. The vast majority of large-scale quantitative
studies pertain to public sphere attitudes; studying support for equality in the
private sphere or sexual emancipation would greatly add to our knowledge (e.g.,
<xref rid="bibr22-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Inglehart and Norris
2003</xref>; <xref rid="bibr32-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Lussier and
Fish 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bibr42-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Price
2016</xref>). Current data do not permit this, however. For instance, the WVS
includes an item on the justifiability of divorce, but it is hard to discern whether
men and women filling out the questionnaire had <italic>talaq</italic> or
<italic>khul</italic>&#x02019; in mind&#x02014;men&#x02019;s unilateral right to divorce or divorce that
women can initiate (<xref rid="bibr55-0891243218783670" ref-type="bibr">Shehada
2016</xref>).</p><p>Still, to our knowledge, this study has included more precise and nuanced
measurements of religiosity&#x02019;s impact on gender equality attitudes than any other
MENA study. Studying the multidimensional facets of religiosity, as well as their
interrelated and particularly agency-moderated influences, has provided important
and more nuanced insights into the gendered impact religiosity has on support for
gender equality in the MENA, which is pivotal for women in the MENA as well as for
public debates around the world.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="section18-0891243218783670"><title>Supplemental Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="suppl1-0891243218783670"><caption><title>9129.R2_Online_Appendices_final &#x02013; Supplemental material for
Re-Understanding Religion And Support For Gender Equality In Arab
Countries</title></caption><media xlink:href="Online_Appendices_final.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media><p>Supplemental material, 9129.R2_Online_Appendices_final for Re-Understanding
Religion And Support For Gender Equality In Arab Countries by Saskia Glas, Niels
Spierings and Peer Scheepers in Gender ender &#x00026; Society Society</p></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; Note:</bold>This project was funded by the NWO (406-16-517). We thank three anonymous
reviewers for their insightful feedback.</p></fn></fn-group><notes><fn-group><fn fn-type="other" id="fn1-0891243218783670"><label>1.</label><p>The Quran states, &#x0201c;And no person can ever die except by Allah&#x02019;s leave and at
an appointed time&#x0201d; (3:145, Khan trans.), and Bukhari&#x02019;s Hadith (4.56.669)
reports Allah&#x02019;s response to a man who has taken his own life, &#x0201c;My Slave
hurried to bring death upon himself so I have forbidden him (to enter)
Paradise.&#x0201d;</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn2-0891243218783670"><label>2.</label><p>In our sample, women attended services less than men; still, about one-third
frequents religious services weekly or more.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn3-0891243218783670"><label>3.</label><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldvaluessurvey.org/">http://www.worldvaluessurvey.org/</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn4-0891243218783670"><label>4.</label><p>In the Bahrain 2014 survey, employment and education loaded on two factors.
The pooled analysis showed high factor loadings (0.78 [politics], 0.63
[education], 0.72 [employment]) on one dimension, although Cronbach&#x02019;s alpha
was moderate (0.50), probably because of the number of items.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn5-0891243218783670"><label>5.</label><p><italic>F</italic> tests showed that support&#x02019;s variation over time is
marginal compared to between countries, justifying our data structure. Also,
the much debated minimal number of higher-level units is not very relevant,
as we add no higher-level predictors.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn6-0891243218783670"><label>6.</label><p>The interaction terms largely (just) lose their statistical significance in
the men-only model, but they remain similar in the women-only and
Muslim-only subsamples.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn7-0891243218783670"><label>7.</label><p>Eleven surveys include <italic>frequency of private prayer</italic>. We
standardized scores per survey. Thirteen surveys included
<italic>particularism</italic> as follows: &#x0201c;On this list are various
groups of people. Which would you not like to have as neighbors?&#x0201d; The answer
&#x0201c;from a different religion&#x0201d; is scored 1, others 0. Details can be obtained
from the authors.</p></fn></fn-group></notes><bio id="d35e2302"><p>Saskia Glas is a PhD candidate in sociology at Radboud Social and Cultural Research,
Radboud University (the Netherlands). The project, funded by the NWO, focuses on
religion, support for gender equality, and Muslim feminism in Arab countries. Her
research interests include sociopolitical attitudes, political structures, and
gender equality.</p><p>Niels Spierings is assistant professor in sociology at Radboud Social and Cultural
Research, Radboud University. His expertise includes women&#x02019;s socioeconomic position,
religion, migration, political behavior, and sociopolitical attitudes. Two of his
current projects are funded by NWO and focus on Islamic religiosity and
politcosocial attitudes in Arab countries.</p><p>Peer Scheepers is professor of comparative methodology at Radboud Social and Cultural
Research, Radboud University. He focuses on cross-national research on social
cohesion (e.g., religiosity), on which he has published widely (H-index=48). He is
member of the Royal Dutch Academy of Arts and Sciences and of Academia Europeae.</p></bio><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abu-Lughod</surname><given-names>Lila</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Do Muslim women really need
saving? Anthropological reflections on cultural relativism and its
others</article-title>. <source>American Anthropologist</source>
<volume>104</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>783</fpage>-90.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>Amy</given-names></name><name><surname>Welzel</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Islam and patriarchy: How
robust is Muslim support for patriarchal values?</article-title>
<source>International Review of Sociology</source>
<volume>21</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>249</fpage>-76.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Hibri</surname><given-names>Azizah</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1982</year>
<source>Women and Islam</source>.
<publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Pergamon</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aune</surname><given-names>Kristin</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Feminist spirituality as
lived religion: How UK feminists forge religio-spiritual
lives</article-title>. <source>Gender &#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>29</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>122</fpage>-45.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avishai</surname><given-names>Orit</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>&#x0201c;Doing religion&#x0201d; in a secular
world: Women in conservative religions and the question of
agency</article-title>. <source>Gender &#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>22</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>409</fpage>-33.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avishai</surname><given-names>Orit</given-names></name><name><surname>Irby</surname><given-names>Courtney</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Bifurcated conversations in
sociological studies of religion and gender</article-title>. <source>Gender
&#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>31</volume> (<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>647</fpage>-76.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avishai</surname><given-names>Orit</given-names></name><name><surname>Jafar</surname><given-names>Afshan</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinaldo</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>A gender lens on
religion</article-title>. <source>Gender &#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>29</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>5</fpage>-<lpage>25</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartkowski</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>Jen&#x02019;nan</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Veiled submission: Gender,
power, and identity among evangelical and Muslim women in the United
States</article-title>. <source>Qualitative Sociology</source>
<volume>26</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>71</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blaydes</surname><given-names>Lisa</given-names></name><name><surname>Linzer</surname><given-names>Drew</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The political economy of
women&#x02019;s support for fundamentalist Islam</article-title>. <source>World
Politics</source>
<volume>60</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>576</fpage>-<lpage>609</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>Pazit</given-names></name><name><surname>Arikan</surname><given-names>Gizem</given-names></name><name><surname>Courtemanche</surname><given-names>Marie</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Religious social identity,
religious belief, and anti-immigration sentiment</article-title>.
<source>American Political Science Review</source>
<volume>109</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>203</fpage>-21.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolzendahl</surname><given-names>Catherine</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Feminist attitudes and
support for gender equality: Opinion change in women and men,
1974-1998</article-title>. <source>Social Forces</source>
<volume>83</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>759</fpage>-90.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charrad</surname><given-names>Mounira</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Gender in the Middle East:
Islam, state, agency</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of
Sociology</source>
<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>-37.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>Kelly</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Negotiating patriarchy: South
Korean evangelical women and the politics of gender</article-title>.
<source>Gender &#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>20</volume> (<issue>6</issue>):
<fpage>697</fpage>-<lpage>724</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornwall</surname><given-names>Marie</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>Stan</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>Perry</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitcher</surname><given-names>Brian</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>The dimensions of
religiosity: A conceptual model with an empirical test</article-title>.
<source>Review of Religious Research</source>
<volume>27</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>226</fpage>-44.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eagly</surname><given-names>Alice</given-names></name><name><surname>Diekman</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name><name><surname>Johannesen-Schmidt</surname><given-names>Mary</given-names></name><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Gender gaps in sociopolitical
attitudes: A social psychological analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal
of Personality and Social Psychology</source>
<volume>87</volume> (<issue>6</issue>):
<fpage>796</fpage>-<lpage>816</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15598107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elder</surname><given-names>Glen</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Monica</given-names></name><name><surname>Crosnoe</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The emergence and development
of life course theory</article-title>. In <source>Handbook of the life
course</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Mortimer</surname><given-names>Jeylan</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanahan</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name></person-group>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kluwer
Academic</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Fadl</surname><given-names>Khaled</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<source>Speaking in God&#x02019;s name. Islamic law,
authority and women</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>One World</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>Marie</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<source>God&#x02019;s daughters: Evangelical women
and the power of submission</source>.
<publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of
California Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>Alessandra</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Measuring religiosity in a
majority Muslim context: Gender, religious salience, and religious
experience among Kuwaiti college students&#x02014;A research note</article-title>.
<source>Journal for the Scientific Study of Religion</source>
<volume>50</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>339</fpage>-50.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<source>Lived religion in America: Toward a
history of practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Princeton University
Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hervieu-L&#x000e9;ger</surname><given-names>Dani&#x000e8;le</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>The transmission and
formation of socioreligious identities in modernity: An analytical essay on
the trajectories of identification</article-title>. <source>International
Sociology</source>
<volume>13</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>213</fpage>-28.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inglehart</surname><given-names>Ronald</given-names></name><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>Pippa</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>The true clash of
civilizations</article-title>. <source>Foreign Policy</source>
<volume>135</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>Willy</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>The economy of religious
merit: Women and ajr in Algeria</article-title>. <source>Journal of North
African Studies</source>
<volume>9</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kandiyoti</surname><given-names>Deniz</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1988</year>
<article-title>Bargaining with
patriarchy</article-title>. <source>Gender &#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>2</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>274</fpage>-90.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kellstedt</surname><given-names>Lyman</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><name><surname>Guth</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name><name><surname>Smidt</surname><given-names>Corwin</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Grasping the essentials: The
social embodiment of religion and political behavior</article-title>. In
<source>Religion and the culture wars: Dispatches from the front</source>,
edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name></person-group>
<publisher-loc>Lanham, MD</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Rowman &#x00026; Littlefield</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Al-Hilali</given-names></name><name><surname>Taqi-ud-Din</surname><given-names>Muhammad</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<source>The Noble Quran</source>.
<publisher-name>Muslim directory</publisher-name>, <month>5</month>
<day>8</day>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.noorehidayat.org">http://www.noorehidayat.org</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khurshid</surname><given-names>Ayesha</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Islamic traditions of
modernity: Gender, class, and Islam in a transnational women&#x02019;s education
project</article-title>. <source>Gender &#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>29</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>98</fpage>-<lpage>121</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korteweg</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>The sharia debate in Ontario:
Gender, Islam, and representations of Muslim women&#x02019;s agency</article-title>.
<source>Gender &#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>22</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>434</fpage>-54.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kostenko</surname><given-names>Veronica</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuzmuchev</surname><given-names>Pavel</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponarin</surname><given-names>Eduard</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Attitudes towards gender
equality and perception of democracy in the Arab world</article-title>.
<source>Democratization</source>
<volume>23</volume> (<issue>5</issue>):
<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kucinskas</surname><given-names>Jaime</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>A research note on Islam and
gender egalitarianism: An examination of Egyptian and Saudi Arabian youth
attitudes</article-title>. <source>Journal for the Scientific Study of
Religion</source>
<volume>49</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>761</fpage>-70.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lueptow</surname><given-names>Lloyd</given-names></name><name><surname>Garovich-Szabo</surname><given-names>Lori</given-names></name><name><surname>Lueptow</surname><given-names>Margaret</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Social change and the
persistence of sex typing: 1974-1997</article-title>. <source>Social
Forces</source>
<volume>80</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lussier</surname><given-names>Danielle</given-names></name><name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>Steven</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Men, Muslims, and attitudes
toward gender inequality</article-title>. <source>Politics and
Religion</source>
<volume>9</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>Saba</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<source>Politics of piety: The Islamic
revival and the feminist subject</source>. <publisher-loc>Princeton,
NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Princeton University
Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masoud</surname><given-names>Tarek</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamal</surname><given-names>Amaney</given-names></name><name><surname>Nugent</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Using the Qur&#x02019;&#x00101;n to empower
Arab women? Theory and experimental evidence from Egypt</article-title>.
<source>Comparative Political Studies</source>
<volume>49</volume> (<issue>12</issue>):
<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>44</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mir-Hosseini</surname><given-names>Ziba</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Muslim women&#x02019;s quest for
equality: Between Islamic law and feminism</article-title>. <source>Critical
Inquiry</source>
<volume>32</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>629</fpage>-45.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moaddel</surname><given-names>Mansoor</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>The Saudi public speaks:
Religion, gender, and politics</article-title>. <source>International
Journal of Middle East Studies</source>
<volume>38</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>79</fpage>-<lpage>108</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moghadam</surname><given-names>Valentine</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<source>Modernizing women: Gender and social
change in the Middle East</source>, <edition>3rd ed.</edition>
<publisher-loc>Boulder, CO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lynne
Rienner</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moghissi</surname><given-names>Haideh</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Islamic feminism
revisited</article-title>. <source>Comparative Studies of South Asia, Africa
and the Middle East</source>
<volume>31</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>76</fpage>-<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>Pippa</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Why do Arab states lag the
world in gender equality? HKS faculty research working paper series RWP09-
020</article-title>. <publisher-name>John F. Kennedy School of Government,
Harvard University</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge,
MA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyhagen</surname><given-names>Line</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>The lived religion approach
in the sociology of religion and its implications for secular feminist
analyses of religion</article-title>. <source>Social Compass</source>
<volume>64</volume> (<issue>4</issue>):
<fpage>495</fpage>-<lpage>511</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr41-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paxton</surname><given-names>Pamela</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunovich</surname><given-names>Sheri</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>Melanie</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Gender in
politics</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Sociology</source>
<volume>33</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>-84.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr42-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>Anne</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>How national structures shape
attitudes toward women&#x02019;s right to employment in the Middle
East</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Comparative
Sociology</source>
<volume>56</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>408</fpage>-32.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr43-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prickett</surname><given-names>Pamela</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Negotiating gendered
religious space: The particularities of patriarchy in an African American
mosque</article-title>. <source>Gender &#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>29</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>51</fpage>-<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr44-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>Jen&#x02019;nan</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartkowski</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>To veil or not to veil? A
case study of identity negotiation among Muslim women in Austin,
Texas</article-title>. <source>Gender &#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>14</volume> (<issue>3</issue>):
<fpage>395</fpage>-<lpage>417</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr45-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinaldo</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Pious and critical: Muslim
women activists and the question of agency</article-title>. <source>Gender
&#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>28</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>824</fpage>-46.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr46-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>Helen</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Latif</surname><given-names>Abdel-Hamid</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>Katherine</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The relationship between
gender equality and democracy: A comparison of Arab versus non-Arab Muslim
societies</article-title>. <source>Sociology</source>
<volume>41</volume> (<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1151</fpage>-70.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr47-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>Helen</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>Katherine</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>Yousef</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Extending political rights in
the Middle East: The case of Kuwait</article-title>. <source>Journal of
Political and Military Sociology</source>
<volume>35</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>177</fpage>-97.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr48-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Said</surname><given-names>Edward</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1979</year>
<source>Orientalism</source>.
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Vintage</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr49-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheepers</surname><given-names>Peer</given-names></name><name><surname>Gijsberts</surname><given-names>M&#x000e8;rove</given-names></name><name><surname>Hello</surname><given-names>Evelyn</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Religiosity and prejudice
against ethnic minorities in Europe: Cross-national tests on a controversial
relationship</article-title>. <source>Review of Religious Research</source>
<volume>43</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>242</fpage>-65.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr50-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>Shalom</given-names></name><name><surname>Huismans</surname><given-names>Sipke</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Value priorities and
religiosity in four western religions</article-title>. <source>Social
Psychology Quarterly</source>
<volume>58</volume> (<issue>2</issue>):
<fpage>88</fpage>-<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr51-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selim</surname><given-names>Nahed</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<source>De vrouwen van de profeet: Hoe vrouw
(on)vriendelijk is de Koran?</source>
<publisher-loc>Amsterdam, NL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Van
Gennep</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr52-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sewell</surname><given-names>William</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>A theory of structure:
Duality, agency, and transformation</article-title>. <source>American
Journal of Sociology</source>
<volume>98</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr53-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shamaileh</surname><given-names>Ammar</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Am I equal? Internet access
and perceptions of female political leadership ability in the Arab
World</article-title>. <source>Journal of Information Technology &#x00026;
Politics</source>
<volume>13</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>257</fpage>-71.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr54-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>Gilla</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Abortion law in
Muslim-majority countries: An overview of the Islamic discourse with policy
implications</article-title>. <source>Health Policy and Planning</source>
<volume>29</volume> (<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>483</fpage>-94.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr55-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shehada</surname><given-names>Nahda</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The asymmetrical
representation of gender in Islamic family law</article-title>. In
<source>Women, law and culture</source>, edited by <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Scutt</surname><given-names>Jocelynne A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave
Macmillan</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr56-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spierings</surname><given-names>Niels</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Islamic attitudes and the
support for gender equality and democracy in seven Arab countries, and the
role of anti-Western feelings</article-title>. <source>Multidisciplinary
Journal of Gender Studies</source>
<volume>3</volume> (<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>423</fpage>-56.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr57-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spierings</surname><given-names>Niels</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<source>Women&#x02019;s employment in Muslim
countries: Patterns of diversity</source>. <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Palgrave
Macmillan</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr58-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>Rodney</given-names></name><name><surname>Glock</surname><given-names>Charles</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1968</year>
<source>American piety: The nature of
religious commitment</source>. <publisher-loc>Oakland</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>University of California
Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr59-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sumerau</surname><given-names>J. Edward</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>&#x0201c;That&#x02019;s what a man is
supposed to do&#x0201d;: Compensatory manhood acts in an LGBT Christian
church</article-title>. <source>Gender &#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>26</volume> (<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>461</fpage>-87.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr60-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van de Vijver</surname><given-names>Fons</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>Kwok</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<source>Methods and data analysis for
cross-cultural research</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr61-0891243218783670"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zion-Waldoks</surname><given-names>Tanya</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Politics of devoted
resistance: Agency, feminism, and religion among Orthodox Agunah activists
in Israel</article-title>. <source>Gender &#x00026; Society</source>
<volume>29</volume> (<issue>1</issue>):
<fpage>73</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>