<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mem. Inst. Oswaldo Cruz</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">mioc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Mem&#x000f3;rias do Instituto Oswaldo Cruz</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0074-0276</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1678-8060</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Instituto Oswaldo Cruz, Minist&#x000e9;rio da Sa&#x000fa;de</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4727438</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0074-02760150386</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The dynamics of Brazilian protozoology over the past
century</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M Carolina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c01">
<sup>+</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Floeter-Winter</surname><given-names>Lucile M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mena-Chalco</surname><given-names>Jesus P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Instituto Butantan, Laborat&#x000f3;rio Especial de Ciclo Celular, S&#x000e3;o Paulo,
SP, Brasil</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Instituto Butantan, Centro de Toxinas, Resposta-Imune e Sinaliza&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o
Celular, S&#x000e3;o Paulo, SP, Brasil</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Universidade de S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Instituto de Bioci&#x000ea;ncias, Departamento de
Fisiologia, S&#x000e3;o Paulo, SP, Brasil</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Universidade Federal do ABC, Centro de Matem&#x000e1;tica, Computa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o e
Cogni&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o, Santo Andr&#x000e9;, SP, Brasil</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c01"><label>+</label> Corresponding
author:<email>carolina.eliassabbaga@butantan.gov.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' --><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>111</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly
cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Brazilian scientists have been contributing to the protozoology field for more than
100 years with important discoveries of new species such as<italic>Trypanosoma
cruzi</italic> and <italic>Leishmania</italic> spp. In this work, we used a
Brazilian thesis database (Coordination for the Improvement of Higher Education
Personnel) covering the period from 1987-2011 to identify researchers who contributed
substantially to protozoology. We selected 248 advisors by filtering to obtain
researchers who supervised at least 10 theses. Based on a computational analysis of
the thesis databases, we found students who were supervised by these scientists. A
computational procedure was developed to determine the advisors&#x02019; scientific ancestors
using the Lattes Platform. These analyses provided a list of 1,997 researchers who
were inspected through Lattes CV examination and allowed the identification of the
pioneers of Brazilian protozoology. Moreover, we investigated the areas in which
researchers who earned PhDs in protozoology are now working. We found that 68.4% of
them are still in protozoology, while 16.7% have migrated to other fields. We
observed that support for protozoology by national or international agencies is
clearly correlated with the increase of scientists in the field. Finally, we
described the academic genealogy of Brazilian protozoology by formalising the
&#x0201c;forest&#x0201d; of Brazilian scientists involved in the study of protozoa and their vectors
over the past century.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>protozoology</kwd><kwd>pioneers</kwd><kwd>academic genealogy</kwd><kwd>scientific mapping method</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="5"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="36"/><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>The last decade of the XIX century is considered to be the period in which experimental
protozoology began (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Calkins 1911</xref>). At that time,
protozoa were suspected of being the causative agents of only two human diseases: dysentery
and malaria (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Calkins 1911</xref>). Currently, protozoan
parasites are recognised as the causative agents of some of most important human illnesses.
For instance, amebiasis is the second leading cause of death due to parasitic diseases
worldwide and causes approximately 40-100,000 deaths per year (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">Moraes et al. 2015</xref>). Approximately 6.5 million people are estimated to
be infected with <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>, 1,300,000 new cases of leishmaniasis
occur every year, and 214 million new cases of malaria have occurred in 2015 alone.
Toxoplasmosis and giardiasis are also diseases caused by protozoa, both of which represent
significant public health threats (who.int). These are examples of protozoa that are of
medical interest and do not include protozoa of veterinary interest or free-living
protozoa, which may be important environmental markers.</p><p>Therefore, protozoology has become a unique field of study, and an impressive amount of
work has gone into detailing the biological aspects of this subject. Indeed, the study of
protozoa has rapidly evolved from the molecular characterisation of eukaryotes through
host-parasite interactions and ecoepidemiological aspects to therapeutic interventions.
Several important mechanisms were first described in protozoa, such as nonconventional RNA
polymerase II promoter sites (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Clayton 2002</xref>),
<italic>trans</italic>-splicing (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">Mayer &#x00026;
Floeter-Winter 2012</xref>) and RNA editing (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">Simpson et
al. 2006)</xref>. Some of these findings have been highly influential in other medical
and biological fields, such as the discovery of telomeres protecting chromosomes in
<italic>Tetrahymena</italic> (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">Blackburn &#x00026; Gall
1978)</xref>, the understanding of glycosylphosphatidylinositol protein anchor
structures (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson et al. 1985</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson 1999)</xref>, and the delineation of the respective
roles of the T-helper (Th)1 and Th2 lymphocyte subsets against infectious agents in studies
using <italic>Leishmania major</italic>-infected mice (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">Heinzel et al. 1989)</xref>.</p><p>In Brazil, where some protozoan infections are endemic, these aetiological agents and their
vectors have attracted considerable interest from researchers and students. A few &#x0201c;founding
fathers&#x0201d; (pioneers) of this field of science have nurtured later generations of
protozoologists, resulting in the development of a solid network of 100 years of
scientists.</p><p>The evolution of science is the pillar that provides a solid foundation for the development
of society by creating the means to face the challenges ahead (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">Cordova et al. 2015</xref>). The study of the origin of a scientific area and
the identification of the motives behind its development in new disciplines provide
important contributions to the understanding of future needs. This academic genealogy
allows the development of qualifying studies based on the training of new researchers.</p><p>Academic genealogy was defined by <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Sugimoto (2014)</xref>as
a quantitative study of the intellectual heritage perpetuated through academic orientation
relationships among professors (i.e., mentors or supervisors) and their students. Various
questions can be answered by building an academic genealogy. <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">Sugimoto (2014)</xref> proposed five types of academic genealogies: honorific,
egotistical, historical, paradigmatic, and analytical. These categories are not mutually
exclusive, and most academic genealogies can be classified into at least two of these
types.</p><p>In this work, we followed the development of protozoology in Brazil using a historical and
paradigmatic approach. Systematic data collection was performed through the analysis of
formal thesis orientation and was organised to create a chain of mentorships, resulting in
the construction of our academic genealogy.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>In this work, the identification of researchers associated with protozoology who
influenced (supervised) other researchers over a 100 year timespan was performed through
seven processes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig. 1</xref>). The methodology was
based on the analysis of two sources of Brazilian academic information that allowed the
tracing of scholarly interactions among researchers.</p><p>
<fig id="f01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>: diagram of the tracking of Brazilian protozoologists. Each block
represents a process and each arrow represents the information flow between
processes.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0074-0276-mioc-111-1-0067-gf01"/></fig>
</p><p>
<italic>Process 1 - Identification of dissertations and theses related to protozoology
-</italic> A local repository extracted from the Coordination for the Improvement of
Higher Education Personnel (CAPES) thesis database (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Mena-Chalco &#x00026; Rocha 2014</xref>) was used in this process. We identified 10,456
dissertations or theses with at least one descriptor related to protozoology
(Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app01">Table I</xref>). This quantity
represented 1.7% of the 607,389 dissertations or theses registered in the local
repository.</p><p>
<italic>Process 2 - Identification of supervisors of Masters and PhD students in
protozoology</italic> - In this process, we extracted all supervisors&#x02019; names from the
dissertations/theses identified in process 1. The process handled incomplete or similar
names using approximate string matching. Two names were considered the same/similar if
the Levenshtein distance (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">Levenshtein 1966</xref>)
between them was equal to 2. This process allowed us to identify 4,176 researchers
related to the protozoology field.</p><p>
<italic>Process 3 - Identification of representative protozoologists in terms of the
quantity of supervisions registered in the CAPES thesis database</italic> - In this
process, researchers who supervised at least 10 projects were selected to generate a
list of 248 supervisors (6% of 4,176 researchers). This threshold was considered
suitable for manual inspection. Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app02">Table
II</xref> presents the complete list of names obtained through this process.</p><p>
<italic>Process 4 - Identification of ancestors of the representative
protozoologists</italic> - This process was performed recursively for each supervisor
identified in the Lattes Platform. First, the name of the supervisor was identified and
associated with its Lattes CV. Then, the same approach was undertaken for the
supervisors of the supervisors until the inability to identify a new supervisor was
reached. We identified 445 researchers as the ancestors of the 248 representative
protozoologists.</p><p>
<italic>Process 5 - Identification of the descendants of the representative
protozoologists</italic> - This process was accomplished by selecting the PhD
students (process 1) who were supervised by the researchers obtained in process 3. We
identified 1,335 direct descendants from the group of 248 representative
protozoologists.</p><p>
<italic>Process 6 - Construction of a scientist network -</italic> In this process, the
researchers identified in processes 3, 4 and 5 were used to generate a supervisor
network (i.e., a directed graph where each node represented a researcher, and the edge
represented the relationship between 2 researchers). Duplicated names were processed
manually. A list of 1,997 complete names was generated as the result of this process
(Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app03">Table III</xref>).</p><p>
<italic>Process 7 - Classification of protozoologists -</italic> This process was
performed by manual inspection of each researcher identified in the previous process.
Information from the protozoology field was associated with each of the 1,997
researchers using the Lattes Platform and academic repositories.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><p>
<italic>Identification of scientists actively working in protozoology</italic> - This
work aims to understand the past and present of Brazilian protozoology and the migration
of scientists from protozoology to other fields and from other fields to protozoology.
Academic dissertations and theses are an important source of information concerning the
growth and evolution of science (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">Andersen &#x00026;
Hammarfelt 2011</xref>). Therefore, we accessed a data collection containing most of
the Brazilian protozoologists from the CAPES database combined with the Lattes
examination. By searching for the supervisors of actively working protozoologists, the
supervisors of these supervisors, and so on, we identified the pioneers of this field in
Brazil. Similarly, by searching for students trained by these actively working
protozoologists, we identified other people currently working in the field. To establish
the names of actively working protozoologists to nucleate our search, we prepared a set
of 60 words (descriptors) (Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app01">Table
I</xref>) for use as keywords to screen theses (Masters or PhD) present in the local
CAPES thesis database, which contained all theses completed in Brazil from 1987-2011
(<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Mena-Chalco &#x00026; Rocha 2014)</xref>. A total of
10,456 Masters or PhD theses contained at least one such descriptor. This number
corresponded to 1.7% of the total theses presented in the same period throughout all
fields. A total of 4,176 researchers supervised these 10,456 dissertations/theses. As
expected, the number of scientists diminished when we increased the number of works
supervised per researcher (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02">Fig. 2</xref>). For
operational reasons, it might not be possible to analyse in detail all the 4,176
researchers (advisors) and the relevant factors considered in the adopted methodology.
Therefore, only researchers with at least 10 dissertations/theses supervised in the
field of protozoology were considered in our study (248 scientists) (Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app02">Table II</xref>). With a threshold of five or two
dissertations, for instance, the number of researchers increases by 276% (689
researchers) or 745% (1,864 researchers), respectively. With the threshold adopted,
important pioneers in the field of protozoology are included in the analyses, but we
recognise that this empirical value might penalise early career researchers. However, we
believe that this arbitrarily selected threshold of 10 dissertations/theses was
appropriate to define a selected group of representative researchers. A total of 36% of
these researchers are or were members of the Brazilian Society of Protozoology in the
period between 2000-2015.</p><p>
<fig id="f02" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>: relationship between the number of supervisors and number of theses
generated from 1987-2011 containing at least one descriptor. Supplementary
Table I containing 60 descriptors was used to screen the Coordination for the
Improvement of Higher Education Personnel database. The graph indicates how
many scientists supervised a different number of theses containing at least one
descriptor as a keyword.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0074-0276-mioc-111-1-0067-gf02"/></fig>
</p><p>
<italic>Identification of Brazilian protozoologists</italic> - We used the complete list
of names in Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app02">Table II</xref> as a starting
point to search for the people supervised by these people and <italic>vice
versa</italic> (i.e., scientists who supervised these people). Using automated
analysis of the local CAPES thesis database, we found students whom these researchers
supervised (descendants). We did not search for students of these students because some
of them were still settling, which could compromise our analysis. Based on the automated
analysis of their Lattes CVs, we could also follow the advisors&#x02019; ancestors by searching
for their supervisors and the supervisors of these supervisors available on the Lattes
CV database (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01">Fig. 1</xref>). As shown below, the analyses
also allowed the identification of Brazilian supervisors who worked outside of
protozoology and supervisors that were from other countries; thus, we could identify the
seeds of Brazilian protozoology. These analyses provided a list of 1,997 names that were
manually inspected through the Lattes CV examination, following the pathway shown
in<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Fig. 3A</xref>. We used the following criteria to
establish that a researcher is/was working in the field of protozoology. Researchers
studying the biology of protozoa or protozoa-host interaction were considered
protozoologists. Additionally, scientists investigating protozoa vectors were considered
protozoologists. In contrast, researchers working with protozoa but investigating the
clinical aspects of diseases (e.g., mostly ophthalmologists, dermatologists, and
cardiologists who study diseases caused by protozoa) were not considered
protozoologists. From the total of 1,997 names found, some were not included in the
Lattes database. This discrepancy might have occurred for four different reasons: (i)
misspelling of names, (ii) people who are no longer in science, (iii) foreign
supervisors, and (iv) people who worked in protozoology before the Lattes CV was
created. To include this last group in our analysis, we searched for these people in the
CAPES database or in public repositories to identify their ancestors and the field in
which they worked. To include supervisors from other countries, we searched for these
people in PubMed to verify the field in which they work/worked. Finally, 10.86% of the
1,997 names could not be found in either the Lattes Platform, CAPES database, or public
repositories and were removed from the forward analyses. These analyses allowed the
classification of researchers into five different categories: (a) scientists who are
working or previously worked in protozoology in Brazil, (b) scientists working in
protozoology outside of Brazil who were advisors of Brazilians, (c) scientists who did
not work in protozoology during their PhD and did not establish a research interest in
this field but were advisors of scientists who migrated to protozoology, (d) people who
obtained their PhD in protozoology but were now involved in activities other than
science, and (e) scientists who developed their PhD in protozoology but established a
research interest in another field (Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app03">Table
III</xref>). The frequency of each group is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03">Fig. 3B</xref>. Based on the data, 907 names were identified as Brazilian
protozoologists (classified as group a).</p><p>
<fig id="f03" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>: classification of scientists according to Lattes CV. A: pathway followed
during inspection with Lattes CV; B: frequency of each category described in A;
a: scientists working or who worked in the past in protozoology in Brazil; b:
scientists working in protozoology outside of Brazil that were advisors of
Brazilians; c: scientists that did not work in protozoology during their PhD or
establish a research interest in this field but were advisors of scientists
that migrated to protozoology; d: persons who developed their PhD in
protozoology but are now involved in activities other than science; e:
scientists who developed their PhD in protozoology but established research in
another field.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0074-0276-mioc-111-1-0067-gf03"/></fig>
</p><p>
<italic>Identification of Brazilian protozoology pioneers</italic> - To identify
researchers who were Brazilian protozoology pioneers, we first assumed that people who
were awarded a PhD in protozoology in Brazil were not pioneers but that the pioneers
would be their advisors. Therefore, we concluded that the pioneers were among the
scientists who were awarded PhD degrees in other fields and then migrated to
protozoology or people who were awarded PhDs in protozoology outside Brazil and then
came to our country to establish a group here. Among the researchers classified as group
a (Brazilian protozoologists), we manually searched the Lattes CV and the CAPES database
for ones who were (766) and were not (141) awarded a PhD in protozoology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04">Fig. 4</xref>, Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app04">Table IV</xref>). Additionally, we searched the Lattes CV for researchers
who were awarded a PhD in protozoology outside Brazil (15) (Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app05">Table V</xref>, in bold). Then, we determined in what year
these researchers who did not receive a PhD in protozoology (141 names) or who received
a PhD outside Brazil (15 names; a total of 156 names) established a protozoology group
in Brazil. For scientists who arrived from other fields, we searched the Lattes CV for
the year of their first paper published in protozoology (Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app05">Table V</xref>). For scientists who received their PhD
outside of Brazil, we searched the Lattes CV for the year in which they published their
first paper after their PhD from a position in Brazil (Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app05">Table V</xref>, in bold). Carlos Chagas&#x02019;s paper describing
<italic>T. cruzi</italic> was not found in PubMed but was considered due to its
relevancy. Using this date as the year the scientist entered Brazilian protozoology, we
plotted a graph of this incoming year for each of the 156 scientists who arrived in
protozoology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Fig. 5A</xref>). Additionally, we plotted a
graph showing the frequency of this influx according to the year of migration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Fig. 5B</xref>). From both analyses, it was clear that there
were three waves of immigration into Brazilian protozoology: (i) up to and including
1974, (ii) between 1978-1993, and (iii) between 1998-2013. However, the drop observed
after 2013 might be artificial because the collection of data is recent. Thus, we
concluded that the pioneers (i.e., founders or precursors) of Brazilian protozoology
were the 20 scientists who migrated into the field up to 1974: Carlos Chagas, Samuel
Pessoa, Hertha Meyer, Zigman Brener, Wladimir Lobato Paraense, Leonidas Deane, Maria von
Paumgartten Deane, Amilcar Viana Martins, Jos&#x000e9; Rodrigues da Silva, Washington Luiz
Tafuri, Erney Felicio Plessmann de Camargo, Jayme Neves, Alu&#x000ed;zio Prata, Thales de Brito,
Astolpho Ferraz de Siqueira, Jeffrey Jon Shaw, Mario Endsfeldez Camargo, Isaac Roitman,
Raymundo Martins de Castro, and Walter Colli.</p><p>
<fig id="f04" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>: analysis of fields where scientists classified as developed their PhD.
Scientists classified in category &#x0201c;PhD in protozoology&#x0201d; were divided into those
who developed and those who did not develop PhDs in protozoology.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0074-0276-mioc-111-1-0067-gf04"/></fig>
</p><p>
<fig id="f05" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>: incoming scientists into protozoology. A: the graph shows the year in
which each researcher who did not develop a PhD in protozoology published their
first paper in this field. Red dots indicate the year that scientists who
developed a PhD in protozoology outside of Brazil published their first paper
in Brazil after their PhD; B: frequency of scientists immigrating into
Brazilian protozoology according to the year of arrival.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0074-0276-mioc-111-1-0067-gf05"/></fig>
</p><p>
<italic>Migration of protozoology into Brazilian science</italic> - We also investigated
the immigration and emigration of scientists to and from Brazilian protozoology. A total
of 17.1% of the studied researchers immigrated into protozoology, based on the number of
people who entered protozoology from other fields and arrived from protozoology outside
of Brazil (156 names/907 total). Researchers who stayed in protozoology after their PhD
corresponded to 68.4% of individuals, based on the 770 protozoologists who received a
PhD in protozoology and were still acting as protozoologists, those who received a PhD
in protozoology and were involved in other activities but still involved in science
[group d: 167 (Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app03">Table III</xref>)], and
those who received a PhD in protozoology and established a group in another field [group
e: 188 (Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app03">Table III</xref>)]. Finally, we
determined the percentage of people who left Brazilian protozoology to contribute to
other fields of Brazilian science. To obtain this number, we divided the number of
people classified as group e in Supplementary <xref ref-type="app" rid="app03">Table
III</xref> (188) by the total number who received a PhD in protozoology. This
analysis demonstrated that protozoology provided 16.7% of its PhDs to other fields of
science.</p><p>
<italic>Academic genealogy of Brazilian protozoologists</italic> - Finally, we
constructed an academic genealogy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Fig. 6</xref>) that
included all names classified as protozoologists to reflect the scenario of protozoology
in Brazil. The resulting structure is a forest containing one tree for each scientist
who entered Brazilian protozoology. A detailed view of this academic genealogy is
available from professor.ufabc.edu.br/~jesus.mena/brazilian-protozoology-scenario/. It
is clear that protozoology expanded in the mid-1970s. It is also clear that protozoology
today consists of the descendants of the pioneers as well as other scientists who
migrated to protozoology and supervised their students in this field.</p><p>
<fig id="f06" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>: academic genealogy of Brazilian protozoology protozoologists (group a in
Fig. 3) were included in this graph. Each circle represents one researcher and
lines represent student-supervisor relationships. Persons identified as
pioneers are shown in red, persons directly influenced by pioneers (students or
students of their students) are shown in blue, and persons who arrived in
protozoology after the pioneers and their descendants are shown in green. The
x-axis shows the year of the conclusion of the PhD in protozoology or, for
those who did not receive a PhD in protozoology, the year that they migrated to
protozoology.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0074-0276-mioc-111-1-0067-gf06"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The analysis of the dynamics of Brazilian protozoology over the past century based on
database searches from 1987-2011 allowed us to track and identify scientists who made
important contributions by acting as the pioneers of this field. Moreover, we could
determine the percentage of scientists immigrating to protozoology as well as the
percentage of scientists who were supervised in protozoology but established a research
group in another field. The field of Brazilian protozoology comprises at least 907
researchers. Certainly, there are other protozoologists who were not covered by our
criteria and therefore were not included in our analysis. The interesting result is that
a large number of people working in this field are the result of the efforts of 20
pioneers who introduced protozoa as biological models or drug targets in the period
between 1909-1974. In a seminal paper published in<italic>Mem&#x000f3;rias do Instituto Oswaldo
Cruz</italic>, Carlos Chagas described<italic>T. cruzi</italic> and thereby
introduced the study of protozoology in Brazil (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">Chagas
1909</xref>). Surprisingly, no descendants were identified for Carlos Chagas,
probably because his descendants were clinical doctors and therefore were not classified
as protozoologists according to the criteria used in this study. However, Carlos
Chagas&#x02019;s work at the beginning of the previous century was so complete in showing the
causal agent of a disease and its relationship to an insect vector that it still
inspires researchers today.</p><p>In the 1940s, Samuel Pessoa inaugurated his huge contribution to the field by studying
the behaviour of <italic>Leishmania</italic> in tissues (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">Pessoa &#x00026; Barreto 1945</xref>) and the geographic distribution of phlebotomines
(<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">Barreto &#x00026; Pessoa 1946)</xref>. Hertha Meyer
published on <italic>T. cruzi</italic> cultivation (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">Meyer &#x00026; de Oliveira 1948</xref>); this field of study evolved to include her
contribution regarding the structural analysis of this organism. In the 1950s, the study
of protozoa in Brazil expanded with Amilcar Viana Martins, Leonidas Deane, and Maria
Deane, who investigated the epidemiology of leishmaniasis (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">Deane &#x00026; Deane 1954</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Martins et
al. 1956)</xref>, Zigman Brener and Washington Luiz Tafuri, who contributed to our
understanding of Chagas disease (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">Brener 1952</xref>, de
<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">Queiroz &#x00026; Tafuri 1957)</xref>, Jos&#x000e9; Rodrigues da
Silva, who investigated hepatic problems related to <italic>Leishmania</italic> and
amoeba infections (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">da Silva &#x00026; de Paola 1957</xref>,
da<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">Silva &#x00026; Torres 1957)</xref>, and Wladimir
Lobato Paraense, who was interested in <italic>Plasmodium</italic> (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">Paraense 1952)</xref>. Then, over the next two decades, a
new group of scientists migrated into protozoology. Their studies included the detection
and treatment of <italic>Trypanosoma</italic>,<italic>Leishmania</italic>,
<italic>Toxoplasma</italic>, and<italic>Plasmodium</italic> by Raymundo Martins de
Castro (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Sampaio et al. 1971)</xref>, Alu&#x000ed;zio Prata
(<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">Prata 1963</xref>), Mario Camargo (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">Camargo 1964b</xref>), and Thales de Brito (de <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">Brito et al. 1962)</xref>, the biology of trypanosomatids
by Walter Colli (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">Alves &#x00026; Colli 1974)</xref>, Erney
Camargo (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Camargo 1964a</xref>), and Isaac Roitman
(Roitman 1969), and epidemiological approaches to studying diseases and hosts by Jeffrey
Shaw (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">Shaw &#x00026; Lainson 1968)</xref>, Jayme Neves
(<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">Neves et al. 1961)</xref>, and Astolpho Ferraz de
Siqueira (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">Barreto et al. 1963)</xref>. These studies
concluded the first phase of Brazilian protozoology. The co-authors of the works cited
above certainly contributed to Brazilian protozoology and could be identified as
founders of Brazilian protozoology.</p><p>The pioneers/founders, together with the students they supervised, nucleated the
Brazilian protozoologist network. Thus, the environment favouring the construction of
this field in Brazilian science was created. By supervising new students, organising
scientific meetings and working side by side with agencies to create programmes for
financial support, these scientists solidified the foundations of Brazilian protozoology
and allowed the influx of new scientists into this area.</p><p>Immigration occurred in two waves. The entry of scientists between 1978-1993 might be a
consequence of the creation of the Integrated Program for Endemic Diseases (PIDE), which
was the Funding Programme from the Brazilian Council for Science Development (CNPq) that
operated between 1976-1986. This programme invested the equivalent of 12 million
American dollars in groups working in approximately 200 projects in endemic diseases
(<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">Gon&#x000e7;alves et al. 1988</xref>). Due to its
differentiated financial policy, which means an initiative to influence the development
of a special area, the programme had a huge impact on attracting more groups to work in
protozoology, and our data reinforce this importance.</p><p>The second wave of incoming scientists occurred after 1998 and might be the consequence
of the elevated number of fellowships and resources offered by the CNPq. In this sense,
national politics favoured Brazilian science, and protozoology took advantage of this
situation. However, we cannot forget the contribution of International Funding
Programmes such as the Tropical Diseases Research (TDR) of the World Health
Organization.</p><p>By tracking students who completed their PhD in protozoology, we observed that 85% of
them were still involved with science. Considering that the other 15% might include
people who teach in private universities using the knowledge acquired during their PhD,
we can conclude that the resources invested in protozoology were very well returned to
society. However, it is time to reflect on whether the current number of students
completing their PhDs will be harnessed in Brazil as has occurred in the past.</p><p>The scenario of protozoology in Brazil, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Fig.
6</xref>, presents an increasing trend. Although the immigration dynamics presented
in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05">Fig. 5</xref> showed a possible decrease in interest,
Brazilian protozoology is the result of the work of pioneers and also (as evidenced by
the green dots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06">Fig. 6</xref>) the consequence of the
immigration of many scientists to protozoology who supervised their students in this
area. It is important to reinforce that this flux requires financial support or strong
funding programmes such as the PIDE and TDR.</p><p>Our goal in this communication was to show the dynamics of protozoologists and the
impact of protozoology on Brazilian science. The same approach can be used to study
contributions in other fields. The use of different criteria can group people in various
ways to reveal other trees and identify other pioneers, even in protozoology. The
genealogy presented here is one of multiple possible methods to track our past and
hopefully point to our future.</p><p>From Isaac Newton to Stephen Hawking, the idea of &#x0201c;having seen further by standing on
the shoulders of giants&#x0201d; has been used in science to recognise past mentors for new
discoveries. We expect that in addition to serving as a source for research on the
historical and paradigmatic aspects of Brazilian protozoology and positioning the
contributions of the field to Brazilian science, this paper may be seen as a form of
acknowledgement of the pioneering researchers who built the foundations of our work and
inspired new generations of protozoology.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>To Marcelo Reis, for grateful discussions concerning data analysis.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure" id="fn1"><p>Financial support: FAPESP (2013/07467-1 to MCE), CNPq (461757/2014-1 to JPM-C) MCE
and LMF-W are research fellows from CNPq (306376/2012-1 and 307587/2014-2
respectively).</p></fn></fn-group><app-group><app id="app01"><label>Supplementary data</label><table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>TABLE I</label><caption><title>Descriptors used to screen theses on Coordination for the Improvement of
Higher Education Personnel database</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0074-0276-mioc-111-1-0067-gt01"/></table-wrap></app><app id="app02"><label/><table-wrap id="t2" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>TABLE II</label><caption><title>Scientists that supervised at least 10 theses/dissertations containing at
least one of the 60 descriptors present on Supplementary Table I</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0074-0276-mioc-111-1-0067-gt02"/><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><p>source: Coordination for the Improvement of Higher Education Personnel
database in the period from 1987-2011.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></app><app id="app03"><label/><table-wrap id="t3" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>TABLE III</label><caption><title>Classification of names according to diagram in Fig. 3A</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0074-0276-mioc-111-1-0067-gt03"/><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN2"><p>a: scientists working or who worked in the past in protozoology in Brazil;
b: scientists working in protozoology outside of Brazil that were advisors
of Brazilians; c: scientists that did not work in protozoology during their
PhD or establish a research interest in this field but were advisors of
scientists that migrated to protozoology; d: persons who developed their PhD
in protozoology but are now involved in activities other than science; e:
scientists who developed their PhD in protozoology but established research
in another field.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></app><app id="app04"><label/><table-wrap id="t4" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>TABLE IV</label><caption><title>Classification of names that developed (1) or not (2) PhD in
protozoology</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0074-0276-mioc-111-1-0067-gt04"/><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN3"><p>bolded names: persons who developed PhD in protozoology having as supervisor
a nonprotozoologist.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></app><app id="app05"><label/><table-wrap id="t5" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><label>TABLE V</label><caption><title>Year that persons who did not develop PhD in protozoology published in this
field</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="0074-0276-mioc-111-1-0067-gt05"/><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN4"><p>
<italic>a</italic>: the year that scientist published his first paper in
Brazil after his PhD; bolded names: persons who did develop PhD in
protozoology outside Brazil.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></app></app-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>MJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Colli</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><year>1974</year><article-title>Agglutination of Trypanosoma cruzi by concavalin
A</article-title><source>J Protozool</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4214499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammarfelt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Price revisited: on the growth of dissertations in eight
research fields</article-title><source>Scientometrics</source><volume>88</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>383</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pessoa</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1946</year><article-title xml:lang="pt">Contribui&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o para o estudo da distribui&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o geogr&#x000e1;fica
dos fleb&#x000f3;tomos americanos (Diptera, Psychoidae)</article-title><source>An Paul Med Cir</source><volume>51</volume><size units="pages">261</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Siqueira</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1963</year><article-title>Study on reservoirs and forest vectors of Trypanosoma
cruzi. I. Presence of Triatoma infestans (Hemiptera, Reduviidae) in forest
outhouses</article-title><source>Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</source><volume>5</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14116864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blackburn</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gall</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1978</year><article-title>Tandemly repeated sequence at the termini of the
extrachromosomal ribosomal RNA genes in Tetrahymena</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><volume>120</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">642006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brener</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year>1952</year><article-title>Complement fixation with L. brasiliensis in cutaneous
American leishmaniasis and in Chagas disease</article-title><source>Hospital</source><volume>41</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>275</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calkins</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><year>1911</year><article-title>The scope of protozoology</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17741330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1964a</year><article-title>Growth and differantiation in Trypanosoma cruzi. I.
Origin of metacyclic trypanosomas in liquid media</article-title><source>Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14177814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><year>1964b</year><article-title>Improved technique of indirect immunofluorescence for
serological diagnosis of toxoplasmosis</article-title><source>Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</source><volume>6</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14177810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chagas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>1909</year><article-title xml:lang="pt">Nova tripanozomiaze humana. Estudos sobre a morfolojia e
o ciclo evolutivo do Schizotrypanum cruzi n. gen., n. sp., ajente etiolojico de
nova entidade morbida do homem</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>218</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clayton</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Life without transcriptional control? From fly to man
and back again</article-title><source>Embo J</source><volume>21</volume><fpage>1881</fpage><lpage>1888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11953307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cordova</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaghi</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>The development of global science</article-title><source>ACS Cent Sci</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Paola</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>1957</year><article-title>Histochemical changes in the hepatic reticuloendothelial
system in kala-azar</article-title><source>Med Cir Farm</source><volume>19</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13464323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year>1957</year><article-title>Amebic abscess of the liver; review and case
report</article-title><source>Rev Bras Gastroenterol</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13518695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meira</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassoi</surname><given-names>ON</given-names></name></person-group><year>1962</year><article-title>Contribution to the study of malaria. II. Pathology of
the liver in acute malaria</article-title><source>Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13873178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Queiroz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tafuri</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1957</year><article-title>Lesion of the eye and adnexa in experimental
schizotrypanosomiaisis in albino rats</article-title><source>Rev Assoc Med Bras</source><volume>3</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13506129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deane</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Deane</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1954</year><article-title>Dogs naturally infected by Leishamnia donovani in
Cear&#x000e1;</article-title><source>Hospital</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>707</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>The structure, biosynthesis, and function of
glycosylphosphatidylinositol anchors, and the contribution of trypanosome
research</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><volume>112</volume><fpage>2799</fpage><lpage>2809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10444375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Haldar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cross</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985</year><article-title>Trypanosoma brucei variant surface glycoprotein has a
sn-1,2-dimyristyl glycerol membrane anchor at its COOH terminus</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><volume>260</volume><fpage>4963</fpage><lpage>4968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3988741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lins</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Neiva</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year><article-title xml:lang="pt">Avalia&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o explorat&#x000f3;ria de atua&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o bienal do Programa
Integrado de Doen&#x000e7;as End&#x000ea;micas do Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico
e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico PIDE/CNPq</article-title><source>Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3201060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinzel</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadick</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Holaday</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Locksley</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Reciprocal expression of interferon gamma of interleukin
4 during the resolution or progression of murine leishmaniasis. Evidence for
expansion of distinct helper T-cell subsets</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><volume>169</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2521244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levenshtein</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name></person-group><year>1966</year><article-title>Binary codes capable of correcting deletions,
insertions, and reversals</article-title><source>Soviet Physics-Doklady</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>710</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Brener</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mour&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><year>1956</year><article-title xml:lang="pt">Autochthonous kala-azar in Minas Gerais</article-title><source>Rev Bras Malariol Doencas Trop</source><volume>8</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13494875</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Floeter-Winter</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Identification of SL addition trans-splicing acceptor
sites in the internal trasncribed spacer I region of pre-rRNA in Leishmania
(Leishmania) amazonensis</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><volume>107</volume><fpage>1070</fpage><lpage>1072</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23295762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mena-Chalco</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><source xml:lang="pt">Caracteriza&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o do banco de teses e disserta&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es da
CAPES</source><conf-name>4&#x000ba; Encontro Brasileiro de Bibliometria e Cientometria</conf-name><conf-date>14-16 de maio de 2014</conf-date><conf-loc>Recife</conf-loc><size units="pages">11</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name></person-group><year>1948</year><article-title>Cultivation of Trypanosoma cruzi in tissue cultures; a
four day study</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><volume>39</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18876881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moraes</surname><given-names>LCA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pessoa</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagundes</surname><given-names>DLG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandes</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hon&#x000f3;rio-Fran&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>The effect of INF-g and TGF-b in the functional activity
of mononuclear cells in the presence of Entamoeba histolytica</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><volume>8</volume><size units="pages">413</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neves</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayrink</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Mourao</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1961</year><article-title>Kala-azar in Minas Gerais. Clinical and
immuno-serological survey in the Hospital das Cl&#x000ed;nicas and in the Santa Casa de
Miseric&#x000f3;rdia de Belo Horizonte, to identify cases of kala-azar</article-title><source>Hospital</source><volume>59</volume><fpage>1165</fpage><lpage>1177</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paraense</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><year>1952</year><article-title>Observations on a Brazilian strain of Plasmodium
circumflexum</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source><volume>50</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>241</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pessoa</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><year>1945</year><article-title xml:lang="pt">Sobre a localiza&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o dos parasitos nos tecidos e a
intensidade do parasitismo na leishamaniase tegumentar americana</article-title><source>Rev Paul Med</source><volume>26</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21012132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>1963</year><article-title>Treatment of kala-azar with amphotericin
B</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>57</volume><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14047022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roitman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><year>1969</year><article-title>Experiments in growing Trypanosoma conorhini on a
synthetic medium</article-title><source>J Protozoology</source><volume>16</volume><size units="pages">36</size></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sampaio</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivitti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampaio</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1971</year><article-title>Treatment of mucocutaneous (American) leishmaniasis with
amphotericin B: report of 70 cases</article-title><source>Int J Dermatol</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>388</fpage><lpage>394</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lainson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1968</year><article-title>Leishmaniasis in Brazil. II. Observation on enzootic
leishamaniasis in the lower Amazonian Basin</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><volume>62</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5659233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>The evolution and diversity of kinetoplastid
flagellates</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16504583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><year>2014</year><chapter-title>Academic genealogy</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><role>eds</role></person-group><source>Beyond bibliometrics: harnessing multidimensional indicators of
scholarly impact</source><publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>382</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>