<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7205979</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">64230</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-64230-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Flying on their own wings: young and adult cuckoos respond similarly to long-distance displacement during migration</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Thorup</surname><given-names>Kasper</given-names></name><address><email>kasper.thorup@sund.ku.dk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>Marta Lomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Snell</surname><given-names>Katherine Rachel Scotchburn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lubkovskaia</surname><given-names>Regina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Willemoes</surname><given-names>Mikkel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sj&#x000f6;berg</surname><given-names>Sissel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sokolov</surname><given-names>Leonid V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bulyuk</surname><given-names>Victor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0674 042X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5254.6</institution-id><institution>Center for Macroecology, Evolution and Climate, Globe Institute, University of Copenhagen, </institution></institution-wrap>Copenhagen, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2289 6897</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.15447.33</institution-id><institution>Saint Petersburg University, </institution></institution-wrap>St Petersburg, Russia </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2314 7601</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.439287.3</institution-id><institution>Biological Station Rybachy, Zoological Institute of Russian Academy of Sciences, </institution></institution-wrap>St Petersburg, Russia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>7</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>7698</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Common cuckoos <italic>Cuculus canorus</italic> are obligate nest parasites yet young birds reach their distant, species-specific wintering grounds without being able to rely on guidance from experienced conspecifics &#x02013; in fact they never meet their parents. Na&#x000ef;ve marine animals use an inherited navigational map during migration but in inexperienced terrestrial animal migrants unequivocal evidence of navigation is lacking. We present satellite tracking data on common cuckoos experimentally displaced 1,800&#x02009;km eastward from Rybachy to Kazan. After displacement, both young and adult travelled similarly towards the route of non-displaced control birds. The tracking data demonstrate the potential for young common cuckoos to return to the species-specific migration route after displacement, a response so far reported exclusively in experienced birds. Our results indicate that an inherited map allows first-time migrating cuckoos to locate suitable wintering grounds. This is in contrast to previous studies of solitary terrestrial bird migrants but similar to that reported from the marine environment.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Animal migration</kwd><kwd>Behavioural ecology</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">For a lone young common cuckoo <italic>Cuculus canorus</italic>, raised by foster-parents of other species, finding the proper wintering grounds thousands of kilometres away without conspecific guidance appears almost impossible. Nevertheless, as more than a billion other inexperienced migrants from the Palearctic do, it reaches its African wintering grounds every year<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. How it manages to do this remains one of the most fascinating mysteries of migration biology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Such challenges are faced across land and sea by a diverse range of organisms, including insects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> and cetaceans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. In the marine environment, inexperienced young of several species that travel independent of adults, including turtles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, salmon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> and eels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>, are shown to rely on an inherited navigational map based on geomagnetic information<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. This has the obvious advantage of being able to correct for unwanted displacement. Nevertheless, evidence for true navigation in first-time avian migrants remains equivocal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Routes and non-breeding staging sites of many long-distance migrating land birds are population-specific and conserved across individuals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> (but see<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>), with routes involving challenging barrier crossings such as the Mediterranean and the Sahara for Afro-Palearctic migrants. In general, young migrants possess an innate migratory orientation programme enabling them to overcome these challenges; a programme which over generations has provided the highest chances of returning to breed next spring and thus the highest fitness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Many aspects of the adaptive programme have been revealed, such as innate timing and direction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. However, the evidence about whether it involves some form of navigation remains contradictory<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Studying responses to displacement allows us to distinguish between different types of underlying navigation strategies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Displacement experiments, such as the paradigmatic experiment by Perdeck<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> involving more than 11,000 European starlings <italic>Sturnus vulgaris</italic> and later repeated with <italic>Zonothricia</italic> sparrows<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, have documented an endogenous directional programme steering inexperienced migrants in a certain direction. Cage studies have shown that the direction is followed over an innately controlled period of time, providing first-time migrants with direction and distance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. With experience, this programme develops into a goal-area navigation programme normally allowing the birds to pinpoint at least their breeding and winter grounds even from unfamiliar areas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Such an ability has been well documented in adult birds as shown by lesser black-backed gulls <italic>Larus fuscus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> and adult common cuckoos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> returning to the normal migration route after long-distance displacements of 1,080 and 2,500&#x02009;km, respectively, though with marked inter-individual flexibility in route and timing. Similar navigation responses have been shown for directional preferences of displaced adults<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> but not always<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. However, while the displacements of starlings and <italic>Zonothricia</italic> sparrows did not indicate such an ability in juveniles, contradicting evidence has been reported in other studies, and whether some ability to correct for orientation errors or wind displacement is also present in juvenile birds remains unclear<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. A re-analysis of 109 published displacement experiments indicated that even juvenile birds were able to detect and react to displacements, including those in which displacement was simulated in a planetarium<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Additionally, experiments by &#x000c5;kesson <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> indicate that juvenile white-crowned sparrows <italic>Zonothricia leucophrys</italic> may be able to correct for displacements and both wind-displaced and experimentally displaced birds on the Faroe Islands showed compensatory responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Given the contradicting evidence about the ability to compensate displacement, we challenged this experimentally by building on recent advances in tracking technologies that allow globally unbiased spatiotemporal mapping of movements of smaller, long-distance migrants. Thus, we tracked the responses to an experimental 1,800&#x02009;km eastward displacement of adult and young common cuckoos. Common cuckoos migrate from their breeding grounds in the Palearctic to their wintering grounds in sub-Saharan Africa. The long distances are travelled at night, presumably solitarily without guidance from conspecifics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. As the cuckoo is a nest parasite, juveniles rely on their inherent migration programme to locate suitable winter grounds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. We investigated the nature of the innate migration programme by comparing the tracks of displaced birds with those from non-displaced migrants caught <italic>en route</italic> on the Courish Spit at the Baltic Coast (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). We tested for evidence of navigation in young birds, potentially shown by displaced first-time migrants differing from non-displaced controls and responding similarly to adults compensating the displacement.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Tracks of control common cuckoos migrating through Rybachy, Kaliningrad, Russia, during autumn (red) and experimental birds displaced to Kazan, Russia (blue). (<bold>a</bold>) Standard uncompensated migration from Rybachy to the winter grounds (black), theoretical compensated route with navigation from the release site in Kazan to the normal winter grounds (grey dotted) and expected displacement responses (green) showing an uncompensated route (solid line) and adult-type response (dotted and transparent). (<bold>b</bold>) Tracks of adult (pale) and first time (dark) migrating cuckoos released in Rybachy (controls, red) and displaced (blue) to Kazan. Tracks of adults released in Denmark (pink) and displaced to Spain (grey) (Adapted from Willemoes <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup> with permission) are shown for comparison. (<bold>c</bold>) Comparison of control and displaced tracks with standardised starting longitude. Maps are created using R software (version 3.4.4; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/">https://cran.r-project.org/</ext-link>) using the packages &#x0201c;maps&#x0201d; version 3.3.0 and &#x0201c;rgdal&#x0201d; version 1.3-6.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_64230_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e464"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="Par7">The routes of first-time migrating cuckoos displaced eastwards from Rybachy to Kazan (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>) led them overall closer to the normal migration routes, with the endpoints of the displaced first-time migrants being significantly displaced westward compared to the controls (&#x02212;10.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.1&#x000b0; and 0.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.9&#x000b0; [mean &#x000b1; s.d.] for displaced (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;8) and control (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4) young, respectively; t-test of difference: p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.027; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>. Bearings to endpoints of control young: 178.5&#x000b0;, r&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.992, Rayleigh test: p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.008; displaced young: 202.7&#x000b0;, r&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.976, Rayleigh test: p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; Watson-Williams test of difference, F<sub>1,10</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10.708, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.008). The displaced young cuckoos travelled south-southwest from Kazan in a slightly more westward direction than the control first-time migrants but their ability to correct only became apparent after they had travelled over a long distance, indicated by the initial bearings (after crossing 500&#x02009;km), which were not significantly different (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a,b</xref>). No differences in the timing of control and displaced birds were apparent (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. Difference in timing of crossing 500&#x02009;km distance: p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.128, 1000&#x02009;km distance: p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.865; t-tests). Movements of young birds were on average slightly earlier &#x02013; 10 days when crossing 500&#x02009;km distance &#x02013; but not significantly so and not after crossing 1,000&#x02009;km (Difference in timing of crossing 500&#x02009;km distance: p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.063, 1,000&#x02009;km distance: p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.834; t-tests. Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Directional response to displacement in first-time and adult cuckoos. Bearing after crossing 500&#x02009;km in first-time (white) and adult (black) cuckoos from (<bold>a</bold>) Rybachy, Russia, (182.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14.9&#x000b0; and 175.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.7&#x000b0; [mean &#x000b1; s.d.] for juveniles (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4) and adults (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;7), respectively) and (<bold>b</bold>) after the 1,800&#x02009;km displacement eastward to Kazan, Russia, (203.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;17.7&#x000b0; and 207.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.7&#x000b0; for juveniles (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;8) and adults (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;2), respectively). Arrows indicate mean direction and vector length, dotted lines 95% CI.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_64230_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e503"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Timing of flights in displaced (blue) and control (red) adult (light) and young (dark) cuckoos. Displaced and control young were tracked for equally long (day of the year of last position: 289.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;35.9 and 319.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;47.7 [mean &#x000b1; SD] for displaced (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;8) and control young (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4), respectively; t<sub>10</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.22, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.25; Day of the year of last position adults: 288.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;24.7 and 307.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;37.3 for displaced and control adults, respectively). The tracks were terminated for four out of the eight displaced juvenile cuckoos already in September and for the displaced adults in the end of September and early October.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_64230_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e515"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">Though we find significant compensation in the displaced young on average, the individual responses varied and the resulting tracks showed a large scatter in directions and a large longitudinal spread along the migration route. Two birds demonstrated significant compensation (Outliers in simulation tests, p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001, respectively; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) both being more westerly than those of control birds with one individual reaching the longitudes of control birds and thus evidently compensating fully for the displacement. The tracks of displaced adults overlapped those of the displaced young with similar distances and degree of compensation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b,c</xref>) as did the directions to positions after crossing 500&#x02009;km (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>), and so the compensatory reactions among displaced young were similar to the compensation in displaced adults. Among the first-time migrants that compensated only partly (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>,<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">c</xref> and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>), a bird wintering 2,500&#x02009;km northeast of the nearest control bird demonstrates the potential for surviving in new wintering grounds without fully compensating for the displacement. This bird in fact moved toward south-southwest in January and February after having reached sub-Saharan Africa in October.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of simulated (grey) and observed endpoints of displaced (blue) and control (red) adult (light) and young (dark) cuckoos displaced to starting in (0&#x000b0;, 0&#x000b0;). Confidence intervals of simulated endpoints (dots; n&#x02009;=&#x02009;1,500) are indicated (solid line: p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; stippled line: p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2020_64230_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e545"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par9">Our results provide new insights into the migratory programme that brings na&#x000ef;ve parasitic cuckoos to their wintering grounds for the first time. Our tracks of displaced young demonstrate that it is possible for first time migrants to compensate for such a displacement and thus the existence of inherited navigational responses similar to those demonstrated in marine animals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. At the same time, other individuals followed routes with little or no compensation, although this may have changed if the birds were tracked all the way to the wintering grounds. The responses observed are similar to those observed in adults, which are also able to compensate for displacements but many nevertheless follow uncompensated routes long after the displacement. Overall, the tracks provide evidence of an adult-type response to long-distance displacement in juvenile common cuckoos.</p><p id="Par10">Despite the evidence from animals navigating in the marine environment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>, the capability of compensation after displacement in migratory na&#x000ef;ve birds has not been unequivocally demonstrated before. Such an &#x0201c;open and flexible&#x0201d; system &#x02013; similar to that found in adults &#x02013; likely provides evolutionary advantages as birds have the &#x0201c;option&#x0201d; to stay if they find suitable routes and wintering areas but also the possibility of returning to the normal route. Compensatory responses might be needed less often for migrants in the terrestrial than in the marine environment as terrestrial migrants spend most of the time resting on the ground whereas marine animals are constantly in a flowing media<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Thus, compensation is typically only necessary for terrestrial migrants during travel when they are more exposed to for example winds. In fact, compensating partly would not need to be based on an inherited map: juveniles could combine orientation in the normal migration direction with experienced-based navigation toward a site already visited on migration, as birds already on the way on their first migration could be acquiring information necessary for later navigation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par11">While individual birds&#x02019; responses to displacements are key for distinguishing navigation strategies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>, most studies only track these in the lab<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup> or for a shorter distance (up to a few hundred kilometres)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. For long-distance migrants, satellite tracking allows spatially unbiased study of the behavioural responses to displacement but few experiments have been performed in first-time migrants, and all of these have focussed on social migrants where group orientation might be guided by experienced individuals. Displacement experiments with young white storks <italic>Ciconia ciconia</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> and relocations of lesser spotted eagles <italic>Clanga pomarina</italic> for re-introduction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> indicated a less precise migration programme with birds being dependent on social interactions to complete normal migrations as also indicated by a study on hybrids between lesser and greater spotted eagles <italic>Clanga clanga</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The initial uncompensated movements could indicate navigation based on inherited &#x0201c;signposts&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> and they align well with observations from the marine environment, where navigation in inexperienced animals appears to be based on navigational markers (a simple look-up table<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>). Thus, the information might only be available when the animal is within a certain range, requiring long-distance tracking to observe.</p><p id="Par12">An alternative explanation for the observed changes in routes by first-time migrating cuckoos would be that they travelled with experienced individuals. However, we believe this is unlikely to be the case because young cuckoos are mainly solitary migrants managing to reach their wintering grounds without guidance as shown by differences in timing between young and adults from other populations with other routes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Nevertheless, the routes for populations naturally occurring at the site of displacement may well be similar to the displaced birds but flocking and social interactions such as calling are not regularly observed during migration. The overall navigation strategies employed by displaced birds appear similar between experienced and first-time migrants. The fact that many tracks ended without full compensation might be caused by transmission ending before having reached the wintering grounds. The less than full compensation in those ending far to the south could also be caused by a compensatory response rooted in a plane rather than a sphere. On a sphere, a certain difference in longitudes corresponds to a longer distance closer to the Equator and the distance between the capture and displacement sites is shorter than the distance between the normal wintering grounds and those that would be reached after uncompensated migration in displaced individuals. Thus, if the birds compensated the displacement distance (rather than a difference in longitudes) after having moved south they would not reach the longitudes of the control birds.</p><p id="Par13">The actual mechanisms used for the navigational tasks remain unclear. Geomagnetic cues are widely available across taxa for orientation even in insects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Given the omnipresence of geomagnetic cues and the demonstration of their use for true navigation in adult bird migrants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup> as well as in inexperienced marine animals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> these appear to be the most likely candidates. Furthermore, experiments have indicated that geomagnetic cues, characteristic of certain latitudes or regions, affect the orientation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> or the deposition of fuel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> of first-time migrants. However, their use over inter-continental scales are not straightforward as neither field intensity, inclination nor declination show simple gradient patterns over the scales considered. Alternatively, navigation could be based on olfactory cues as in experienced migrating gulls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> and catbirds <italic>Dumetella carolinensis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par14">Our results challenge the common understanding of the orientation programme in inexperienced migratory birds. The strategy appears to include some form of navigation, at least in common cuckoos. A navigational programme as demonstrated here might be crucial during even more extreme land bird migrations as for example the 13,000&#x02009;km long migration spanning across many degrees of latitudes and longitudes of willow warblers <italic>Phylloscopus trochilus</italic> migrating from Chukotka to Southeast Africa<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, but navigational responses at the scale considered has not been studied so far. Our study lays out the foundation for studying capabilities and underlying cue use necessary for a deeper understanding of bird migration. Broadening out our study with respect to populations and species awaits even further technical advancements such as those promised by ICARUS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec5"><title>Ethical statement</title><p id="Par15">The Ethical Committee of the Zoological Institute (RAS #2015-01-14) and Kaliningrad Regional Agency for Protection, Reproduction and Use of Animal World and Forests approved sampling procedures and experimental manipulations, and permitted the catching and tagging of cuckoos. This study was carried out in accordance with Guidelines to the use of wild birds in research of the Ornithological Council<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>.The common cuckoo is not a protected species and it is not considered threatened or endangered.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Experimental animals, tagging and displacement</title><p id="Par16">Adult and juvenile cuckoos used for the study were caught in the Kaliningrad Region shortly after initiation of autumn migration during late July &#x02013; August 2015-2018. Individual migration routes were tracked using satellite telemetry and individuals were either controls (tagged and released close to trapping site) or displaced (tagged and displaced in groups 1,800&#x02009;km eastward to Kazan, Tatarstan).</p><p id="Par17">Cuckoos were trapped at two sites: the Biological Station Rybachy (55&#x000b0; 9&#x02019; 13&#x0201d; N, 20&#x000b0; 51&#x02019; 29&#x0201d; E) and the Fringilla Field Station (55&#x000b0; 5&#x02019; 18&#x0201d; N, 20&#x000b0; 44&#x02019; 3&#x0201d; E). Two large Heligoland traps at the Fringilla station as well as mist-nests at the two stations were used for trapping. Playback of cuckoo song and calls was widely used to attract birds.</p><p id="Par18">To treat both control and experimental birds equally, all birds were kept in aviaries after trapping for 1 to 22 days. They were provisioned with mealworms and water ad libitum until tagging and release. During this time, the birds&#x02019; behaviour and weight changes were monitored. Birds with high body mass (minimum &#x0003e;100&#x02009;g) and good condition were tagged and released, or kept for planned displacement events if they had not been kept in captivity for too long (&#x0003e; 1 week). Control birds were released during the period both before and after displacements.</p><p id="Par19">We fitted satellite transmitters on 27 juvenile and 18 adult common cuckoos (see Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>-<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref> for deployment details). Tags were fitted with a backpack harness of 2&#x02009;mm &#x000f8; braided nylon cord. The juvenile harness size was the same as the one used in adults to account for further body growth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Cuckoos were tagged just before release (control birds), or one or two days before (displaced birds).</p><p id="Par20">The displaced group consisted of 15 juveniles and 7 adults translocated to Kazan in 2015, 2016 and 2018. They were transported by commercial airline in pet carriers and released into a natural, wooded habitat in daylight conditions as soon as possible after arrival (release site 55&#x000b0; 51&#x02019; 18&#x0201d; N, 48&#x000b0; 48&#x02019; 18&#x0201d; E and 55&#x000b0; 39&#x02019; 22&#x0201d; N, 49&#x000b0; 2&#x02019; 13&#x0201d; E, respectively). The control group consisted of 12 juveniles and 11 adults. Apart from the early movement of two juveniles displaced to Kazan that moved more than 100&#x02009;km within four days, we found no general difference between control and displaced birds in departure timing after release (Difference in days after first position when crossing 500&#x02009;km distance: p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.154, 1,000&#x02009;km distance: p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.920; t-tests).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Tracking</title><p id="Par21">The tags used for this study transmitted location information via satellites. Two models of transmitting tags were used to obtain spatial data in this study: Platform Terminal Transmitters (PTTs) 5&#x02009;g solar PTT-100s (Microwave Telemetry Inc., Maryland, USA) and 3.4&#x02009;g or 3.7&#x02009;g PinPoint GPS ARGOS Tags 75 (LOTEK, Newmarket, Canada; tag mass depended on antenna specifications).</p><p id="Par22">Location estimates were obtained from PTTs by interpreting the Doppler effect of transmissions from the tags to the Argos Satellite system. Position quality and accuracy is determined (where possible) by the number and duration of transmissions (estimated error classes 0: &#x0003e;1,500&#x02009;m; 1: 500&#x02013;1,500&#x02009;m; 2: 250&#x02013;500&#x02009;m; 3: &#x0003c;250&#x02009;m (<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>). The tags had a solar cell and the temporal schedule was 10&#x02009;hours transmission followed by 48&#x02009;hours off, for as long there was sufficient power.</p><p id="Par23">The PinPoint tags provide GPS positions acquired at scheduled intervals, compressed and transmitted via the Argos system. The tags are scheduled in advance and limited by internal battery capacity (determined by the GPS acquisition time and transmission of data to the Argos system). In 2015, tags were programmed to obtain positions regularly on a short schedule and transmit data on a predefined date (estimable to a date prior to the Sahara crossing), or for a long schedule where positions were attempted until transmission which was determined by a critical battery voltage. In 2017, tags were equipped with Argos satellite pass prediction software by which the tag only transmitted data when a satellite was within range, thus substantially improving power efficiency and enabling regular transmission of data throughout the migration period. All transmission data include time stamps and satellite ID.</p><p id="Par24">From the PinPoint tags, GPS position data were transmitted via the ARGOS satellite system and processed with LOTEK software; failed positions were excluded. Doppler positions can also be obtained from transmitting PinPoint tags but only a few of these were received.</p><p id="Par25">In cases where an Argos transmission occurred but no Doppler position could be estimated, an estimate and error radii was calculated from satellite pass data by CLS. Where a PinPoint tag had acquired a concurrent GPS position this was used in preference to the ARGOS estimate.</p><p id="Par26">After rejecting class Z estimates, we used the highest quality position from each transmission cycle closest to noon.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Data analyses</title><p id="Par27">Of the 27 tagged juveniles, we considered the 12 individuals that were tracked for more than 500&#x02009;km/crossed south of 50&#x000b0;N to have started migration (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Initial movements appeared to be slightly further westward in the first year but the bearings after crossing 100&#x02009;km were not significantly different from the other years, and thus in the analyses we considered results from all years together. In adults, 9 of 18 started migration.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of common cuckoo data. Numbers indicate individuals included in analyses, i.e. tracked for more than 500&#x02009;km/crossing south of 50&#x000b0;N.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Year</th><th colspan="2">Juveniles</th><th colspan="2">Adults</th><th rowspan="2">Total</th></tr><tr><th>Rybachy</th><th>Kazan</th><th>Rybachy</th><th>Kazan</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>2015</td><td>1 (5)</td><td>3 (5)</td><td>3 (6)</td><td>1 (5)</td><td>8 (21)</td></tr><tr><td>2016</td><td>1 (2)</td><td>1 (5)</td><td/><td/><td>2 (7)</td></tr><tr><td>2017</td><td>2 (5)</td><td/><td>4 (5)</td><td/><td>6 (10)</td></tr><tr><td>2018</td><td/><td>4 (5)</td><td/><td>1 (2)</td><td>5 (7)</td></tr><tr><td>All years</td><td>4 (12)</td><td>8 (15)</td><td>7 (11)</td><td>2 (7)</td><td>21 (45)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Numbers in brackets indicate numbers of individuals tagged.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par28">We used the highest quality position for every duty cycle obtained from ARGOS/CLS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Several birds moved back and forth for some time after release with no consistent direction of movement, and we considered that they started migration when consistent directions were observed.</p><p id="Par29">We investigated the spatiotemporal pattern of responses by grouping individuals&#x02019; locations according to when they had passed certain distances. However, the sampling schedule did not allow detailed analyses of timing of responses. We compared bearings and timings after crossing 500&#x02009;km (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;13) and 1,000&#x02009;km (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;19) from the release areas because for shorter intervals there were not enough locations for meaningful comparisons (only up to a maximum of 7 in 100&#x02009;km intervals). The directedness of sample orientations for the individuals of a group was tested with the Rayleigh test. Differences in sample orientations were tested with Watson-Williams tests. We used t-tests on day of the year of crossing 500&#x02009;km and 1,000&#x02009;km as well as reaching endpoints to compare the timing of migration between controls and displaced and between adult and juveniles.</p><p id="Par30">Because of the distance to the wintering grounds, even large distances at the latitude of the wintering grounds result in potentially relatively small differences in bearings. Thus, in addition to comparing bearings to endpoints (last position, see Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref> for details) using a Watson-Williams test, we tested for evidence of navigation in young birds by comparing the westward longitudinal displacement of endpoints in displaced versus controls. We treated longitude data as linear and compared groups with a t-test. This was justified as less than 10% of the full circle of longitudes were traversed and the Watson-Williams test based on longitudes reported the same result (F<sub>1,10</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.701, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.027 for a difference between controls and displaced). In an ANOVA including both age and displacement effects together, displacement was significant but age was not (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.07) potentially because of small sample size.</p><p id="Par31">To test for displaced individuals compensating for the displacements, we compared with tracks simulated under the assumption that control birds follow a clock-and-compass strategy (vector orientation). Outliers (i.e. significantly deviating longitudinally), were considered compensating if the deviation was in the direction of compensation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). In the young cuckoos, we identified 37 movements longer than 100&#x02009;km that were used for simulations. Considering the longitudes and latitudes traversed in each of these as the result of a clock-and-compass step, we simulated tracks by adding from 1 to 15 randomly chosen longitudes/latidues from this set. For each total number of steps (1 to 15), we simulated 1,000 tracks, resulting in a total of 15,000 simulated endpoints for the test data.</p><p id="Par32">We used R 3.3.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup> for linear statistics and Oriana 3.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup> for circular statistics and diagrams. MS Excel was used for simulations.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec9"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2020_64230_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Information.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>is available for this paper at 10.1038/s41598-020-64230-x.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the Danish Council for Independent Research supporting the MATCH project (1323&#x02013;00048B), the Danish National Research Foundation supporting the Center for Macroecology, Evolution and Climate (DNRF96), the Russian Foundation for Basic Research (grant 16-04-00761 to LS) and the participation of the Zoological Institute of Russian Academy of Sciences (project AAAA-A19-119021190073-8). This project has received funding from the European Union&#x02019;s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme under the Marie Sk&#x00142;odowska-Curie grant agreement No 751692. We thank Emily Baird and Miriam Liedvogel for comments on an earlier draft of this manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>K.T. and V.B. conceived and designed the study. K.T., M.L.V., K.R.S.S., R.L. M.W., S.S., L.V.S., and V.B. carried out field work and gathered the tracking data. K.T. and S.S. analysed the data with assistance from M.L.V., K.R.S.S. and M.W. K.T. drafted the manuscript with assistance from M.L.V. and K.R.S.S. K.T., M.L.V., K.R.S.S., R.L. M.W., S.S., L.V.S. and V.B. commented on and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All tracking data are available in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.movebank.org">www.movebank.org</ext-link> (10.5441/001/1.vk36vq82)</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par33">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The heritability of migration</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1988</year><volume>334</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/334471a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>First-Time Migration in Juvenile Common Cuckoos Documented by Satellite Tracking</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0168940</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0168940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28005960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alerstam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conflicting Evidence About Long-Distance Animal Navigation</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1129048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-range seasonal migration in insects: mechanisms, evolutionary drivers and ecological consequences</article-title><source>Ecol. Lett.</source><year>2015</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ele.12407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25611117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mate</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Critically endangered western gray whales migrate to the eastern North Pacific</article-title><source>Biol. Lett.</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>20150071</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsbl.2015.0071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25878049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putman</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name><surname>Endres</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>CMF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohmann</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Longitude perception and bicoordinate magnetic maps in sea turtles</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2011.01.057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21353561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putman</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An inherited magnetic map guides ocean navigation in juvenile Pacific salmon</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>446</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.01.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24508165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naisbett-Jones</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Putman</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ladak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A magnetic map leads juvenile European eels to the Gulf Stream</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1236</fpage><lpage>1240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2017.03.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28416118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putman</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inherited magnetic maps in salmon and the role of geomagnetic change</article-title><source>Integr. Comp. Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icb/icv020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25888216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obligate and facultative migration in birds: Ecological aspects</article-title><source>J. Ornith.</source><year>2012</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10336-011-0765-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorup</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Resource tracking within and across continents in long-distance bird migrants</article-title><source>Sci. Adv.</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e1601360</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.1601360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28070557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>AMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cresswell</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low migratory connectivity is common in long&#x02010;distance migrant birds</article-title><source>J. Anim. Ecol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>662</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2656.12635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28093769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bird Migration and Natural Selection</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>1968</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3564725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berthold</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Querner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic Basis of Migratory Behavior in European Warblers</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1981</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.212.4490.77</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17747634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Berthold, P. Control of bird migration (Chapman and Hall, London, 1996).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">&#x000c5;kesson, S. Avian long-distance navigation: Experiments with migratory birds. In (ed. Berthold P, Gwinner E, Sonnenschein E) Avian Migration, 471-492 (Springer-Verlag, Berlin, 2003).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Perdeck, A.C. Two Types of Orientation in Migrating Starlings, <italic>Sturnus vulgaris</italic> L., and Chaffinches, <italic>Fringilla coelebs</italic> L., as Revealed by Displacement Experiments. <italic>Ardea</italic><bold>55</bold>, 1-37 (1958).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mewaldt</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>California sparrows return from displacement to Maryland</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1964</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>941</fpage><lpage>942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.146.3646.941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17777062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorup</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evidence for a navigational map stretching across the continental U.S. in a migratory songbird</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>18115</fpage><lpage>18119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0704734104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17986618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wikelski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>True navigation in migrating gulls requires intact olfactory nerves</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>17061</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep17061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26597351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willemoes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wikelski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorup</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flexible navigation response in common cuckoos <italic>Cuculus canorus</italic> displaced experimentally during migration</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>16402</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep16402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26549318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chernetsov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishkinev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouritsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Long-Distance Avian Migrant Compensates for Longitudinal Displacement during Spring Migration</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2008.01.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18249113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kishkinev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Experienced migratory songbirds do not display goal-ward orientation after release following a cross-continental displacement: an automated telemetry study</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>37326</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep37326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27876843</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorup</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rab&#x000f8;l</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Compensatory behaviour following displacement in migratory birds. A meta-analysis of cage-experiments</article-title><source>Behav. Ecol. Sociobiol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>825</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00265-006-0306-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c5;kesson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Muheim</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottosson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dramatic orientation shift of white-crowned sparrows displaced across longitudes in the high Arctic</article-title><source>Curr Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1591</fpage><lpage>1597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2005.07.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16139216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorup</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Juvenile Songbirds Compensate for Displacement to Oceanic Islands during Autumn Migration</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e17903</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0017903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21464975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seel</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Migration of the northwestern European population of the cuckoo (<italic>Cuculus canorus</italic>), as shown by ringing</article-title><source>Ibis</source><year>1977</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1474-919X.1977.tb08250.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Putman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Marine migrations</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>R972</fpage><lpage>R976</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2018.07.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30205073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kishkinev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Anashina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishchenko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anosmic migrating songbirds demonstrate a compensatory response following long-distance translocation: a radio-tracking study</article-title><source>J. Ornithol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10336-019-01698-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wikelski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Going wild: what a global small-animal tracking system could do for experimental biologists</article-title><source>J. Exp. Biol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>210</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.02629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17210955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Testing the role of sensory systems in the migratory heading of a songbird</article-title><source>J. Exp. Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>4065</fpage><lpage>4071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.034504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19946085</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chernetsov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Berthold</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Querner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Migratory orientation of first-year white storks (<italic>Ciconia ciconia</italic>): inherited information and social interactions</article-title><source>J. Exp. Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>207</volume><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>943</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.00853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14766952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyburg</surname><given-names>BU</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Orientation of native versus translocated juvenile lesser spotted eagles (<italic>Clanga pomarina</italic>) on the first autumn migration</article-title><source>J. Exp. Biol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>2765</fpage><lpage>2776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.148932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28768749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000e4;li</surname><given-names>&#x000dc;</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellis</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagys</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maciorowski</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic determination of migration strategies in large soaring birds: evidence from hybrid eagles</article-title><source>Proc. R. Soc. B.</source><year>2018</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>20180855</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2018.0855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Beck, W. &#x00026; Wiltschko, W. Magnetic factors control the migratory direction of Pied Flycatchers (Ficedula hypoleuca Pallas). In: Ouellet H, editor. Acta XIX Congressus Internationalis Ornithologici (University of Ottawa Press, Ottawa, Canada) 1955&#x02013;1962 (1988).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fransson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Magnetic cues trigger extensive refuelling</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>414</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35102115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11689932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animal Navigation: A Map for All Seasons</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>R153</fpage><lpage>R155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.01.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24556436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dreyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Earth&#x02019;s magnetic field and visual landmarks steer migratory flight behaviour in the nocturnal Australian bogong moth</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2160</fpage><lpage>2166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2018.05.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29937347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deutschlander</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-dependent orientation to magnetically-simulated geographic displacements in migratory Australian silvereyes (<italic>Zosterops l. lateralis</italic>)</article-title><source>Wilson J. Ornithol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1676/11-043.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kishkinev</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernetsov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pakhomov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouritsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eurasian reed warblers compensate for virtual magnetic displacement</article-title><source>Curr. Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>R822</fpage><lpage>R824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2015.08.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26439333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sokolovskis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ten grams and 13,000 km on the wing &#x02013; route choice in willow warblers <italic>Phylloscopus trochilus yakutensis</italic> migrating from Far East Russia to East Africa</article-title><source>Move. Ecol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40462-018-0138-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The internet of things</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2018</year><volume>562</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>326</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fair, J., Paul, E. &#x00026; Jones, J. (eds) Guidelines to the use of wild birds in research. Ornithological Council (Washington, DC, 2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willemoes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Narrow-Front Loop Migration in a Population of the Common Cuckoo <italic>Cuculus canorus</italic>, as Revealed by Satellite Telemetry</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e83515</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0083515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24421890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brightsmith</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Error Properties of Argos Satellite Telemetry Locations Using Least Squares and Kalman Filtering</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e63051</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23690980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Development Core Team. R: A language and environment for statistical computing (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria) <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org">http://www.R-project.org</ext-link> (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kovach, W. Oriana &#x02013; Circular Statistics for Windows, ver. 3. (Kovach Computing Services). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kovcomp.co.uk">http://www.kovcomp.co.uk</ext-link>. (2009).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>