<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Orthop Surg Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Orthop Surg Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Orthopaedic Surgery and Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1749-799X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7216515</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1692</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13018-020-01692-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>In vitro analysis of the effect of Flightless I on murine tenocyte cellular functions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>Jessica E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kopecki</surname><given-names>Zlatko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>Peter J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2885-2080</contrib-id><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>Allison J.</given-names></name><address><email>allison.cowin@unisa.edu.au</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1026.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8994 5086</institution-id><institution>Regenerative Medicine, Future Industries Institute, </institution><institution>University of South Australia, </institution></institution-wrap>Adelaide, South Australia Australia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1010.0</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 7304</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Medicine and Health, </institution><institution>University of Adelaide, </institution></institution-wrap>Adelaide, South Australia Australia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>170</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Healing of tendons after injury involves the proliferation of tenocytes and the production of extracellular matrix; however, their capacity to heal is limited by poor cell density and limited growth factor activity. Flightless I (Flii) has previously been identified as an important regulator of cellular proliferation and migration, and the purpose of this study was to evaluate the effect of differential Flii gene expression on tenocyte function in vitro.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The role of Flii on tenocyte proliferation, migration, and contraction was assessed using established assays. Tenocytes from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, wild-type, and <italic>Flii</italic> overexpressing mice were obtained and the effect of differential <italic>Flii</italic> expression on migration, proliferation, contraction, and collagen synthesis determined in vitro<italic>.</italic> Statistical differences were determined using unpaired Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test and statistical outliers were identified using the Grubbs&#x02019; test.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3"><italic>Flii</italic> overexpressing tenocytes showed significantly improved migration and proliferation as well as increased collagen I secretion. Explanted tendons from <italic>Flii</italic> overexpressing mice also showed significantly elevated tenocyte outgrowth compared to <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> mice. In contrast to its role in dermal wound repair, Flii positively affects cellular processes in tendons.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">These findings suggest that Flii could be a novel target for modulating tenocyte activity and improving tendon repair. This could have significant clinical implications as novel therapeutic targets for improved healing of tendon injuries are urgently needed.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Flii</kwd><kwd>Flightless I</kwd><kwd>Tendon</kwd><kwd>Healing</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par12">Tendons inherently have minimal capacity for healing owing to poor cell density and growth factor activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Healing of tendons involves the proliferation of spindle-shaped fibroblast-like cells known as tenocytes, which comprise the main cellular content of mature tendons. Tenocytes have long cellular processes which facilitate cell-extracellular matrix (ECM) and cell-cell communication through desmosomes and tight junctions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. They are highly metabolically active and are responsible for synthesizing and secreting ECM. Tendon repair is characterized by the influx of intrinsic and extrinsic tenocytes which migrate to the injured area and synthesize and secrete ECM to begin the repair process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Tendon healing can occur solely through epitenon-based intrinsic tenocytes that secrete larger, more mature collagen fibers compared with extrinsic tenocytes, resulting in improved physiological outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Tenocyte characterization during injury repair is poorly understood; however, it is well established that tenocyte function is to secrete ECM components and growth factors during healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Of particular importance is their secretion of transforming growth factor beta (TGF&#x003b2;) ligands as this family of growth factors is active throughout all phases of tendon repair [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p id="Par13">Tenocyte migration, proliferation, and contraction are essential processes that allow tendon healing to occur. The actin cytoskeleton is the driving force behind these processes and it also has essential roles in transmembrane signaling and healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In response to injury, the actin cytoskeleton is remodeled to facilitate the permeation of inflammatory cells and promote tenocyte migration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Flightless (Flii) is a highly conserved actin remodeling protein that contains both a gelsolin and leucine-rich repeat (LRR) domain enabling it to modulate the cytoskeleton by regulating actin polymerization and depolymerization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Flii is a known regulator of cellular migration, proliferation, contraction, and adhesion; however, this has been mainly characterized in cutaneous healing responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Flii is expressed ubiquitously throughout cells and tissues of the body but its specific expression in cells and structures with migratory capabilities is of particular interest due to their involvement with wound repair [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Flii has previously been determined to be an important negative regulator of cutaneous wound healing and skin blistering [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. There is also strong evidence to suggest that Flii modulates TGF&#x003b2; expression, with decreased levels of TGF&#x003b2;1 detected in cutaneous healing studies in mice with low levels of Flii (<italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. In addition, reducing the levels of Flii decreases pro-scarring TGF-&#x003b2;1 and Smad 3, while causing an elevation of anti-scarring inhibitory Smad 7, suggesting a mechanistic role for Flii in TGF-&#x003b2; signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">In this study, the effect of altering <italic>Flii</italic> expression on tenocyte activity was investigated. Primary tenocytes were extracted from digital tendons of <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup><italic>,</italic> wild-type (WT), and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice and the effect of differential <italic>Flii</italic> expression on their migration, proliferation, contraction, and ECM production assessed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title><italic>Flii</italic> mouse generation</title><p id="Par15">All mouse strains were congenic on the Balb/c background and Balb/c littermates were used as wild-type (<italic>WT</italic>) control animals. <italic>Flii</italic> homozygous knockout mice are embryonic lethal due to defects with gastrulation during early embryogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. <italic>Flii</italic> heterozygous mice (<italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>) are phenotypically normal, fertile with normal life expectancy. Mice carrying the complete human <italic>Flii</italic> gene on a cosmid transgene were maintained as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Heterozygous transgenic mice <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/+</italic></sup> were made by crossing <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup> with cosmid transgene <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>. These transgenic mice were inter-crossed to obtain animals homozygous for the transgene <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> and carry two copies of the mouse <italic>Flii</italic> gene and two additional copies of the human <italic>Flii</italic> gene (<italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup>) resulting in elevated levels of Flii protein in various tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Isolation of mouse tenocytes</title><p id="Par16">Murine tenocyte isolation can generally be achieved from adult mice (12&#x02013;16&#x02009;weeks) following established protocols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Therefore, digital tendons were removed intact from the hind feet of 4 euthanized female 12-week-old <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice using micro dissection (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). The tendon sheath was removed, and the tip and base of the tendons discarded. The remaining tendons were chopped into 1 mm<sup>3</sup> sections and digested overnight in 4&#x02009;mg/mL dispase (Worthington Biochem, NJ, USA), and 0.5&#x02009;mg/mL collagenase (Worthington Biochem, NJ, USA) in Dulbecco&#x02019;s modified Eagle&#x02019;s media (DMEM) without serum at 37 &#x000b0;C. The following day, the tendon mix was put through a 70-&#x003bc;M cell strainer (In Vitro Technologies, Victoria, Australia) and the remaining tissue discarded. The tube and strainer were washed with sterile media (DMEM + 10% fetal bovine serum [FBS] + penicillin/streptomycin [Pen/Strep] + fungizone) and excess media added to stop the action of the dispase/collagenase mix. The suspension was spun at 1200&#x02009;rpm for 5&#x02009;min and the supernatant discarded. The pellet was resuspended in 4&#x02009;mL sterile media and plated on collagen-coated T25 flask. The T25 was left in an incubator (37 &#x000b0;C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>) for approximately 7&#x02009;days with media changes every 2&#x02013;3&#x02009;days until the cells were a minimum of 90% confluent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Migration assay</title><p id="Par17">Tenocytes isolated from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice were plated into 96-well plates at 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/mL and left overnight in an incubator at 37 &#x000b0;C at 5% CO<sub>2</sub> to reach confluence. A Woundmaker&#x02122; (Essen Bioscience, Michigan, USA) was used to create uniform wounds of 7&#x02013;800&#x02009;&#x003bc;M in each well of the 96-well plate which was subsequently placed into an Incucyte (Essen Bioscience, Michigan, USA) at 37 &#x000b0;C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> where images were automatically taken every 3&#x02009;h for 24&#x02009;h. The resulting images were analyzed using Image Pro Plus 7.1 as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Tendon outgrowth assay</title><p id="Par18">Whole tendons were removed in sterile conditions from the hind feet of 6 <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice. Five millimeters was removed from the ends of each tendon and the remaining tendon was cut into 3 mm<sup>3</sup> sections, transferred into 12-well plates (1 section per well), and cultured in DMEM + 20% FBS + Pen/Strep + Fungizone. Cultures were maintained at 37 &#x000b0;C at 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 12&#x02009;days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Images were taken at days 0, 4, 8, and 12. Migration distances were measured every 90&#x000b0; using Image Pro Plus 7.1 (MediaCybernetics Inc., Maryland, USA) and the average distance calculated.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Collagen immunoassay</title><p id="Par19">A collagen immunoassay was employed similar to previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Briefly isolated <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes were seeded into 96-well plates at 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/mL in media (DMEM + 20% FBS + Pen/Strep + Fungizone) and left overnight at 37 &#x000b0;C 5% CO<sub>2.</sub> Following serum starvation, media were replaced with serum-free media plus Pen/Strep and Fungizone and left for 60&#x02009;h to allow collagen accumulation. The cells were subsequently washed 3 times in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), then fixed and permeabilized in ice-cold methanol for 15&#x02009;min at &#x02212; 20 &#x000b0;C. The cells were aspirated and briefly air-dried before being washed 3 times in PBS. Cells were treated with 0.5% Tween 20 in PBS for 10&#x02009;min and blocked in PBS + 3% normal goat serum for 30 min. The cells were incubated in 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;L per well collagen I (#600-401-103; Rockland, PA; 2 &#x003bc;g/mL) in PBS and 3% normal goat serum for 2&#x02009;h at room temperature. The cells were washed and incubated in 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;L per well secondary antibody in PBS for 1&#x02009;h in the dark at room temperature. Once the secondary staining was complete, the cells were washed in PBS, stained with 4&#x02032;,6-diamindino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) at 1:5000 for 1&#x02009;min and analyzed immediately on an Olympus Epifluorescent microscope as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Collagen contraction assay</title><p id="Par20">Primary tenocytes and fibroblasts isolated from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice tendons or skin, respectively, were trypsinized in 10 &#x000d7; trypsin/EDTA (Sigma-Aldrich, Sydney, Australia) for 5&#x02009;min at 37 &#x000b0;C and quenched using DMEM + 20% FBS. The cells were spun for 5&#x02009;min at 1200&#x02009;rpm and resuspended in ice-cold DMEM at 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL. 3D collagen gels were prepared by mixing 8 parts of chilled collagen solution (2&#x02009;mg/mL) with 1 part 10 &#x000d7; DMEM containing 10% FBS as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The pH was adjusted to 7.4 using 0.1&#x02009;M NaOH. The tenocytes and fibroblasts were added to the collagen gel mixture at 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/mL. Five hundred microliters of this mixture was added per well to a flat-bottomed 48-well plate and allowed to set for 120&#x02009;min at 37 &#x000b0;C 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Following this, the gel was carefully dislodged using a 200-&#x003bc;L pipette and the gels floated by the addition of 1&#x02009;mL DMEM (+ 20% FCS, Pen/Strep, and Fungizone). Images were taken at 24, 48, and 72&#x02009;h post media addition using Olympus Epifluorescent microscope and the images analyzed for degree of contraction using Image Pro-Plus 7.1 as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Immunocytochemistry</title><p id="Par21">Immunocytochemistry was undertaken as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Briefly, isolated <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocyte cells were plated onto glass coverslips and fixed and stained for Flii (2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL; sc-21716, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, CA), TGB&#x003b2;1(2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL; sc-52893 Santa Cruz Biotechnology CA), &#x003b2;-tubulin (2 &#x003bc;g/mL, T4026, Sigma-Aldrich, NSW), collagen I (2 &#x003bc;g/mL #600-401-103, Rockland, PA), Tenascin-C (2 &#x003bc;g/mL, sc-25328 Santa Cruz Biotechnology CA), and Scleraxis (2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL, sc-87425 Santa Cruz Biotechnology CA). Cells were subsequently stained with phalloidin-FITC (2 &#x003bc;g/mL #P5282-0.1G, Sigma-Aldrich, NSW) and nuclear counterstain 4,6-diamidino-2-phenyindole DAPI (2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL D9564, Sigma-Aldrich, NSW). The cells were mounted in fluorescent mounting media (DAKO, CA) and viewed under an Olympus Epifluorescent microscope. Average stain-specific fluorescence was measured using AnalySiS (Soft-Imaging System GmbH, Munster, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>WST-1 proliferation assay</title><p id="Par22">Methods were as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Briefly, cells were serum-starved for 6&#x02009;h to synchronize the cell cycle. The media was then replaced with DMEM + 20% FBS and incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 24, 48, or 72&#x02009;h. Ten microliters WST-1 was added to each well and the absorbance read on a microplate reader at 450&#x02009;nm and 600&#x02009;nm. Cell proliferation was normalized relative to cells with no serum added as control.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par23">Statistical differences were determined following unblinding of the data using GraphPad software (USA) using the unpaired Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test. A <italic>p</italic> value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. A <italic>p</italic> value of less than 0.01 was considered highly significant. Statistical outliers were determined using the Grubbs&#x02019; test with a significance level of 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Tenocytes express Tenascin-C and Scleraxis</title><p id="Par24">Digital tendons were removed from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice, the tendon sheath was removed by microscopic dissection, and intrinsic tenocytes were isolated by outgrowth or enzyme digestion methods (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Specific care was taken to remove the ends of the tendons to avoid phenotypically different tenocytes at the myotendinous junction (MTJ) and osteotendinous junction (OTJ). Dermal fibroblasts were also isolated from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> by outgrowth or enzyme digestion methods. Tenocytes are structurally similar to fibroblasts and it is impossible to visually distinguish the two cell-types. Tendon-specific markers Tenascin-C and Scleraxis were used to identify tenocytes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b&#x02013;d, h&#x02013;j). Tenascin-C is a glycoprotein expressed specifically in tenocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Scleraxis is uniquely expressed in tissues that form tendons and ligaments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Tenascin-C and Scleraxis were expressed in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes with no expression seen in fibroblasts from the same mice, (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b&#x02013;g). Tenascin-C staining was observed to be peri-nuclear whereas Scleraxis staining was observed in the cytoplasm as well as nuclear regions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b&#x02013;g, h&#x02013;m). Tenascin-C was significantly higher in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> tenocytes when compared to WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> (<italic>p</italic> = 0.042 and 0.008, respectively) but no significant difference was noted in Scleraxis expression in tenocytes across the three <italic>Flii</italic> genotypes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>n, o).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Tenascin-C and Scleraxis are expressed specifically in tenocytes. <bold>a</bold> Intact digital tendons were removed from the right and left hind paws of mice for tenocyte isolation. The tendon sheath is indicated by arrows and was removed before digestion to ensure a pure population of intrinsic tenocytes. Scale bar = 1&#x02009;cm. Representative images of Tenascin C (<bold>b</bold>&#x02013;<bold>g</bold>) and Scleraxis (<bold>h</bold>&#x02013;<bold>m</bold>) staining in tenocyte and fibroblast cells isolated from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice. Positive staining was detected in tenocyte cells for both Tenascin-C and Scleraxis, and no expression was noted in fibroblasts. Magnification &#x000d7; 20, scale bar = 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;M. Graphical representation of mean fluorescence intensity of Tenascin C (<bold>n</bold>) and Scleraxis (<bold>o</bold>) staining. Tenascin-C staining was significantly higher in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> cells compared to WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> cells. Data is represented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. *<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05, **<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.01, <italic>n</italic> = 6</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13018_2020_1692_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Flii is differentially expressed in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes in response to scratch wounding</title><p id="Par26">Previous studies have shown that Flii is upregulated in fibroblasts in response to wounding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Here we examined Flii levels in wounded <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes. Confluent monolayers of tenocytes isolated from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice were scratch wounded and immunofluorescently stained for Flii at 3, 6, 12, and 24&#x02009;h post-wounding. Representative images can be seen in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a&#x02013;l. <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes showed significantly higher Flii expression at 3, 6, 12, and 24&#x02009;h than WT (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0006, 0.0002, 0.00002, and 0.00002, respectively) and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> tenocytes (<italic>p</italic> = 0.000005, 0.00005, 0.00001, and 0.00003, respectively) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a&#x02013;m). Flii staining was apparent at all time points and peaked at 12&#x02009;h post-wounding. The staining was mainly perinuclear in distribution, although some cytoplasmic staining was also seen in the later time points.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Flii expression in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes. Confluent tenocytes were scratch-wounded and stained for Flii expression at 3, 6, 12, and 24&#x02009;h post-wounding. <bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>l</bold> Representative images showing Flii expression in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes at 3, 6, 12, and 24&#x02009;h post-wounding. Magnification &#x000d7; 10. Scale bar = 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;M. Flii represented by white arrows (<bold>m</bold>) Graphical representation of Flii expression in tenocytes. <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes express significantly more Flii than WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> tenocytes. *<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup>. <sup>^</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> and WT. <sup>+</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> and WT. Data represented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. <italic>n</italic> = 6</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13018_2020_1692_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Tenocyte migration is regulated by Flii</title><p id="Par27">Previous studies have established the role for Flii in regulating cell migration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Here we examined the effect of Flii on tenocyte migration and compared it to effects seen in fibroblasts. Isolated primary tenocytes and fibroblasts from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice were scratch wounded and cellular migration measured over 24&#x02009;h. Increased <italic>Flii</italic> expression resulted in faster cellular migration in tenocytes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a&#x02013;c) with the <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes showing significantly faster migration than <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> tenocytes across the entire time course measured (<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.001) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>g). <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes also showed significantly faster migration than WT tenocytes at 21 and 24&#x02009;h post-scratch wounding (<italic>p</italic> = 0.05 and 0.02, respectively). At 24&#x02009;h post-scratch wounding, <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocyte wounds had fully closed whereas <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> tenocyte wounds were still 25% open, suggesting that increased levels of Flii improve the migratory ability of primary murine tenocytes. In contrast, murine fibroblast cells showed that decreased <italic>Flii</italic> expression improved cellular migration (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d&#x02013;f), with scratch wounded <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> fibroblasts showing significantly faster closure than <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> fibroblasts across the whole time course (<italic>p</italic> = &#x02264; 0.001) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d&#x02013;f, h).
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><italic>Flii</italic> regulates tenocyte cellular migration. An in vitro scratch wound model was used to investigate the effect of differential <italic>Flii</italic> on tenocyte migration. <bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>c</bold> Representative images of scratch wounds in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes at 24&#x02009;h post-wounding. <bold>d</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold> Representative images of scratch wounds in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> fibroblasts at 24&#x02009;h post-wounding. Magnification &#x000d7; 4. Scale bar = 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;M. <bold>g</bold> Graph showing scratch closure in tenocytes expressed as percentage of original wound size. <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes show significantly improved wound closure. <bold>h</bold> Graph showing scratch closure in fibroblasts expressed as percentage of original wound size. <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> fibroblasts show significantly improved wound closure. *<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup>. <sup>^</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> and WT. <sup>+</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> and WT. Data represented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. <italic>n</italic> = 6</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13018_2020_1692_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Tenocyte cellular outgrowth is regulated by Flii</title><p id="Par28">Flii has previously been shown to regulate cellular outgrowth including both fibroblasts and keratinocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. To investigate the effect of <italic>Flii</italic> on tenocyte cellular outgrowth, 2 mm<sup>3</sup> sections of digital tendons, cleaned of their sheaths, from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice were placed onto collagen type I coated plates in culture, and the average outgrowth measured over 12&#x02009;days (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a&#x02013;d). <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes had significantly increased cellular outgrowth across all 12&#x02009;days when compared to WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> tenocytes (<italic>p</italic> = 0.007 and 0.0005, respectively, at day 12), with <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> cells showing a 2-fold increase in cellular migration by day 12 compared to <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a&#x02013;d). A dense collection of cells migrated out of <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> and WT explants by day 3, whereas <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> showed a less dense, slower initial migration. These cells stained positive for Scleraxis confirming the tenocyte phenotype (data not shown).
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Differential effect of <italic>Flii</italic> expression on tenocyte outgrowth from tendon explants. 2 mm<sup>3</sup> sections of tendons from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup>mice were cultured for 12&#x02009;days and tenocyte outgrowth measured as average migration distance. <bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>c</bold> Representative images of cellular outgrowth in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes at 12&#x02009;days post seeding. Dotted line + arrow = outgrowth distance. Magnification &#x000d7; 4. Scale bar = 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;M. <bold>d</bold><italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes have significantly increased outgrowth compared to WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> tenocytes. Data represented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. *<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05, <italic>n</italic> = 6</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13018_2020_1692_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes have significantly improved proliferation</title><p id="Par29">Using primary murine tenocytes and fibroblasts from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice, we examined the effect of altering the level of <italic>Flii</italic> on proliferation using a 24-h WST-1 assay. In tenocytes, increased <italic>Flii</italic> resulted in improved cellular proliferation (<italic>p</italic> = 0.01 compared to <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). In contrast, fibroblasts showed that increased <italic>Flii</italic> levels resulted in a decrease in cellular proliferation (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03 compared to <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b).
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Increased Flii levels increases tenocyte proliferation. Murine tenocytes and fibroblasts from in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice were used in a 24-h WST-1 assay to determine the effect of Flii on cellular proliferation. <bold>a</bold> Graphical representation of tenocyte proliferation in the three genotypes. <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes showed significantly improved cellular proliferation. <bold>b</bold> Graphical representation of fibroblast proliferation in the three genotypes. <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> tenocytes showed significantly improved cellular proliferation. *<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05. Data represented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. <italic>n</italic> = 6</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13018_2020_1692_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Flii has minimal effect on tenocyte contraction</title><p id="Par30"><italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes and fibroblasts were incorporated into a 3D floating collagen gel matrix and left for 72&#x02009;h to assess the rate of contraction. Minimal contraction was seen in the tenocyte gels across the 72&#x02009;h with no significant difference seen between the genotypes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a&#x02013;c, g). In contrast, significant contraction was seen in the fibroblast gels across the 72&#x02009;h, with <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> gels showing significantly increased contraction than WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> gels at 48&#x02009;h (<italic>p</italic> = 0.004 and 0.0001, respectively) and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> at 72&#x02009;h (<italic>p</italic> = 0.00007) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>d&#x02013;f, h).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Flii affects collagen type I and collagen type III production in unwounded fibroblasts but not tenocytes</title><p id="Par31">Collagen type I is the main component of tendons, providing stability and strength. Here the effect of <italic>Flii</italic> on collagen type I and III production in tenocytes and fibroblasts from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice was investigated. No significant difference was observed in collagen type I production in tenocytes with different levels of Flii; however, fibroblasts were observed to have secreted significantly more collagen type I than the tenocytes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>i&#x02013;o). Overexpression of <italic>Flii</italic> in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> fibroblasts significantly decreased collagen type I production when compared with fibroblasts from WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> mice (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0002 and 0.03, respectively) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>l&#x02013;o). Similarly, no significant difference in collagen type III production was observed in the tenocytes across all three genotypes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>p&#x02013;r, v); however, fibroblasts showed an overall significant increase in collagen type III production (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>s&#x02013;v) Furthermore, <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> fibroblasts showed significantly increased collagen type III secretion when compared to fibroblasts from WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> mice (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0002 and 0.003, respectively) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>v).
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Effect of <italic>Flii</italic> on collagen contraction and production in fibroblasts and tenocytes. Contraction of tenocyte and fibroblast populated collagen gels was analyzed over 72&#x02009;h. <bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>c</bold> Representative images of tenocyte populated 3D collagen gels at 72&#x02009;h post-plating. <bold>d</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold> Representative images of fibroblast populated 3D collagen gels at 72&#x02009;h post-plating. Scale bar = 2.5&#x02009;mm and refers to all images. <bold>g</bold> No significant difference seen in contraction in tenocytes across 72&#x02009;h. <bold>h</bold><italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> fibroblasts have increased cellular contraction over 72&#x02009;h. *<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup>. <sup>^</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> and WT. <sup>+</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> and WT. Data represented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. <italic>n</italic> = 6. Confluent tenocytes and fibroblasts from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice were left for 48&#x02009;h in a 2D culture to allow the accumulation of secreted collagen type I. <bold>i</bold>&#x02013;<bold>k</bold> Representative images show no significant difference in collagen type I secretion in tenocytes across all three genotypes. <bold>l</bold>&#x02013;<bold>n</bold> Overexpression of <italic>Flii</italic> significantly decreased the level of collagen type I secretion in fibroblasts. Magnification &#x000d7; 10, scale bar = 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;M. <bold>o</bold> Graphical representation of collagen type I secretion in fibroblasts and tenocytes. Data is represented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. *<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05, **<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.01. <italic>n</italic> = 6. Confluent fibroblasts and tenocytes from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice were left for 48&#x02009;h in a 2D culture to allow the accumulation of secreted collagen type III. <bold>p</bold>&#x02013;<bold>r</bold> There was no difference seen in collagen type III secretion in tenocytes across all three genotypes. <bold>s</bold>&#x02013;<bold>u</bold> Representative images show that overexpression of <italic>Flii</italic> significantly increased the level of collagen type III secretion in fibroblasts. Magnification &#x000d7; 10, scale bar = 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;M. <bold>v</bold> Graphical representation of collagen type III secretion in fibroblasts and tenocytes. Data is represented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. *<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05, **<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.01. <italic>n</italic> = 6</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13018_2020_1692_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Collagen type I production is delayed in scratch-wounded <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes</title><p id="Par32">Previous studies have shown that Flii can regulate collagen I production during cutaneous wound healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Here we examined the effect of differential Flii expression on collagen type I production by wounded tenocytes using established collagen I assay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Tenocytes from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice were scratch-wounded and immunofluorescently stained for collagen type I expression at 3, 6, 12, and 24&#x02009;h post-wounding (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a&#x02013;l). <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes had a significant delay in peak collagen type I expression at 12&#x02009;h post-wounding compared to <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>collagen type I expression at 3&#x02009;h post-wounding; however, the peak level of collagen type I expression was not significantly different (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a&#x02013;m). Collagen type I expression had returned to basal levels in the <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> tenocytes by 12&#x02009;h and remained low for the rest of the experiment whereas there was still elevated expression in the <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes by 24&#x02009;h (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>m).
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p><italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes show decreased collagen type I expression in response to wounding in vitro. Confluent tenocytes were scratch-wounded and stained for collagen type I expression at 3, 6, 12, and 24&#x02009;h post-wounding. <bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>l</bold> Representative images showing collagen type I expression in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes at 3, 6, 12, and 24&#x02009;h post-wounding. Magnification &#x000d7; 10. Scale bar = 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;M. Collagen type I represented by white arrows. <bold>m</bold> Graphical representation of collagen type I expression in tenocytes. <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes show a later peak of collagen type I release than <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> cells. *<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup>. <sup>^</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> and WT. <sup>+</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> and WT. Data represented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. <italic>n</italic> = 6</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13018_2020_1692_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title><italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes express significantly less TGF&#x003b2;1 during healing</title><p id="Par33">TGF&#x003b2;1 is often referred to as the pro-scarring growth factor in the TGF&#x003b2; family, and increased levels of this growth factor are generally associated with poorer healing outcomes and more significant scarring and fibrosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Previous studies have described the effect of differential Flii levels on TGF-&#x003b2; expression during wound healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Here we examined the effect if differential Flii levels on tenocyte TGF-&#x003b2;1 expression. Tenocytes from <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> mice were scratch-wounded and immunofluorescently stained for TGF&#x003b2;1 expression at 3, 6, 12, and 24&#x02009;h post-wounding (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a&#x02013;l). TGF&#x003b2;1 expression was significantly decreased across all time points in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes compared to WT (<italic>p</italic> = 0.03, 0.0005, 0.003, and 0.01, respectively) and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> tenocytes (<italic>p</italic> = 0.0003, 0.00003, 0.00007, and 0.00004, respectively) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>a&#x02013;m). Tenocytes showed a significant increase in expression between 3&#x02013;6&#x02009;h, suggesting secretion of TGF&#x003b2;1 occurs early in the healing process, with a gradual decline in expression over the remainder of the experiment (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>m).
<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p><italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes express significantly less TGF&#x003b2;1 than WT or <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> tenocytes following scratch wounding in vitro. Confluent tenocytes were scratch-wounded and stained for TGF&#x003b2;1 expression at 3, 6, 12, and 24&#x02009;h post-wounding. <bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>l</bold> Representative images showing TGF&#x003b2;1 expression in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes at 3, 6, 12, and 24&#x02009;h post-wounding. Magnification &#x000d7; 10. Scale bar = 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;M. TGF&#x003b2;1 represented by white arrows. <bold>m</bold> Graphical representation of TGF&#x003b2;1 expression in tenocytes. TGF&#x003b2;1 expression is significantly decreased in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>TgTg</italic></sup> tenocytes compared to WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> cells. *<italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup>. <sup>^</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> and WT. <sup>+</sup><italic>p</italic> &#x02264; 0.05 between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> and WT. Data represented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. <italic>n</italic> = 6</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13018_2020_1692_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par34">Tendon injuries represent a multifaceted model of cellular change, requiring a complex re-organization of the actin cytoskeleton in order to facilitate essential processes for healing including migration, proliferation, contraction, and secretion. Tenocytes make up the majority of the cellular content in tendons and are integral in coordinating the healing process following injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Tenocytes are responsible for releasing signaling molecules to recruit a variety of growth factors, cytokines, and inflammatory cells to the injury site in order to facilitate successful healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. It is well established that both tenocytes and dermal fibroblasts are of mesodermal origin, and both cell types exhibit similar spindle-shaped morphology when grown in in vitro culture. Both produce major extracellular matrix proteins and growth factors in response to injury. For these reasons, tenocyte function is often compared to dermal fibroblasts; however, it is important to note that they are distinct cell types. Tenocytes are mechanosensitive cells with unique properties that detect and respond to changes in mechanical load via deformation of their cell membrane and actin cytoskeleton [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Our findings that tenocytes and fibroblasts exhibit different cellular responses to changes in <italic>Flii</italic> gene expression aligns with previous studies that have shown tenocytes behave differently to dermal fibroblasts in vitro [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] as well as previous studies that show <italic>Flii</italic> positively affects digit regeneration and rodent vibrissa healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p><p id="Par35">Previous studies have shown that the upregulation of Flii is associated with impaired migration, proliferation, and adhesion of both fibroblasts and keratinocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Flii has previously been reported to act as an intracellular protein that affects actin remodeling and cytoskeleton organization through association with different signaling proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Importantly, Flii translocates from the cytoplasm to the nucleus in response to wounding in fibroblasts but not keratinocytes. This suggests that the cell-specific nuclear translocation of Flii may directly regulate gene expression in fibroblasts but not keratinocytes, providing a potential mechanism of action for Flii in wound healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Using an inducible ROSA26 system to conditionally over-express Flii in fibroblasts resulted in impaired healing responses suggesting that fibroblast-specific production of Flii contributes to wound impaired healing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In this study, increased Flii expression in tenocytes led to an improvement in tenocyte migration, proliferation, and outgrowth, providing more support for the important cell-specific and cell-type-dependent functions of Flii.</p><p id="Par36">Cellular migration is an essential part of the healing process, allowing cells to move across a space created by an injury, to re-establish continuity and strength to an injured area. In order for cells to migrate, a complex cascade of events occurs, with actin assembly driving lamellipodia and filopodia forward, and adhesions forming to anchor the cell body to the surface [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Rear adhesions disassemble to allow the cell to retract its rear edge and the cell to move forward. Actin reassembly is integral to this process and actin remodeling proteins such as Flii are essential to ensure this progression occurs correctly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes showed significantly improved migration and proliferation over 24&#x02009;h compared with WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> counterparts, indicating the important role of Flii in regulating tenocyte adhesion, migration, and proliferation. These findings are in agreement with previous studies showing Flii association with different signaling proteins involved in actin rearrangement including Cdc42 and the Ras-dependent adenylyl cyclase pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Additionally, studies have shown that Flii regulates focal adhesion turn-over and cell migration by inhibition of paxillin phosphorylation via a Rac-1-dependent pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] and its ability to cap actin filaments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Experiments presented in this manuscript show the effects of Flii on tenocyte cell function, further supporting the role of Flii in regulating cellular responses during homeostasis and in response to wounding.</p><p id="Par37">Fibroblasts and tenocytes are both of mesodermal origin and both display similar morphology in vitro as well as being producers of major extracellular proteins such as collagen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Collagen type I is the main component of tendons and tendon adhesions and is an essential protein synthesized during the healing process, providing structure and tensile strength. No significant difference in collagen type I production was observed in the tenocytes while fibroblasts secreted significantly more collagen type I. Overexpression of <italic>Flii</italic> in <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> fibroblasts significantly decreased collagen type I production when compared to fibroblasts from WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> mice. Again, there was no significant difference in collagen type III secretion seen between tenocytes across all three genotypes while fibroblasts showed an overall significant increase in collagen type III production. Flii does have an effect on both collagen type I and collagen type III production as seen in fibroblasts, both in this study and previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. It is, however, the lack of collagen production seen in tenocytes suggest that these cells are less metabolically active than fibroblasts during the &#x0201c;stationary phase&#x0201d; of cell mitosis; this is supported by Stoll et al. that showed slow proliferation and unstable tenocyte phenotype in monolayer cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. In response to wounding, collagen production in tenocytes is increased and the ratio of collagen type I and collagen type III is also increased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. One limitation of this study is the lack of in vivo studies and future in vivo studies in Flii genetic mice will provide more information about the potential effect of differential Flii levels on collagen type I and collagen type III production and organization during the healing of tendon injuries. ECM disorganization is known as a major hallmark in tendinopathy when a significant decrease in type I collagen is prevalent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par38">No significant difference was observed between <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>, WT, and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes in a 3D collagen gel contraction model suggesting that <italic>Flii</italic> does not affect tenocyte contraction. Interestingly, this was opposite to previous observations on the effect of Flii on fibroblast collagen gel contraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Embryonic tenocytes have actin-rich fibripositors which act via contraction in order to form the &#x0201c;crimp&#x0201d; structure seen in established tendons. This structure is vital for the mechanical shock-absorbing behavior of mature tendons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Adult tendons show minimal contraction during healing and the &#x0201c;crimp&#x0201d; structure tends to be lost in the re-established tendon after healing is complete. So, although <italic>Flii</italic> appears to have minimal effect on adult tenocyte contraction in vitro, <italic>Flii</italic> is an important developmental regulator [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] and has been shown to be involved in fibroblast contraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], and so further investigations into its role in embryonic tenocyte cell contraction should be examined.</p><p id="Par39">Many studies have shown that TGF&#x003b2;1 is a regulator of fibrosis, and excess TGF&#x003b2;1 levels have been associated with poorer healing outcomes and excessive scarring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. This is associated with the inflammatory phase of healing and prolonged expression of TGF&#x003b2;1 can lead to an extension of the inflammatory phase which could contribute towards poorer healing outcomes. In a cutaneous burn injury model, elevated Flii leads to increased TGF&#x003b2; gene expression and reduced Flii levels are linked with decreased TGF&#x003b2;1 expression leading to better healing outcomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. To investigate the possible mechanisms behind which overexpression of <italic>Flii</italic> in tenocytes may affect collagen deposition, the expression of TGF&#x003b2;1 in response to in vitro scratch wounding of tenocytes was investigated. <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes expressed significantly less TGF&#x003b2;1 compared with their WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> counterparts. TGF&#x003b2;1 has been shown to increase collagen type I production resulting in excessive and disordered organization, leading to increased tendon adhesion size and severity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes expressed significantly lower TGF&#x003b2;1 levels during migration, and at 12&#x02009;h post-scratch wounding, these cells had significantly lower collagen type I levels than their WT and <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> counterparts. Decreased levels of pro-scarring TGF&#x003b2;1 coupled with decreased and more controlled production of type I collagen, by <italic>Flii</italic><sup><italic>Tg/Tg</italic></sup> tenocytes, suggest a potential positive role for Flii on healing of tendon injuries.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par40">Fibroblast behavior has been extensively studied in cutaneous healing experiments, and a reduction in <italic>Flii</italic> results in improved fibroblast migration, proliferation, adhesion, and contraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The opposite is observed in tenocytes in this study suggesting cell-specific effects of Flii may occur in response to different stimuli. This study clearly suggests a positive role for Flii in regulating tenocyte proliferation and migration. In conjunction with decreased collagen type I and TGF-&#x003b2; production post wounding, this identifies Flii as a novel target for modulating tenocyte activity and for improving tendon repair. While the exact mechanism of Flii effects on tendon repair is still to be determined, the outcome of this study may help to advance new therapeutic approaches aimed at improving the healing of tendon injuries.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>DAPI</term><def><p id="Par5">4&#x02032;,6-Diamindino-2-phenylindole</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ECM</term><def><p id="Par6">Cell-extracellular matrix</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Flii</term><def><p id="Par7">Flightless</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LRR</term><def><p id="Par8">Leucine-rich repeat</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MTJ</term><def><p id="Par9">Myotendinous junction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TGF-&#x003b2;</term><def><p id="Par10">Transforming growth factor beta</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WT</term><def><p id="Par11">Wild-type</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>AJC, PJA, and ZK conceived all experiments. JEJ performed all experiments and analysis with the assistance of ZK. All authors contributed to manuscript writing and have approved the final submitted and published versions.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by an Australian Postgraduate Award scholarship to JEJ. ZK is supported by a Foundation Fellowship from University of South Australia. AJC is supported by NHMRC Senior Research Fellowship GNT#1102617.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par41">All experiments and maintenance of mice were conducted according to Australian Standards for Animal Care under protocols approved by the Women&#x02019;s and Children&#x02019;s Health Network Animal Ethics Committee (WCHN) and carried out in accordance with the Australian code of practice for the care and use of animals for scientific purpose (AE952/9/2016).</p></notes><notes id="FPar2"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par42">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par43">The authors declare they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Legrand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular biology of flexor tendon healing in relation to reduction of tendon adhesions</article-title><source>J Hand Surg Am.</source><year>2017</year><volume>42</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>722</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhsa.2017.06.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28709791?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28709791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Maffulli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tendon injury and tendinopathy: healing and repair</article-title><source>J Bone Joint Surg Am</source><year>2005</year><volume>87</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15634833?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15634833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tendon healing in vitro: genetic modification of tenocytes with exogenous PDGF gene and promotion of collagen gene expression</article-title><source>J Hand Surg</source><year>2004</year><volume>29</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>884</fpage><lpage>890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhsa.2004.05.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Maffulli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic biology of tendon injury and healing</article-title><source>Surgeon</source><year>2005</year><volume>3</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1479-666X(05)80109-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16245649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16245649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical implications of growth factors in flexor tendon wound healing</article-title><source>J Hand Surg</source><year>2004</year><volume>29</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhsa.2004.04.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Longaker</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential expression of transforming growth factor-beta receptors in a rabbit zone II flexor tendon wound healing model</article-title><source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1260</fpage><lpage>1267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00006534-200110000-00025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11604629?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11604629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Yalamanchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Longaker</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flexor tendon healing in vitro: effects of TGF-&#x003b2; on tendon cell collagen production</article-title><source>J Hand Surg</source><year>2002</year><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/jhsu.2002.34004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Strudwick</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Flightless I deficiency enhances wound repair by increasing cell migration and proliferation</article-title><source>J Pathol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>211</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>572</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/path.2143</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17326236?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17326236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopecki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flightless I: an actin-remodelling protein and an important negative regulator of wound repair</article-title><source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1415</fpage><lpage>1419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocel.2007.04.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17526423?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17526423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molloy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Murrell</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The roles of growth factors in tendon and ligament healing</article-title><source>Sports Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00007256-200333050-00004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12696985?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12696985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davy</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fountain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Crouch</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The flightless I protein colocalizes with actin- and microtubule-based structures in motile Swiss 3&#x02009;T3 fibroblasts: evidence for the involvement of PI 3-kinase and Ras-related small GTPases</article-title><source>J Cell Sci.</source><year>2001</year><volume>114</volume><issue>Pt 3</issue><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>562</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11171324?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11171324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knaup</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mavroidis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stathakis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Papanikolaou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the effect of prostate volume change on tumor control probability in LDR brachytherapy</article-title><source>J Contemp Brachytherapy.</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5114/jcb.2011.24818</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23346121?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23346121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopecki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of focal adhesions by Flightless I involves inhibition of paxillin phosphorylation via a Rac1-dependent pathway</article-title><source>J Invest Dermatol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>131</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1450</fpage><lpage>1459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2011.69</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21430700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21430700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopecki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Melville</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Flightless I over-expression impairs skin barrier development, function and recovery following skin blistering</article-title><source>J Pathol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>232</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/path.4323</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24375017?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24375017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davy</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthaei</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Crouch</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The flightless I protein localizes to actin-based structures during embryonic development</article-title><source>Immunol Cell Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>78</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1711.2000.00926.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10947868?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10947868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopecki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Strudwick</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overexpression of the Flii gene increases dermal-epidermal blistering in an autoimmune ColVII mouse model of epidermolysis bullosa acquisita</article-title><source>J Pathol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>225</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/path.2973</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21984127?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21984127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopecki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flightless I regulates hemidesmosome formation and integrin-mediated cellular adhesion and migration during wound repair</article-title><source>J Invest Dermatol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>129</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2031</fpage><lpage>2045</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2008.461</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19212345?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19212345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kopecki Z, Ruzehaji N, Turner C, Iwata H, Ludwig RJ, Zillikens D, et al. Topically applied Flightless I neutralizing antibodies improve healing of blistered skin in a murine model of epidermolysis bullosa acquisita. J Invest Dermatol. 2012.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chappell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthaei</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mouse strains for the ubiquitous or conditional overexpression of the Flii gene</article-title><source>Genesis.</source><year>2011</year><volume>49</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/dvg.20735</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21786402?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21786402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopecki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoskeletal protein flightless I differentially affects TGF-beta isoform expression in both in vitro and in vivo wound models</article-title><source>Wound Pract Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>169</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fountain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McLennan</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Berven</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crouch</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Davy</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fliih, a gelsolin-related cytoskeletal regulator essential for early mammalian embryonic development</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3518</fpage><lpage>3526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.22.10.3518-3526.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11971982?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11971982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ideno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiunten</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficient expansion of mouse primary tenocytes using a novel collagen gel culture method</article-title><source>Histochem Cell Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>142</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00418-014-1191-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24509807?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24509807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bestwick</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bestwick</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Maffulli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Aspden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenotypic drift in human tenocyte culture</article-title><source>Tissue Eng</source><year>2006</year><volume>12</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1843</fpage><lpage>1849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ten.2006.12.1843</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16889514?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16889514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shukunami</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Takimoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiraki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scleraxis positively regulates the expression of tenomodulin, a differentiation marker of tenocytes</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>298</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2006.06.036</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16876153?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16876153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kopecki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Luchetti</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Strudwick</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantamadiotis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoppacciaro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Collagen loss and impaired wound healing is associated with c-Myb deficiency</article-title><source>J Pathol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>211</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/path.2113</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17152050?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17152050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>W-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>J-HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>F-C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-level laser irradiation stimulates tenocyte migration with up-regulation of dynamin II expression</article-title><source>PLoS One.</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e38235</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038235</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22666495?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22666495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wohlmuth</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Native Australian plant extracts differentially induce collagen I and collagen III in vitro and could be important targets for the development of new wound healing therapies</article-title><source>Fitoterapia.</source><year>2016</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2015.12.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26705840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26705840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughan-Thomas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinchbeck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Macrory</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression markers of tendon fibroblasts in normal and diseased tissue compared to monolayer and three dimensional culture systems</article-title><source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord.</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>27</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2474-10-27</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19245707?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19245707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murchison</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Keene</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabin</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of tendon differentiation by scleraxis distinguishes force-transmitting tendons from muscle-anchoring tendons</article-title><source>Development.</source><year>2007</year><volume>134</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>2697</fpage><lpage>2708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.001933</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17567668?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17567668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brosnan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of TGF-beta and its receptors in murine fetal and adult dermal wounds</article-title><source>Eur J Dermatol</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11525949?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11525949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopecki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoskeletal protein Flightless I differentially affects TGF-&#x003b2; isoform expression in both in vitro and in vivo wound models</article-title><source>Wound Pract Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>22</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>181</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andarawis-Puri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Flatow</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Soslowsky</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tendon basic science: development, repair, regeneration, and healing</article-title><source>J Orthop Res.</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>780</fpage><lpage>784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.22869</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25764524?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25764524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lui</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapacee</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadler</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>McGrouther</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cellular biology of flexor tendon adhesion formation: an old problem in a new paradigm</article-title><source>Am J Pathol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>175</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1938</fpage><lpage>1951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2353/ajpath.2009.090380</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19834058?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19834058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Trail</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibroblast-like cells from tendons differ from skin fibroblasts in their ability to form three-dimensional structures in vitro</article-title><source>J Hand Surg Br.</source><year>1998</year><volume>23</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0266-7681(98)80018-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9821610?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9821610</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strudwick</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flightless I expression enhances murine claw regeneration following digit amputation</article-title><source>J Invest Dermatol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>137</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jid.2016.08.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27595936?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27595936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindo</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regeneration of hair follicles is modulated by Flightless I (Flii) in a rodent vibrissa model</article-title><source>J Invest Dermatol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2010.393</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21191408?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21191408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Waters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibroblast-specific upregulation of Flightless I impairs wound healing</article-title><source>Exp Dermatol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>24</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>692</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/exd.12751</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25959103?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25959103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goshima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kariya K-i, Yamawaki-Kataoka Y, Okada T, Shibatohge M, Shima F, et al. Characterization of a novel Ras-binding protein Ce-FLI-1 comprising leucine-rich repeats and gelsolin-like domains</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source><year>1999</year><volume>257</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1999.0420</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10092519?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10092519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Woroniuk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vennin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Timpson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential Rac1 signalling by guanine nucleotide exchange factors implicates FLII in regulating Rac1-driven cell migration</article-title><source>Nature Commun</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>10664</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms10664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26887924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Naghibzadeh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mascarenhas</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Flightless I is a focal adhesion-associated actin-capping protein that regulates cell migration</article-title><source>FASEB J.</source><year>2012</year><volume>26</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3260</fpage><lpage>3272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.11-202051</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22581781?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22581781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tang Q-M, Chen JL, Shen WL, Yin Z, Liu HH, Fang Z, et al. Fetal and adult fibroblasts display intrinsic differences in tendon tissue engineering and regeneration. Sci Reports. 2014;4.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stoll</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Endres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaps</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extracellular matrix expression of human tenocytes in three-dimensional air-liquid and PLGA cultures compared with tendon tissue: implications for tendon tissue engineering</article-title><source>J Orthop Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1170</fpage><lpage>1177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.21109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20187116?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20187116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thankam</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dilisio</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Collagen I: a kingpin for rotator cuff tendon pathology</article-title><source>Am J Transl Res.</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3291</fpage><lpage>3309</lpage><?supplied-pmid 30662587?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30662587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herchenhan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalson</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadler</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Margetts</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tenocyte contraction induces crimp formation in tendon-like tissue</article-title><source>Biomech Model Mechanobiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3-4</issue><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10237-011-0324-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21735243?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21735243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kapacee</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Starborg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Baar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tension is required for fibripositor formation</article-title><source>Matrix Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.matbio.2007.11.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18262777?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18262777</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Doetschman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenhalgh</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Delayed wound healing in immunodeficient TGF-&#x003b2;1 knockout mice</article-title><source>J Invest Dermatol</source><year>2000</year><volume>115</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1523-1747.2000.00010.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10886500?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10886500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Longaker</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of TGF-&#x003b2;-induced collagen production in rabbit flexor tendons</article-title><source>J Hand Surg</source><year>2004</year><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhsa.2003.11.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruzehaji</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Strudwick</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Arkell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Attenuation of Flightless I, an actin-remodelling protein, improves burn injury repair via modulation of transforming growth factor (TGF)-&#x003b2;1 and TGF-&#x003b2;3</article-title><source>Br J Dermatol</source><year>2009</year><volume>161</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2133.2009.09296.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19519830?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19519830</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>