<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cell Death Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cell Death Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cell Death &#x00026; Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-4889</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7214449</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2529</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-020-2529-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transgelin is a poor prognostic factor associated with advanced colorectal cancer (CRC) stage promoting tumor growth and migration in a TGF&#x003b2;-dependent manner</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7096-998X</contrib-id><name><surname>Elsafadi</surname><given-names>Mona</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manikandan</surname><given-names>Muthurangan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Almalki</surname><given-names>Sami</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9199-0120</contrib-id><name><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>Amer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shinwari</surname><given-names>Tasneem</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vishnubalaji</surname><given-names>Radhakrishnan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mobarak</surname><given-names>Mohammad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alfayez</surname><given-names>Musaad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aldahmash</surname><given-names>Abdullah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kassem</surname><given-names>Moustapha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Alajez</surname><given-names>Nehad M.</given-names></name><address><email>nalajez@hbku.edu.qa</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 5396</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.56302.32</institution-id><institution>Stem Cell Unit, Department of Anatomy, College of Medicine, </institution><institution>King Saud University, </institution></institution-wrap>Riyadh, 11461 Kingdom of Saudi Arabia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0516 2170</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.418818.c</institution-id><institution>Cancer Research Center, Qatar Biomedical Research Institute (QBRI), Hamad Bin Khalifa University (HBKU), </institution><institution>Qatar Foundation (QF), </institution></institution-wrap>Doha, Qatar </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 5396</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.56302.32</institution-id><institution>Department of Histopathology, College of Medicine, </institution><institution>King Saud University, </institution></institution-wrap>Riyadh, 11461 Saudi Arabia </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0512 5013</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7143.1</institution-id><institution>Molecular Endocrinology Unit (KMEB), Department of Endocrinology, </institution><institution>University Hospital of Odense and University of Southern Denmark, </institution></institution-wrap>Odense, Denmark </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>341</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the fourth most common cancer type globally. Investigating the signaling pathways that maintain cancer cell phenotype can identify new biomarkers for targeted therapy. Aberrant transforming growth factor-&#x003b2; (TGF&#x003b2;) signaling has been implicated in CRC progression, however, the exact mechanism by which TGF&#x003b2; exerts its function is still being unraveled. Herein, we investigated TAGLN expression, prognostic value, and its regulation by TGF&#x003b2; in CRC. While TAGLN was generally found to be downregulated in CRC, elevated expression of TAGLN was associated with advanced CRC stage and predicted poor overall survival (hazard ratio (HR)&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.8, log-rank test <italic>P</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.014) and disease-free survival (HR&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.6, log-rank test <italic>P</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.046), hence implicating TAGLN as poor prognostic factor in CRC. Forced expression of TAGLN was associated with enhanced CRC cell proliferation, clonogenic growth, cell migration and in vivo tumor formation in immunocompromised mice, while targeted depletion of TAGLN exhibited opposing biological effects. Global gene expression profiling of TAGLN-overexpressing or TAGLN-deficient CRC cell lines revealed deregulation of multiple cancer-related genes and signaling pathways. Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) revealed ultrastructural changes due to loss of TAGLN, including disruption of actin cytoskeleton organization and aberrant actin filament distribution. Hierarchical clustering, principle component, and ingenuity pathway analyses revealed distinct molecular profile associated with TAGLN<sup>high</sup> CRC patients with remarkable activation of a number of mechanistic networks, including SMARCA4, TGF&#x003b2;1, and P38 MAPK. The P38 MAPK was the top predicted upstream regulator network promoting cell movement through regulation of several intermediate molecules, including TGF&#x003b2;1. Concordantly, functional categories associated with cellular movement and angiogenesis were also enriched in TAGLN<sup>high</sup> CRC, supporting a model for the molecular mechanisms linking TGF&#x003b2;-induced upregulation of TAGLN and CRC tumor progression and suggesting TAGLN as potential prognostic marker associated with advanced CRC pathological stage.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Colon cancer</kwd><kwd>Cell growth</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>We would like to thank the Deanship of Scientific Research at King Saud University (Research Group No. RG-1438-033) for funding this work</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Colorectal cancer (CRC) is one of the most common malignancies worldwide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. In addition to conventional histopathological phenotyping, recent years have witnessed increased interest in utilizing genetic and molecular signatures as prognostic and predictive biomarkers to identify patients at high risk of progression and recurrence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Over the past years, molecular profiling led to the identification of a number of signaling pathways associated with CRC, where targeting such pathways demonstrated increased clinical efficacy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">The TGF&#x003b2; family, including TGF&#x003b2;1, TGF&#x003b2;2 and TGF&#x003b2;3, is a regulator of several biological processes such as cell differentiation, cell proliferation, apoptosis, angiogenesis, and immune response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Canonical TGF&#x003b2; signaling involves the phosphorylation of R-Smads (SMAD2 and SMAD3) to form a complex with SMAD4 and its translocation into the nucleus, followed by induction of TGF&#x003b2;-responsive genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. The role of TGF&#x003b2;1, which is ubiquitously expressed, in cancer development and progression has been extensively studied. Alterations in TGF&#x003b2; signaling has been observed in several types of cancers, such as breast, lung, bladder, and CRC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. In CRC, TGF&#x003b2; signaling exhibits contradicting effect either as a suppressor or as a stimulator, based on the cancer stage. During early stages, TGF&#x003b2; plays an inhibitory role on tumor cell growth and proliferation by inducing CDK inhibitors (p15 and p21) and suppressing cell cycle stimulators such as Myc, CDK4, and CDC25A<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. However, enhanced TGF&#x003b2; signaling is associated with advanced CRC, low survival rate, and higher risk of recurrence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">TAGLN, also named SM22, is a TGF&#x003b2;-inducible gene highly expressed in many tissues such as bladder, prostate, stomach, colon, and uterus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. TAGLN, a member of the calponin family, is an actin-binding/gelling protein that is localized in the cytoplasm and expressed by many different types of cells, including fibroblasts, endothelial, immune, and smooth muscle cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. As an actin crosslinking protein, TAGLN participates in the process of cell mobility by enhancing the formation of podosomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, and in several biological processes related to cancer progression such as proliferation, differentiation, migration, invasion, and apoptosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. TAGLN-deficient mice are fertile and develop normally, but they show reduced smooth muscle contractility, and pronounced changes in actin filament distribution and cytoskeletal organization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Similar to TGF&#x003b2;, TAGLN expression and function in cancer biology are dependent on the type and stage of cancer, hence the role of TAGLN in CRC biology is controversial<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">We recently reported TAGLN to play a role in skeletal stem cell proliferation, differentiation, and motility through regulation of actin cytoskeletal organization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. In current study, we investigated the role of TGF&#x003b2;-mediated TAGLN expression in the proliferation, migration, and clonogenic potential of CRC cells in vitro and tumor formation in vivo. Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) revealed remarkable ultrastructural alterations in CRC cells with elevated and downregulated TAGLN expression. In addition, we dissected the molecular mechanism of TAGLN function using transcriptome and pathway analyses. Ingenuity pathway analysis revealed enriched functional categories and regulatory networks associated with cell migration, invasion, angiogenesis, and P38 MAPK signaling in CRC tissue exhibiting elevated TAGLN expression.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Cell culture</title><p id="Par6">HCT116 and RKO human colorectal cell lines were purchased from ATCC (Manassas, VA, USA). The HT-29 cell line was purchased from CLS Cell Lines Service (CLS Cell Lines Service GmbH, Eppelheim, Germany). Cells were maintained in Dulbecco&#x02019;s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) containing <sc>d</sc>-glucose 4500&#x02009;mg/L, 110&#x02009;mg/L sodium pyruvate, 4&#x02009;mM <sc>l</sc>-glutamine, and supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), non-essential amino acids (Gibco-Invitrogen, USA), and 1x penicillin&#x02013;streptomycin (Pen&#x02013;strep).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Small-interfering RNA (siRNA) transfection</title><p id="Par7">HT-29 and RKO cell lines were chosen for TAGLN knockdown because they exhibited higher TAGLN expression level (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Cells were transfected with Silencer Select TAGLN-siRNA (25&#x02009;nM; Ambion, USA) using Lipofectamine RNAiMAX reverse-transfection approach (Invitrogen, CA, USA) as per the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>TAGLN expression is associated with advanced tumor stage and predicts worse clinical outcome.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Boxplot comparing the expression of TAGLN in a cohort of colon adenocarcinoma (COAD), <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;275 compared to normal colon tissue (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;349) from the TCGA and GTEx data sets. <bold>b</bold> Stage plot demonstrating TAGLN expression as a function of pathological stage in COAD. Kaplan&#x02013;Meier overall survival (OS, <bold>c</bold>) and disease-free survival (DFS, <bold>d</bold>) as function of median TAGLN expression in COAD.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e490"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Establishment of the TAGLN overexpressing HCT116 cells</title><p id="Par8">HCT116 cell line was chosen for TAGLN overexpression experiments because it exhibited lower basal TAGLN expression. HCT116 overexpressing TAGLN were created using lentiviral transduction approach as we previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Lentifect&#x02122; control lentiviral particles (LP-FLUC-LV105-0205) and particles encoding for human TAGLN (LP-G0046-Lv213-200) were obtained from Genecopoeia (Genecopoeia Inc., Rockville, MD, USA). Hundred thousand cells were seeded in DMEM and 48&#x02009;h later, media was removed and 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of lentiviral particles in 500&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of DMEM&#x02009;+&#x02009;5% heat-inactivated serum and 1% Pen&#x02013;Strep supplemented with 8&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL polybrene (Sigma) were added to the cells. Seventy-two hours later, transduced cells were passaged and were subjected to puromycin selection (1.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/mL, Sigma) to generate stable clones.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Cell proliferation assay</title><p id="Par9">Alamar Blue assay was used to assess cell viability as per the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations (AbD Serotec, Raleigh, NC, USA) as we described before<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Briefly, 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of alamarBlue was added to each well followed by 1&#x02009;h incubation in the dark at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Fluorescence was then measured using BioTek Synergy II microplate reader (BioTek Inc., Winooski, VT, USA) at Ex 530&#x02009;nm/Em 590&#x02009;nm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Scratch assay</title><p id="Par10">In vitro wound-healing assay was conducted as described before<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Briefly, 0.2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> cells/dish were plated in a 30-mm cell culture dish. When confluent, straight line (scratch) was created using a p10 pipette tip. Time-lapse microscopy was conducted using EVOS FL Auto Cell Imaging System (ThermoFisher Scientific Life Sciences). Images were taken every 30&#x02009;min over 4 days.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Transwell migration assay</title><p id="Par11">After 24&#x02009;h incubation in 1% FBS-DMEM, cell migration was assessed using 8&#x02009;&#x000b5;m pore size BD transwell migration system as described before<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>. Inserts were placed in a 12-well plate, and 60&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> cells in 500&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of 1% FBS-DMEM were added to the upper chamber and 1.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of either 1% FBS-DMEM as a control or 10% FBS-DMEM as chemoattractant were added to the bottom chamber. Seventy-two hours later, cells on the upper surface of inserts were scraped using a cotton swap. Subsequently, the cells were fixed and stained with SIEMENNS DIFF-QUICK stain set (Siemens Healthcare Diagnostics). Stained inserts were cut and mounted on microscope slides.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Colony-forming assay</title><p id="Par12">Colony formation assay was conducted as described before<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. Cells were seeded in a 12-well tissue culture plate at different serial dilutions (1:2 to 1:64) with an initial density of 0.015&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> cells in each well and incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C under 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 6 days. Cells were allowed to grow, and on day 6, they were fixed with 70% ethanol and stained with Diff-Quik Stain Set (Siemens Healthcare Diagnostics, Inc., Newark, DE, USA). Images of colonies formed in each well were taken using a Carl Zeiss-Axio Observer 1 microscope equipped with an Axiocam MRc5 digital camera (Carl Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany) at 10x and 20x magnification.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Western blotting</title><p id="Par13">Whole-cell lysates were prepared using RIPA buffer (ThermoFisher Scientific) followed by immunoblotting using TAGLN-specific antibody (ThermoFisher Scientific, CAT# PA5-29767, 1:5000 dilution). B-actin was used as loading control (Sigma, A3854, 1:10,000 dilution). Horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibodies (Santa-Cruz Biotechnology) and the Clarity western ECL substrate (Bio-Rad) were used for signal using C-Digit Blot Scanner (LI-COR).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Transmission electron microscopy (TEM)</title><p id="Par14">Cells under different treatment conditions were trypsinized and were subsequently washed using PBS followed by resuspending the pellets in 2.5% glutaraldehyde fixative (Electron Microscopy Sciences, cat. no. 16500) in 0.1&#x02009;M phosphate buffer (pH 7.2) and kept at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 4&#x02009;h. Next, the cells were washed in 0.1&#x02009;M phosphate buffer (pH 7.2) and then transferred to 1% osmium tetroxide (OsO4) in 0.1&#x02009;M phosphate buffer (pH 7.2). Subsequently, cells were dehydrated using increasing grades of ethanol (10%, 30%, 50%, 70%, 90%, and 100%) for 15&#x02009;min each, and then were resuspended in acetone for 15&#x02009;min. The cells were then aliquoted into BEEM&#x000ae; embedding capsules and were infiltrated with an acetone-resin mixture. Polymerization of the resin was conducted using 70&#x02009;&#x000b0;C oven for 12&#x02009;h. In all, 0.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;m thickness sections were cut and were stained with 1% Toluidine Blue. Subsequently, ultrathin sections (~70-nm thickness) were cut and were fixed on copper grids followed by contrasting using uranyl acetate (saturated ethanol solution) for 30&#x02009;min, rinsed, and then contrasted using Reynold&#x02019;s lead citrate for 5&#x02009;min, followed by final rinse using distilled water. The contrasted ultrathin sections were imaged using TEM (Jeol 1010, Jeol, Tokyo, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>In vivo tumor formation assay</title><p id="Par15">Animal experiments were approved by the appropriate animal care committee. Cells were harvested via trypsinization, washed in PBS, and resuspended in PBS. Approximately 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> cells were suspended in 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;L PBS per each implant and subcutaneously injected into the right flank of 6&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;8-week-old female nude mice, as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Tumor volumes were measured every 2&#x02013;3 days using a caliper. Tumor volumes were calculated using formula (tumor length&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;width<sup>2</sup>)/2. At the end of the experiment (after 6 weeks), remaining tumors were removed, fixed in 10 % formalin, embedded in paraffin, and were subsequently sectioned and stained with hematoxylin and eosin.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Quantitative reverse-transcription PCR (qRT-PCR)</title><p id="Par16">The PureLink kit (Ambion by Life Technologies, USA, Cat No: 12183018A) was used for total RNA extraction as per the manufacturer protocol. Nanodrop spectrophotometer (Nanodrop 2000, Thermo Scientific, USA) was used for total RNA was quantification. The High Capacity cDNA Reverse-Transcription kit (Applied Biosystem, USA) was used to generate complementary DNA (cDNA) from 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of the RNA using the Labnet Multigene thermocycler. Relative expression levels of selected transcripts were measured using real-time PCR (Applied Biosystem-Real-Time PCR Detection System) and the Power SYBR Green PCR master mix (Applied Biosystem, UK) or with the TaqMan Universal Master Mix II, no UNG (Applied Biosystem, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Differential expression was measured using a comparative Ct method and GAPDH as reference gene.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Gene expression profiling</title><p id="Par17">Total RNA was extracted using the PureLink RNA mini kit (Ambion by Life Technologies, USA, Cat No: 12183018A). One-hundred and fifty nanograms of total RNA were initially labeled and then hybridized to the Agilent Human SurePrint G3 Human GE 8&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;60&#x02009;k microarray chip (Agilent Technologies). Microarray experiments were conducted at the Microarray Facility (Stem Cell Unit, King Saud University College of Medicine). GeneSpring GX software (Agilent Technologies) was used for normalization and data analyses. The Single Experiment Pathway analysis feature in GeneSpring 12.0 (Agilent Technologies) was used for pathway analysis. Twofold cutoff with <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.02 were used.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Retrieval of the Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) colon adenocarcinoma (COAD) expression data, and gene set enrichment and modeling of gene interactions networks</title><p id="Par18">COAD TCGA expression data were retrieved from the cBioPortal for Cancer Genomics (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cbioportal.org/">https://www.cbioportal.org/</ext-link>) database as we described before<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. TCGA COAD data were stratified into TAGLN<sup>high</sup> and TAGLN<sup>low</sup> based on median TAGLN expression. Hierarchal and PCA analyses were conducted as we descried before<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Differentially expressed genes in the TAGLN<sup>high</sup> vs TAGLN<sup>low</sup> COAD were imported into the ingenuity pathways analysis (IPA) software (Ingenuity Systems; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ingenuity.com/">www.ingenuity.com/</ext-link>) followed by functional annotations and regulatory network analysis using upstream regulator analysis (URA), downstream effects analysis (DEA), and mechanistic networks (MN) prediction algorithms. <italic>Z</italic>-score was used to determine association significance.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>TAGLN expression and survival analysis in the TCGA/GTEx dataset</title><p id="Par19">The expression of TAGLN in the TCGA/GTEx dataset and its association with tumor stage, overall and disease-free survival was conducted using the GEPIA2 database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gepia2.cancer-pku.cn">http://gepia2.cancer-pku.cn</ext-link>) as described before<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par20">All results are presented as the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation (SD) from at least three independent experiments and <italic>P</italic>-values&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 (using unpaired two-tailed <italic>t</italic>-test) were considered significant. Pearson&#x02019;s correlation was conducted using Graphpad prism 6.0.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec19"><title>TAGLN expression is associated with advanced tumor stage and predicts worse clinical outcome</title><p id="Par21">First, we explored the expression of TAGLN in 275 tumor and 349 normal tissue from the TCGA/GTEx COAD dataset. Interestingly, TAGLN was downregulated in COAD compared to normal colon tissue (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>), which is concordant with our previously published work<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Notably, TAGLN expression was elevated during stage progression (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). Additionally, high TAGLN expression was associated with worse overall survival (OS, hazard ratio (HR)&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.8, log rank <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.014, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>) and worse disease-free survival (DFS, HR&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.6, log rank <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.046, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). Therefore, we postulated loss of TAGLN during early stage and subsequent re-acquisition of TAGLN expression in late stages of COAD, suggesting a possible role for TAGLN in driving colon cancer progression.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>TAGLN enhances CRC cell proliferation and colony formation</title><p id="Par22">To gain better understanding of the role of TAGLN in in CRC biology, we established an HCT116 CRC cell line stably overexpressing TAGLN (HCT116-TAGLN) utilizing lentiviral delivery system. HCT116 cells were chosen because they exhibited low-basal TAGLN expression (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Overexpression of TAGLN in HCT116-TAGLN cells was confirmed by the presence of high levels of the TAGLN mRNA transcript (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>, upper panel) and protein (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>, lower panel). Additionally, we performed siRNA-mediated loss-of-function of TAGLN expression in the RKO CRC line, which has higher basal TAGLN expression (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). siTAGLN transfection led to substantial reduction in TAGLN expression in the RKO model (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Similarly, TPM1, a previously characterized TGF&#x003b2;-responsive gene, was also downregulated in TAGLN-depleted RKO cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2d</xref>). We recently reported that TAGLN is a TGF<italic>&#x003b2;</italic> &#x02013;responsive gene in bone marrow stromal stem cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Thus, we examined the effect of exogenous TGF<italic>&#x003b2;</italic> treatment on TAGLN expression, as well as on the expression of a number of TGF<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-responsive genes (ACTA2, and TPM1), in the RKO colon cancer cell model. Exposing RKO cells to TGF<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>1 (10&#x02009;ng/mL) enhanced TAGLN, ACTA2, and TMP1 mRNA expression (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>). In contrast, inhibition of TGF<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>1 signaling using type I activin receptor-like kinase (ALK) inhibitor, SB431542 (10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m), resulted in downregulation of TAGLN, ACTA2, and TPM1 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>TAGLN is a TGF&#x003b2; responsive gene in CRC.</title><p><bold>a</bold> TAGLN mRNA expression in three different CRC cell lines based on the CCLE database: HCT116, HT-29, and RKO. Expression level is compared to TAGLN expression in HCT116 cells. <bold>b</bold> qRT-PCR of TAGLN expression in HCT116 control cells or cells transduced with TAGLN-overexpressing lentiviral vector (upper panel). Western blotting for TAGLN (upper panel) in HCT116-TAGLN vs. control cells. &#x003b2;-Actin was used as the loading control. QRT-PCR for TAGLN (<bold>c</bold>) or TPM1 (<bold>d</bold>) gene expression 3 days post transfection of RKO cells with TAGLN-siRNA (siTAGLN) or scrambled-siRNA (siScr). Data are presented as fold change in mRNA expresion. <bold>e</bold> qRT-PCR of TAGLN, TPM1, and ACTA2 gene expression in RKO cells treated with TGF&#x003b2;1 (10&#x02009;ng/&#x000b5;l) or SB431542 (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), compared to control cells. The two-tailed <italic>t</italic>-test was used to compare different treatment groups. **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005, ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e766"/></fig></p><p id="Par23">We subsequently investigated the biological ramifications of TAGLN overexpression or knockdown on CRC cells using cell viability and colony formation unit (CFU) assays. TAGLN-HCT116 exhibited significant increase in cell proliferation and colony formation ability (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a, e</xref>). In contrast, downregulation of TAGLN expression was associated with reduced cell proliferation and colony formation employing the HT-29 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b, f</xref>) and RKO (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c, g</xref>) cell models. Similarly, activation or inhibition of TGF&#x003b2; signaling exhibited similar biological effects on the RKO cell model (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d, h</xref>). Taken together, our data suggests a role for TAGLN in promoting CRC proliferation and colony formation.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>TAGLN induces CRC cell proliferation and colony formation.</title><p>Alamar blue assay showing cell viability in HCT116 overexpressing TAGLN compared to control cells (<bold>a</bold>) and in TAGLN-depleted HT-29 (<bold>b</bold>) or RKO (<bold>c</bold>) cells at the indicated time points. <bold>d</bold> Effect of exogenous TGF&#x003b2; (10&#x02009;ng/mL) and TGF&#x003b2; inhibition using SB431542 (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) on RKO cell viability. Data are shown as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;S.D. of at least two independent experiments. *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0005. <bold>e</bold> Representative clonogenic assay showing clonogenicity of HCT116 cells overexpressing TAGLN or TAGLN-depleted HT-29 (<bold>f</bold>) and RKO (<bold>g</bold>) cells. <bold>h</bold> Effects of TGF&#x003b2; (10&#x02009;ng/mL) and TGF&#x003b2; inhibition using SB431542 (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) on RKO colony formation ability. Plates were stained with Diff-Quik stain set on day 6. Wells are representative of at least two independent experiments for each condition.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e822"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>TAGLN enhances CRC migration and in vivo tumor formation</title><p id="Par24">The effects of TAGLN on CRC cell migration was subsequently investigated using transwell migration assay. HCT116 cells overexpressing TAGLN exhibited enhanced migration capabilities (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>), whereas TAGLN-depleted HT-29 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>) and RKO (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>) cells exhibited reduced cell migration. In agreement with those data, RKO cells treated with TGF&#x003b2;1 (10&#x02009;ng/&#x000b5;L) exhibited enhanced cell migration (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>), whereas inhibition of TGF&#x003b2; signaling using SB431542 (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) reduced RKO cells migration potential (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>). Similar effects of TAGLN depletion, exogenous TGF&#x003b2; treatment, and TGF&#x003b2; inhibition using SB431542 was observed using wound-healing assay (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4e, f</xref>). Additionally, TAGLN-depleted RKO cells exhibited reduced tumor formation in vivo (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4g</xref>), corroborating the in vitro results, thus highlighting an important role for TAGLN in driving CRC migration and tumor formation.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>TAGLN promotes CRC cell migration and in vivo tumor formation.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Transwell migration assay showing increase of cell migration in HCT116 overexpressing TAGLN in response to 10% FBS attractant. Effects of TAGLN depletion on HT-29 (<bold>b</bold>) and RKO (<bold>c</bold>) cell migration using transwell migration system. <bold>d</bold> Effect of exogenous TGF&#x003b2; (10&#x02009;ng/mL) and TGF&#x003b2; inhibition using SB431542 (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) on RKO cell migration using the transwell migration system. Effects of TAGLN depletion (<bold>e</bold>) and exogenous TGF&#x003b2; (10&#x02009;ng/mL) and TGF&#x003b2; inhibition using SB431542 (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M) (<bold>f</bold>) on RKO cell migration using wound-healing assay. Time-lapse microscopy was conducted using EVOS FL Auto Cell Imaging System where images were taken every 30&#x02009;min over 4 days. <bold>g</bold> Subcutaneous tumor formation of control (siControl) and TAGLN-depleted (siTAGLN) RKO cells in nude mice. Data are presented as mean (tumor volume)&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;S.E., <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5 per group. Representative tumors at the end of experiment is shown (upper panel).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e884"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>TAGLN regulates several functional categories and signaling pathways in CRC</title><p id="Par25">To unravel the molecular mechanism underlying the biological role of TAGLN in CRC, we performed transcriptome analysis on HCT116 cells overexpressing TAGLN, as well as on TAGLN-depleted RKO cells. Hierarchical clustering based on differentially expressed mRNAs revealed separation between HCT116 cells overexpressing TAGLN and control cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Top affected pathways in HCT116 overexpressing TAGLN are illustrated as pie chart (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). Similar changes were also observed in TAGLN-depleted RKO cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c, d</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). Validation of selected number of genes from the microarray data is shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5e</xref>. We subsequently crossed the two data sets and identified 83 common genes that were upregulated in HCT116-TAGLN and were downregulated in siTAGLN-RKO cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5f</xref>).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>TAGLN regulates several functional categories and signaling pathways in CRC.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Hierarchical clustering of TAGLN-overexpressing or control HCT116 cells based on differentially expressed mRNA levels. Each row represents one replica sample and each column represents an mRNA. Expression level of each gene in a single sample is depicted according to the color scale. <bold>b</bold> Pie chart illustrating the distribution of the top pathway designations for the upregulated genes in TAGLN-overexpressing HCT116 cells. <bold>c</bold> Hierarchical clustering of TAGLN-depleted (siTAGLN) and control (siScr) RKO cells based on differentially expressed mRNA levels. <bold>d</bold> Pie chart illustrating the distribution of the top pathway designations for the downregulated genes in siTAGLN transfected RKO cells. <bold>e</bold> qRT-PCR validation of selected genes from microarray, <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2, *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005, ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.005. <bold>f</bold> Venn-diagram depicting the overlap between the upregulated genes in TAGLN-overexpressing HCT116 and the downregulated genes in TAGLN-depleted RKO cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e952"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>TGF&#x003b2;-mediated TAGLN expression induces ultrastructure changes in CRC cells</title><p id="Par26">Given its role as an actin-binding protein, we investigated the effects of TGF&#x003b2; and its inhibitor, SB431542, as well as TAGLN depletion on actin cytoskeleton changes, and actin microfilaments polymerization in RKO cells. TAGLN perturbation using SB431542 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6g, h, i</xref>) or through siRNA-mediated knockdown (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6l, m</xref>) revealed significant inhibition of actin microfilament polymerization. In contrast, exogenous TGF&#x003b2;1 treatment led to prominent actin filaments organized as bundles/aggregates distributed in the whole cytoplasm and in peri-nuclear locations (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6d&#x02013;f</xref>). Moreover, rough endoplasmic reticulum (RER) was cystically dilated in TGF&#x003b2;1-treated cells, suggesting increased protein synthesis activity (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6e</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) illustrating the ultrastructural characteristics of RKO cells under different treatment conditions.</title><p>RKO cells were treated with exogenous TGF&#x003b2; (10&#x02009;ng/mL), TGF&#x003b2; inhibition using SB431542 (10&#x02009;&#x000b5;M), or TAGLN depletion using siTAGLN. N nucleus, Nu nucleolus, AC actin filaments, V microvilli, M mitochondria, rER rough endoplasmic reticulum, V microvilli, HC heterochromatin, AC actin filaments, my myelin figure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e980"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>TAGLN expression predicts more aggressive phenotype in patients with COAD</title><p id="Par27">Our in vitro and in vivo data demonstrated a role for TAGLN in promoting CRC in vitro and in vivo, however, whether such effects for TAGLN can be recapitulated in patients with COAD was not clear. Therefore, the expression data from 592 patients with COAD from the TCGA dataset was retrieved and patients were stratified into TAGLN<sup>high</sup> and TAGLN<sup>low</sup>. Hierarchical clustering and principle component analysis (PCA) revealed separation of the TAGLN<sup>high</sup> and TAGLN<sup>low</sup> groups, suggesting tangible differences between the two tumor groups at the molecular level (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a, b</xref>, and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). IPA analysis on the differentially expressed genes between TAGLN<sup>high</sup> and TAGLN<sup>low</sup> groups highlighted remarkable activation of a number of mechanistic networks, including SMARCA4, TGF&#x003b2;1, and P38 MAPK (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>). Illustration of the TGF&#x003b2;1 mechanistic network in shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6d</xref>. Those data are in agreement with our in vitro data connecting TGF&#x003b2; and TAGLN in CRC.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>Molecular signature of TAGLN<sup>high</sup> COAD.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Heat map clustering of TAGLN<sup>high</sup> (<italic>m</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;296) and TAGLN<sup>low</sup> (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;296) COAD. Samples were stratified into TAGLN<sup>high</sup> and TAGLN<sup>low</sup> based on median TAGLN expression. Each row represents expression level of an mRNA (log2). mRNA expression level in a single sample is depicted according to the color scale. <bold>b</bold> Principal component analysis (PCA) for TAGLN<sup>high</sup> (<italic>m</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;296) and TAGLN<sup>low</sup> COAD. <bold>c</bold> Bar-graph depicting the top thirty significantly activated upstream regulator networks in TAGLN<sup>high</sup> vs TAGLN<sup>low</sup> COAD. Activation <italic>Z</italic>-score is indicated on the <italic>x</italic>-axis. <bold>d</bold> Illustration of the TGF&#x003b2;1 mechanistic network.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e1086"/></fig></p><p id="Par28">IPA analysis additionally revealed remarkable enrichment in a number of functional categories in TAGLN<sup>high</sup> COAD, predominantly functional categories associated with cellular movement and angiogenesis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8a&#x02013;c</xref> and Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>). Interestingly, P38 MAPK was the top predicted regulator promoting cell movement through regulation of several intermediate molecules, including TGF&#x003b2;1, MMP2, MMP9, and CXCL12 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8d</xref>).<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><title>TAGLN<sup>high</sup> COAD is enriched in functional categories promoting cell migration, angiogenesis, and P38 MAPK signaling.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Disease and function heat map depicting enrichment in the indicated functional and disease categories in the differentially expressed genes in TAGLN<sup>high</sup> vs. TAGLN<sup>low</sup> COAD patients&#x02019; data based on IPA analysis. Heat map-illustrating enrichment in cellular movement (<bold>b</bold>) and cardiovascular system development (<bold>c</bold>) functional categories. <bold>d</bold> Illustration of the predicted P38 MAPK regulator network and its predicted effects of cell movement.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_Fig8_HTML" id="d29e1131"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec25" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par29">Increased risk of poor prognosis of CRC patients is associated with intrinsic characteristics of tumor cells that include rapid proliferation, evidence of invasion and distant metastasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. Suppressing cancer cell proliferation and invasion is an effective strategy to reduce cancer mortality risk and to increase survival rates. In the current study, we report a role for TAGLN, as a TGF&#x003b2; responsive gene, in promoting CRC in vitro and in vivo and its association with poor clinical outcome. We suggested a model where TAGLN expression is reactivated during late stages of CRC to drive a more aggressive CRC phenotype.</p><p id="Par30">A number of earlier studies highlighted TAGLN expression as a TGF&#x003b2;-responsive gene in various biological systems, such as smooth muscle cells, mesenchymal stem cells, embryonic fibroblast cells, neural crest stem cells, and epithelial cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. We have previously shown that TGF&#x003b2;1-induces TAGLN expression via the SMAD2/3 signaling pathway in bone marrow MSCs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Our current and previous data revealed significant downregulation of TAGLN expression in CRC compared to adjacent normal tissue<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Interestingly however, elevated expression of TAGLN was associated with more advanced CRC pathological stage and worse clinical outcome, suggesting a role for TAGLN in driving CRC disease progression. Concordant with our previous report, TAGLN was observed to be specifically upregulated in response to TGF&#x003b2; activation in CRC, whereas TGF&#x003b2;-signaling inhibitor SB431542 abolished this effect<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par31">The TGF&#x003b2; signaling pathway is one of the most important intracellular signaling pathways participating in cancer development and metastasis, and is involved in the regulation of several biological processes associated with oncogenesis such as cell proliferation, differentiation, migration, and apoptosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. TGF&#x003b2; plays a dual function in regulating cell migration and growth. During early tumor progression, TGF&#x003b2; acts as an inhibitor of proliferation and migration, whereas later during advanced CRC and metastasis, it enhances tumor growth and invasion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Induction of the protooncogene c-fos by TGF&#x003b2;1 in poorly invasive HD3 colon carcinoma cells was associated with induction of some growth-inhibitory signals, while this signal transduction pathway is suppressed in TGF&#x003b2;1-stimulated invasive colon carcinoma U9<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Given that TAGLN expression is under the control of TGF&#x003b2;, this explains the paradoxical observations of the role of TAGLN in CRC development and progression.</p><p id="Par32">Although previous studies demonstrated a role of TAGLN as a tumor suppressor and its inhibition is an early event in tumor transformation and development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, recent clinical and functional proteomic evidence showed its association with enhanced cell invasion, cell survival, activation of epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition (EMT) and resistance to anoikis (apoptosis induced by cell detachment) during the distant metastasis stage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The CRC cellular model used in our studies seems to reflect the role of TAGLN in advanced disease as it enhanced both cell proliferation and cell migration. In support of this role in CRC, TAGLN expression is upregulated in CRC tissues present in lymph node-metastasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. In addition, manipulating TAGLN expression influences the expression of other metastasis-related genes and pathways<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Finally, strong association between elevated expression of TAGLN and TGF&#x003b2;1 gene expression in CRC tumor samples and poor prognosis further support the association between TAGLN and advanced CRC disease.</p><p id="Par33">Various actin-binding proteins and signaling pathways are implicated in regulating the dynamics of actin architecture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. As an actin crosslinking protein, TAGLN plays a role in actin cytoskeleton organization and is involved in supporting the cell shape and polarity, along with various cellular and biological processes such as proliferation, migration, apoptosis, and differentiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Our data support the role of TAGLN in maintaining ultrastructural integrity of CRC. In addition, the ability of TAGLN to enhance cell migration is supportive of its effects on cellular cytoskeleton. During cell motility, the actin cytoskeleton regulates protrusion formation, distribution of contractile filaments and assembly/disassembly of focal adhesion molecules through changes in the actin dynamic assembly and disassembly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Several studies have reported inhibition in cell migration and adhesion due to disruption of actin cytoskeleton organization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. In addition to its possible direct role on actin cytoskeleton organization, TGF&#x003b2;-mediated TAGLN expression is associated with upregulation of a number of additional TGF&#x003b2;-responsive genes such as alpha-smooth muscle actin (ACTA2) and tropomyosin (TPM1), which are involved in cell motility and stabilization of cytoskeleton actin filaments and were reported to be regulated in metastatic cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. Molecular profiling comparing TAGLN<sup>high</sup> and TAGLN<sup>low</sup> colon cancer patients&#x02019; specimens shedding some light on the activation of a number of mechanistic networks, including SMARCA4, TGF&#x003b2;1, and P38 MAPK while remarkable enrichment in a number of functional categories associated with cellular movement and angiogenesis was most prominent in TAGLN<sup>high</sup>, suggesting biological relevance to our in vitro findings in patients with colorectal cancer.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par34">Our data describe a model for the molecular mechanisms linking TGF&#x003b2;-induced upregulation of TAGLN and CRC tumor progression. In addition, the clinical data suggest that TAGLN expression is a possible prognostic marker for advanced CRC disease, hence implicating TAGLN as poor prognostic factor offering possible therapeutic opportunity for CRC.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec27"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary table 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary table 2</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary table 3</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary table 4</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="41419_2020_2529_MOESM5_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary table 5</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Edited by J. M. Moreira</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at (10.1038/s41419-020-2529-6).</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank the Deanship of Scientific Research at King Saud University (Research Group No. RG-1438-033) for funding this work.</p></ack><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par35">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pox</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2014</year><volume>383</volume><fpage>1490</fpage><lpage>1502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24225001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erstad</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumusiime</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cusack</surname><given-names>JC</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Prognostic and predictive biomarkers in colorectal cancer: implications for the clinical surgeon</article-title><source>Ann. Surgical Oncol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>3433</fpage><lpage>3450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1245/s10434-015-4706-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alajez</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large-scale analysis of gene expression data reveals a novel gene expression signature associated with colorectal cancer distant recurrence</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0167455</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0167455</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27935967?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27935967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shaath, H., Toor, S. M., Nair, V. S., Elkord, E. &#x00026; Alajez, N. M. Transcriptomic analyses revealed systemic alterations in gene expression in circulation and tumor microenvironment of colorectal cancer patients. <italic>Cancers</italic><bold>1</bold>, 1&#x02013;19 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanz-Garcia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Grasselli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Argiles</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Elez</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabernero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current and advancing treatments for metastatic colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Expert Opin. Biol. Ther.</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/14712598.2016.1108405</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26549053?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26549053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massague</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGFbeta signalling in context</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Mol. cell Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>616</fpage><lpage>630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm3434</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22992590?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22992590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Massague</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of TGF-beta signaling from cell membrane to the nucleus</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00432-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12809600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reduction in Smad2/3 signaling enhances tumorigenesis but suppresses metastasis of breast cancer cell lines</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>8284</fpage><lpage>8292</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14678987?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14678987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bronchioloalveolar invasion in non-small cell lung cancer is associated with expression of transforming growth factor-beta1</article-title><source>World J. Surgical Oncol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>113</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7819-11-113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TGF-beta-induced upregulation of malat1 promotes bladder cancer metastasis by associating with suz12</article-title><source>Clin. Cancer Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1531</fpage><lpage>1541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-13-1455</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24449823?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24449823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Staudacher</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transforming growth factor beta superfamily signaling in development of colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2017</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2016.10.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27773809?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27773809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derynck</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhurst</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Balmain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TGF-beta signaling in tumor suppression and cancer progression</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1001-117</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11586292?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11586292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheen</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting the transforming growth factor-beta signaling in cancer therapy</article-title><source>Biomol. Ther.</source><year>2013</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4062/biomolther.2013.072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schofield</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transforming growth factor beta 1 expression in human colorectal tumours: an independent prognostic marker in a subgroup of poor prognosis patients</article-title><source>Br. J. Cancer</source><year>1996</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bjc.1996.432</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8795578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8795578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsamandas</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The potential role of TGFbeta1, TGFbeta2 and TGFbeta3 protein expression in colorectal carcinomas. Correlation with classic histopathologic factors and patient survival</article-title><source>Strahlenther. Onkol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00066-004-1149-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15057430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15057430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High levels of transforming growth factor beta 1 correlate with disease progression in human colon cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Epidemiol. Biomarkers Prev.</source><year>1995</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>554</lpage><?supplied-pmid 7549813?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7549813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Assinder</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transgelin: an actin-binding protein and tumour suppressor</article-title><source>Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol.</source><year>2009</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>482</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocel.2008.02.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18378184?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18378184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dos Santos Hidalgo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Meola</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosa</surname><given-names>ESJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Paro de Paz</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferriani</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TAGLN expression is deregulated in endometriosis and may be involved in cell invasion, migration, and differentiation</article-title><source>Fertil. Steril.</source><year>2011</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>700</fpage><lpage>703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2011.06.052</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21763649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21763649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transforming growth factor beta: a central modulator of pulmonary and airway inflammation and fibrosis</article-title><source>Proc. Am. Thorac. Soc.</source><year>2006</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/pats.200601-008AW</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16799084?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16799084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transgelin is a direct target of TGF-beta/Smad3-dependent epithelial cell migration in lung fibrosis</article-title><source>FASEB J.</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1778</fpage><lpage>1789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.07-083857</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18245174?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18245174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dvorakova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nenutil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouchal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transgelins, cytoskeletal proteins implicated in different aspects of cancer development</article-title><source>Expert Rev. Proteom.</source><year>2014</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/14789450.2014.860358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of SM22alpha-deficient mice reveals unanticipated insights into smooth muscle cell differentiation and function</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Biol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1336</fpage><lpage>1344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.2001.21.4.1336-1344.2001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11158319?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11158319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeidan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ablation of SM22alpha decreases contractility and actin contents of mouse vascular smooth muscle</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>2004</year><volume>562</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(04)00220-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15044015?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15044015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss of SM22 is a characteristic signature of colon carcinogenesis and its restoration suppresses colon tumorigenicity in vivo and in vitro</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2010</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>2581</fpage><lpage>2589</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20336793?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20336793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TAGLN suppresses proliferation and invasion, and induces apoptosis of colorectal carcinoma cells</article-title><source>Tumour Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13277-012-0575-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23138394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23138394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transgelin promotes migration and invasion of cancer stem cells</article-title><source>J. Proteome Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>5108</fpage><lpage>5117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr100378z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20707403?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20707403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transgelin increases metastatic potential of colorectal cancer cells in vivo and alters expression of genes involved in cell motility</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>55</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-016-2105-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26847345?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26847345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elsafadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transgelin is a TGFbeta-inducible gene that regulates osteoblastic and adipogenic differentiation of human skeletal stem cells through actin cytoskeleston organization</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis.</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e2321</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cddis.2016.196</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27490926?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27490926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>microRNA-320/RUNX2 axis regulates adipocytic differentiation of human mesenchymal (skeletal) stem cells</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis.</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e1499</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cddis.2014.462</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25356868?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25356868</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vishnubalaji</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide mRNA and miRNA expression profiling reveal multiple regulatory networks in colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e1614</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cddis.2014.556</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25611389?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25611389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-toub</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pleiotropic effects of cancer cells&#x02019; secreted factors on human stromal (mesenchymal) stem cells</article-title><source>Stem Cell Res. Ther.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>114</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/scrt325</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24405819?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24405819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vishnubalaji</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-320 suppresses colorectal cancer by targeting SOX4, FOXM1, and FOXQ1</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>35789</fpage><lpage>35802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.8937</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27119506?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27119506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vishnubalaji</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neoplastic transformation of human mesenchymal stromal cells mediated via LIN28B</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>8101</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-44536-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31147574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31147574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vishnubalaji</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaath</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Elkord</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Alajez</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA (lncRNA) transcriptional landscape in breast cancer identifies LINC01614 as non-favorable prognostic biomarker regulated by TGFbeta and focal adhesion kinase (FAK) signaling</article-title><source>Cell Death Discov.</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>109</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41420-019-0190-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31263577?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31263577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GEPIA: a web server for cancer and normal gene expression profiling and interactive analyses</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2017</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>W98</fpage><lpage>W102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx247</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28407145?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28407145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Orthovoltage intraoperative radiotherapy for locally advanced and recurrent colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Dis. Colon Rectum</source><year>2012</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>695</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/DCR.0b013e31824d464c</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22595850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22595850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lechleider</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smad proteins regulate transcriptional induction of the SM22alpha gene by TGF-beta</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1302</fpage><lpage>1310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg224</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12582250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12582250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of Smad3 and SRF-associated complex mediates TGF-beta1 signals to regulate SM22 transcription during myofibroblast differentiation</article-title><source>J. Mol. Cell. Cardiol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1407</fpage><lpage>1420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yjmcc.2003.09.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14654367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14654367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engle</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transforming growth factor beta1 suppresses nonmetastatic colon cancer at an early stage of tumorigenesis</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>3379</fpage><lpage>3386</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10416598?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10416598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hafez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Winawer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colon carcinoma cells switch their response to transforming growth factor beta 1 with tumor progression</article-title><source>Cell Growth Differ.</source><year>1994</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><?supplied-pmid 8018559?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8018559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss of transgelin in repeated bouts of ulcerative colitis-induced colon carcinogenesis</article-title><source>Proteomics</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1158</fpage><lpage>1165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.200500390</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16402363?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16402363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of the actin-binding protein transgelin with lymph node metastasis in human colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Neoplasia</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>864</fpage><lpage>873</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1593/neo.09542</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19724680?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19724680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerlach</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The roles and regulation of the actin cytoskeleton, intermediate filaments and microtubules in smooth muscle cell migration</article-title><source>Respiratory Res.</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>54</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12931-017-0544-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Actin, a central player in cell shape and movement</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>326</volume><fpage>1208</fpage><lpage>1212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1175862</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19965462?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19965462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerthoffer</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Migration of airway smooth muscle cells</article-title><source>Proc. Am. Thorac. Soc.</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/pats.200704-051VS</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18094091?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18094091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alpha-smooth muscle actin (ACTA2) is required for metastatic potential of human lung adenocarcinoma</article-title><source>Clin. Cancer Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>5879</fpage><lpage>5889</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-13-1181</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23995859?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23995859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pawlak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alterations in tropomyosin isoform expression in human transitional cell carcinoma of the urinary bladder</article-title><source>Int. J. Cancer</source><year>2004</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ijc.20151</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15095301?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15095301</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>