<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>World Journal of Surgical Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1477-7819</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7195799</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1859</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12957-020-01859-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MiR-363 suppresses cell migration, invasion, and epithelial-mesenchymal transition of osteosarcoma by binding to NOB1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yongtao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Fang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Lina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Quanbin</given-names></name><address><email>yuwfkq8817@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Orthopedics and Traumatology, Zibo Hospital of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine, Zibo, 255000 Shandong Province China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>CT Imaging Department of Zibo Central Hospital, Zibo, 255000 Shandong Province China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Laboratory of the Fifth People&#x02019;s Hospital of Zibo, Shandong Province, Zibo, 255000 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Orthopaedic Trauma, Zibo Central Hospital, No. 54 Gongqingtuan Road, Zibo, 255000 Shandong Province China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>83</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Osteosarcoma (OS) is a primary malignant bone tumor with a high rate of metastasis and a short 5-year survival rate. MiR-363 was downregulated in a variety of tumors and played a role in suppressing tumors. However, the roles of miR-363 in osteosarcoma remain unknown; thus, the purpose of this study was to explore the functions of miR-363 in osteosarcoma.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">CCK-8 and transwell assays were performed to evaluate the proliferation, migration, and invasion abilities of MG63 cells. The epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) and apoptosis-associated proteins were measured by using Western blot assay. Luciferase reporter assay was utilized to verify whether miR-363 directly bound to the 3&#x02032;-UTR of NOB1 mRNA.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">MiR-363 was downregulated while NOB1 was upregulated in osteosarcoma clinical tissue specimens and cell lines as compared with the adjacent normal tissue specimens and normal cell line. The miR-363 is reversely correlated with the expression of NOB1 in osteosarcoma tissues. Overexpression of miR-363 suppressed the ability of cell migration, invasion, and EMT, whereas low expression of miR-363 promoted this ability. In addition, miR-363 inhibited osteosarcoma proliferation both in vitro and in vivo and inhibited the apoptosis in MG63 cells. Interference of NOB1 could inhibit the migration, invasion, and EMT of osteosarcoma cell line MG63. NOB1 was verified to be a direct target of miR-363 and its expression was mediated by miR-363. Re-expression of NOB1 could partially reverse the inhibitory effect of miR-363 on cell migration and invasion. In addition, low expression of miR-363 or overexpression of NOB1 predicted poor prognosis of osteosarcoma patients.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">MiR-363 inhibited osteosarcoma the proliferation, migration, invasion, and EMT and induced the apoptosis by directly targeting NOB1 in MG63 cells. The newly identified miR-363/NOB1 axis provides novel insights into the pathogenesis of osteosarcoma.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Osteosarcoma</kwd><kwd>miR-363</kwd><kwd>NOB1</kwd><kwd>EMT</kwd><kwd>Migration</kwd><kwd>Invasion</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par5">Osteosarcoma was a primary malignant bone tumor with morbidity of 4,000,000 annually [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Osteosarcoma has a high metastasis that more than 80% of patients may have recurrent metastasis and the 5-year survival rate is only about 50% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Therefore, the identification of new molecular biomarkers involving osteosarcoma metastasis and the possible therapeutic targets for the treatment is urgently needed.</p><p id="Par6">MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are endogenous non-coding RNAs of 22&#x02013;28 nucleotides in length that could modulate gene expression by binding to their 3&#x02032;-untranslated regions (UTR) at the post-transcriptional level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Increasing evidences demonstrated that miRNAs may play important functions in tumorigenesis and tumor progression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. MiR-363 played a role in suppressing cancer in variety of tumors that include gastric cancer, papillary thyroid carcinoma, hepatocellular carcinoma, and lung adenocarcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In gastric cancer, Song et al. have discovered that miR-363 acted as a tumor suppressor to inhibit cell growth and migration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Wang et al. demonstrated similar findings; miR-363 inhibited lung adenocarcinoma cell proliferation, colony formation, and tumor growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. What is more, miR-363 inhibited the EMT and suppressed metastasis of colorectal cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. miR-363 inhibited cell vitality, proliferation, and colony formation ability, but promoted cell apoptosis and G1/S arrest in osteosarcoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. However, in osteosarcoma, there are little papers which study on metastasis of miR-363; therefore, we now investigate whether miR-363 suppressed cell migration, invasion, and EMT in osteosarcoma.</p><p id="Par7">NIN1 (RPN12) binding protein 1 homolog (NOB1) is located on chromosome 16q22.1 and consists of nine exons and eight introns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The RNA substrate containing the D site of pro-ribosomal RNA is efficiently cleaved by NOB1 in a manganese-dependent manner, thereby regulating protease function and RNA metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. NOB1 was upregulated and acted as an oncogene in a variety of cancers including cervical cancer, gastric cancer, epithelial ovarian cancer, and non-small cell lung cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. In laryngeal cancer, Gao et al. have discovered that silencing of NOB1 could inhibit cell growth and metastasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Dai et al. discovered a similar finding that knocking down NOB1 inhibited the proliferation and migration of colorectal cancer cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. In addition, knockdown of NOB1 suppressed the malignant transformation of prostate cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Thus, we strongly believe that knocking down NOB1 could suppress the cellular progression of osteosarcoma. The purpose of this study was to investigate the functions of miR-363 and the relationship between the expression of miR-363 and NOB1 in osteosarcoma tissue specimens.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Patients and clinical samples</title><p id="Par8">From January 2014 and December 2016, patients underwent surgery at the Zibo Hospital of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine and obtained 49 pairs of osteosarcoma and corresponding paracancerous tissues. Before surgery, no patients had received chemotherapy or radiotherapy. Two pathologists performed the pathological diagnosis of osteosarcoma. Instantly after surgery, fresh tissues were frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212; 80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C incubator. All the specimens of this study have got informed consent from patients and have been approved by the Ethical Committee of Zibo Hospital of Integrated Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine. The entire investigation complies with the principles outlined in the Helsinki Declaration.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Cell lines and culture condition</title><p id="Par9">All cells, including two human osteosarcoma cell lines MG63 and SaOS2 and a normal osteoblast cell line NHOst, were obtained from American Type Culture Collection (ATCC; Rockville, USA). All the cells were cultured in RPMI-1640 (Gibco, Carlsbad, USA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS; Gibco), 100&#x02009;IU/mL penicillin, and 100&#x02009;mg/mL streptomycin in an incubator at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and a humid atmosphere of 5% CO<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>RNA isolation and quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR)</title><p id="Par10">Total RNAs were extracted using the TRIzol&#x000ae; reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, USA). To synthesize the cDNA chain, the PrimeScript&#x02122; Reverse Transcription Reagent Kit (TaKaRa Bio, Otsu, Japan) was employed to perform the reverse transcription. Step One Plus&#x02122; real-time PCR system (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) and SYBR&#x000ae; Premix Ex Taq&#x02122; II (TaKaRa Bio) were utilized to carry out the PCR assay. The 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup> method was applied to calculate the relative quantities of each gene. The primers were miR-363 F: 5&#x02032;-GCGGCCAATTGCACGGTAT-3&#x02032;, R: 5&#x02032;-GTGCAGGGTCCGAGGTATTC-3&#x02032;; U6 F: 5&#x02032;-CTCGCTTCGGCAGCACA-3&#x02032; R: 5&#x02032;-AACGCTTCACGAATTTGCGT-3&#x02032;; NOB1 F: 5&#x02032;-ATCTGCCCTACAAGCCTAAAC-3, R: 5&#x02032;-TCCTCCTCCTCCTCCTCAC-3&#x02032;; GAPDH F: 5&#x02032;-GCACCGTCAAGGCTGAGAAC-3&#x02032;, R: 5&#x02032;-ATGGTGGTGAAGACGCCAGT-3&#x02032;.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Protein extraction and Western blotting</title><p id="Par11">Total proteins were lysed and extracted by using radioimmunoprecipitation assay (RIPA) lysis buffer (Beyotime, Shanghai, China) covered with 1% phenlymethanesulfonyl fluoride (PMSF). Equal amounts of protein from each extract were separated by a 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE). Subsequently, the proteins were transferred onto a polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membrane (Millipore, Billerica, MA). Then, the membranes were incubated overnight at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with primary antibodies. The primary antibodies were against NOB1 (1:1000, Abnova, Wuhan, China), E-Cadherin (1:1000, Abcam, Cambridge, USA), and N-Cadherin (1:1000, Abcam), which were diluted in TBST (tris-buffered saline Tween). The goat IgG conjugated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP) (1:4000, Beyotime, Haimen, China) was then utilized to incubate the membranes at room temperature for 1&#x02009;h. Enhanced chemiluminescence detection reagent (ECL, Beyotime) was applied to detect the signals.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Transwell assay</title><p id="Par12">Transwell chambers were inserted into a 24-well plate coated with or without Matrigel (BD Biosciences). The cells were digested with trypsin and then re-suspended in serum-free RPMI-1640 medium. Two hundred microliters of a cell suspension with 1 &#x000d7; 104 cells was added to the upper chamber, while 500 &#x003bc;l of medium containing 10% FBS was added to the lower chamber to serve as a chemoattractant. After incubating at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 48&#x02009;h under 5% CO<sub>2</sub>, the residual cells were removed by cotton swabs. And the migrated and invaded cells were fixed and stained with methanol and crystal violet and counted in 5 random fields using a microscope.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Vectors and transfection</title><p id="Par13">MiR-363 mimic, inhibitor, siRNA-NOB1, pcDNA3.1-NOB1, and their negative control oligonucleotide (NC) were purchased from RiboBio (Guangzhou, China). The cells were seeded into 6-well plate and incubated overnight at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Prior to transfection, the cells were replaced with fresh medium. The vectors and Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) were diluted with Opti-MEM (Gibco, Carlsbad, USA) and then mixed. The mixture was added to cells in the 6-well plate and shook slowly. The cells were harvested 48&#x02009;h after transfection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Cell counting kit-8 assay</title><p id="Par14">MG63 cells (2 &#x000d7; 104 cells per well) were seeded on 96-well plates. After incubation for 24&#x02009;h, MG63 cells were co-transfected with the miR-363 mimic or control mimic. After transfection of 48&#x02009;h, the proliferation of MG63 cells was determined using the cell counting kit-8 (CCK-8) (Beyotime Institute of Biotechnology) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The absorbance was measured with a Bio-Tek Synergy 2 microplate reader at a wavelength of 450&#x02009;nm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Plasmid construction and luciferase reporter assay</title><p id="Par15">TargetScan (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.targetscan.org">http://www.targetscan.org</ext-link>) was applied to predict the potential target genes of miR-363, and NOB1 was discovered to be one of them. Then, the binding sequences were mutated from GUGCAAU (wild type, WT) to GACGGAA (mutant, MUT). Both the wild type and mutant NOB1 were then cloned into the pmirGlo vector (Promega, Madison, WI), and the empty vector was used as the control. After 48&#x02009;h of incubation, the mR-363 mimic and wild type and mutant NOB1 were co-transfected into MG63 cells, and the luciferase reporter gene activity was calculated. Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Promega) was performed to calculate the luciferase activity ability.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Cell apoptosis assay</title><p id="Par16">FITC Annexin V Apoptosis Detection Kit I (BD Pharmingen, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA) was used to measure the rate of apoptosis. MG63 cells (5 &#x000d7; 105 cells per well) were seeded into 6-well plates. After the cells are completely attached, miR-363 mimic (50&#x02009;nM) or NC mimic (50&#x02009;nM) is transfected into the cells. After 48&#x02009;h of incubation, cells were collected, resuspended in 1&#x000d7; binding buffer, and incubated with 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of fluorescein isothiocyanate-conjugated Annexin V and 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;L of PI at 25&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 15&#x02009;min in the dark. Flow cytometry analysis was performed within 1&#x02009;h.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Xenografted tumor model</title><p id="Par17">Four-year-old nude mice were purchased from the Institute of Model Animals of Nanjing University. 5 &#x000d7; 106 cells were injected subcutaneously into the right abdomen of each nude mouse. Subsequently, when there is a significant tumor, the tumor size is measured every 3&#x02009;days. After cultivating for 1 month, nude mice were sacrificed and tumors were isolated and weighed. Tumor volume was calculated by the following formula: (length &#x000d7; width 2)/2.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par18">Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS 16.0 software (SPSS, Inc., Chicago, USA) and GraphPad Prism 6.0 (La Jolla, CA, USA). All quantitative values are expressed as the mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD). The differences between groups were compared using the Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test and nonparametric test (Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> tests). The survival of osteosarcoma patients was evaluated by Kaplan-Meier method and the log-rank test. All other results are representative of three independent experiments. <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec15"><title>The correlation between miR-363 and NOB1 in osteosarcoma tissues</title><p id="Par19">qRT-PCR was performed to measure the expression of miR-363 in 49 pairs of osteosarcoma tissue specimens and corresponding adjacent tissue specimens. As expected, it demonstrated that the levels of miR-363 in osteosarcoma tissues are lower than the corresponding adjacent tissues (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Meanwhile, the mRNA level of NOB1 was calculated in osteosarcoma tissue specimens and the corresponding adjacent tissues. In contrast to the expression of miR-363, NOB1 showed a higher mRNA level in osteosarcoma tissues than the corresponding adjacent tissues (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). Therefore, the relationship between the expression of miR-363 and NOB1 was evaluated, and it was found to have an inverse correlation between miR-363 and NOB1 in osteosarcoma (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, <italic>r</italic> = &#x02212; 0.5069) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). What&#x02019;s more, the expression of miR-363 was calculated in osteosarcoma cell lines MG63 and SaOS2 and normal osteoblast cell line NHOst, and it was observed that the expression of miR-363 was lower in osteosarcoma cell lines MG63 (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) and SaOS2 (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) than NHOst cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The correlation of miR-363 and NOB1 in osteosarcoma tissues. <bold>a</bold> It demonstrated that the levels of miR-363 were lower in osteosarcoma tissues than corresponding adjacent tissues. <bold>b</bold> The level of NOB1 of osteosarcoma tissues was higher than that of corresponding adjacent tissues. <bold>c</bold> The expression of MiR-363 and NOB1 had an inverse correction in osteosarcoma tissues. <bold>d</bold> The expressions of miR-363 in osteosarcoma cell lines MG63 and SaOS2 were lower than that of normal osteoblast cell NHOst. **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; PT, paracancerous tissues; OS, osteosarcoma</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2020_1859_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>MiR-363 inhibited the migration, invasion, and EMT of osteosarcoma cells</title><p id="Par20">To illuminate the metastatic functions of miR-363 in osteosarcoma, miR-363 mimic and inhibitor were transfected into MG63 cells to upregulate (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) or downregulate (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) the expression of miR-363 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). By calculating migratory and invasive abilities, we discovered that the miR-363 mimic inhibited the abilities of migration (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) and invasion (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). In contrast, the migratory (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) and invasive (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) capacities were increased when transfected with the miR-363 inhibitor in MG63 cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b).
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>MiR-363 inhibited migration, invasion, and EMT of osteosarcoma cells. <bold>a</bold> MiR-363 mimic and inhibiter were transfected into MG63 cells to up- or downregulate the expression of miR-363. <bold>b</bold> MiR-363 mimic inhibited the abilities of migration and invasion, whereas miR-363 inhibitor increased the migratory and invasive capacities in MG63 cells. <bold>c</bold> Overexpression of miR-363 inhibited the EMT while low expression of miR-363 promoted the EMT of MG63 cell. E-Ca, E-cadherin, N-Ca, N-cadherin. *<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2020_1859_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">The EMT is an evolutionarily conservative developmental process that has been proved to be a main contributor to the metastasis of tumor. Therefore, in order to further verify the role of miR-363 in osteosarcoma cell metastasis, the differences of EMT markers were calculated when exogenous changed the expression of miR-363. As results, transfection of miR-363 mimic inhibited the EMT by improving the expression of N-cadherin, while decreasing the expression of E-cadherin. On the contrary, knockdown of miR-363 reduced the expression of N-cadherin and promoted the expression of E-cadherin (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c), elucidating that silencing miR-363 promoted the EMT of osteosarcoma cells.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>MiR-363 inhibited tumor proliferation in vivo and in vitro and induced cell apoptosis</title><p id="Par22">CCK-8 and xenograft experiment assays were performed to calculate the tumor growth in vivo and in vitro. As we expected, overexpression of miR-363 inhibited cell proliferation (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), while knocking down miR-363 promoted cell proliferation (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). Similarly, the volume of transplanted tumors in miR-363 overexpression group was significantly larger than that of the control group (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). Flow cytometry analysis revealed that upregulation of miR-363 induced cell apoptosis (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), whereas downregulation of miR-363 inhibited cell apoptosis (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c).
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>MiR-363 inhibited tumor proliferation in vivo and in vitro and induced cell apoptosis. <bold>a</bold> Overexpression of miR-363 inhibited cell proliferation, while cell proliferation was promoted by knocking down miR-363. <bold>b</bold> The volume of transplanted tumors in miR-363 overexpression group was significantly larger than that in the control group. <bold>c</bold> Upregulation of miR-363 induced cell apoptosis, whereas downregulation of miR-363 inhibited cell apoptosis</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2020_1859_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Knockdown of NOB1 inhibited MG63 cell migration, invasion, and EMT</title><p id="Par23">The mRNA level of NOB1 was calculated in a normal osteoblast cell line and two osteosarcoma cell lines. As expected, the results showed that NOB1 was higher in osteosarcoma cells MG63 (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) and SaOS2 (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) than the normal osteoblast cell NHOst (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). siRNA-NOB1 was applied to interfere with the expression of NOB1 in MG63 cells (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b. Then, the migratory and invasive ability of MG63 cells were evaluated, and it was discovered that the migration (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) and invasion (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) were decreased in NOB1 low expressed MG63 cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c).
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Knockdown NOB1 inhibited the migration, invasion, and EMT. <bold>a</bold> The expression of NOB1 was higher in osteosarcoma cell lines MG63 and SaOS2 than that of normal osteoblast cell NHOst. <bold>b</bold> siRNA-NOB1 was applied to interfere the expression of NOB1 in MG63. <bold>c</bold> The migration and invasion were decreased in NOB1 low expressed cells. <bold>d</bold> Interference of NOB1 could decrease the EMT of MG63 cells. **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2020_1859_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p id="Par24">To further explore the impact of NOB1 on cell metastasis, the expression of EMT markers were evaluated. In MG63 cells, the expression of the mesenchymal marker N-cadherin was improved, whereas the expression of the marker epithelial E-cadherin was decreased, which has similar effects with miR-363 overexpression (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>d). All the results demonstrated that low expression of NOB1 inhibited the migration, invasion, and EMT of osteosarcoma cells, which were consistent with the results when miR-363 was overexpressed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>miR-363 directly targeted NOB1 and mediated its expression</title><p id="Par25">TargetScan database was used for identifying the potential target genes of miR-363, and NOB1 gene was predicted as a potential target of miR-363. To test whether miR-363 directly binds to NOB1, the binding sequences at 217&#x02013;223 on NOB1 3&#x02032;-UTR were mutated from GUGCAAU to GACGGAA (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a). Subsequently, the NOB1 wild-type or mutant 3&#x02032;-UTR fragment was cloned into the pmirGlo vector, and then, we calculated the luciferase ability. As results, it was found that the miR-363 mimic inhibited (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) the luciferase activity of cells transfected with the wild-type NOB1 3&#x02032;-UTR, but it did not affect the luciferase activity of cells that transfected with the mutant 3&#x02032;-UTR of NOB1 mRNA (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). What is more, the mRNA level of NOB1 was reduced in MG63 cells overexpressing miR-363 (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), whereas the mRNA level of NOB1 was increased in cells knocking down miR-363 (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c). In brief, the results showed that miR-363 could mediate the expression of NOB1 through binding to the 3&#x02032;-UTR of NOB1 mRNA.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>MiR-363 targeted NOB1 and mediated its expression. <bold>a</bold> The wild type (WT) and mutant (MUT) sequences on the 3&#x02032;-UTR of NOB1 mRNA. <bold>b</bold> MiR-363 mimic inhibited the luciferase activity of cells that transfected with the wild-type 3&#x02032;-UTR of NOB1 mRNA. <bold>c</bold> The mRNA level of NOB1 was reduced in miR-363 overexpressed MG63 cells, whereas increased in miR-363 knocking down cells. **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; <sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05; WT: wild type of ADAM9 3&#x02032;UTR; MUT: mutant of ADAM9 3&#x02032;UTR</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2020_1859_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>NOB1 could partially reverse the roles of miR-363 in migration and invasion</title><p id="Par26">Rescue experiment was performed to verify whether the impacts of miR-363 on cell migratory and invasive abilities were relied on NOB1. NOB1 overexpression vector pcDNA-NOB1 and the miR-363 mimic were co-transfected (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) or only miR-363 mimic was transfected (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) into MG63 cells, and qRT-PCR and Western blot were used to test whether the transfection was successful (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). Then, the capacities of cell migration and invasion were calculated by using transwell assay. NOB1 re-expression could recover the inhibitory effect of overexpressed miR-363 on migratory (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) and invasive (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) abilities of MG63 cells (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). Taken together, all the results demonstrated that NOB1 could partially reverse the roles of miR-363 in the migration and invasion of osteosarcoma cells.
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>NOB1 could partially reverse the roles of miR-363 on cell migration and invasion. <bold>a</bold> NOB1 re-expressed vector pcDNA-NOB1 and the miR-363 mimic were co-transfected or only transfected with miR-363 mimic in MG63 cells. <bold>b</bold> Re-expression of NOB1 could recover the migratory and invasive abilities in miR-363 overexpressing MG63 cells. *<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05; **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01; ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2020_1859_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>The expression of miR-363 and NOB1 related to survival of osteosarcoma</title><p id="Par27">To explore the correlation between the expression of miR-363 and the clinicopathological characteristic of osteosarcoma, 49 patients were divided into high and low two groups according to the expression of miR-363. The relationship was examined between the expression of miR-363 and patients&#x02019; gender, age, tumor size, TNM stage, lymph node metastasis, metastasis, and the expression of NOB1, respectively. Chi-square test was performed to calculate the <italic>P</italic> value, and it was illuminated that the expression of miR-363 had a negative association with tumor size (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), TNM stage (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), lymph node metastasis (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), and the expression of NOB1 in osteosarcoma tissues (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>miR-363 expression and clinicopathological features in 49 osteosarcoma</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Clinicopathological features</th><th rowspan="2">Cases (<italic>n</italic> = 49)</th><th colspan="2">miR-363 expression</th><th rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic> value*</th></tr><tr><th>23 high (%)</th><th>26 low (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Gender</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Male</td><td>25</td><td>12 (48.0)</td><td>13 (52.0)</td><td>0.879</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Female</td><td>24</td><td>11 (45.8)</td><td>13 (51.2)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Age (years)</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x02264; 18</td><td>21</td><td>13 (61.9)</td><td>8 (38.1)</td><td>0.124</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x0003e; 18</td><td>28</td><td>10 (35.7)</td><td>18 (64.3)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Tumor size (mm)</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x02264; 5.0</td><td>22</td><td>14 (63.6)</td><td>8 (36.4)</td><td>0.035*</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x0003e; 5.0</td><td>27</td><td>9 (33.3)</td><td>18 (66.7)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>TNM stage</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;I&#x02013;II</td><td>24</td><td>15 (62.5)</td><td>9 (37.5)</td><td>0.032*</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;III&#x02013;IV</td><td>25</td><td>8 (32.0)</td><td>17 (68.0)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Lymph node metastasis</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;0&#x02013;2</td><td>28</td><td>17 (60.7)</td><td>11 (39.3)</td><td>0.026*</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x0003e; 2</td><td>21</td><td>6 (28.6)</td><td>15 (71.4)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Metastasis</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Absent</td><td>23</td><td>14 (60.9)</td><td>9 (39.1)</td><td>0.066</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Present</td><td>26</td><td>9 (34.6)</td><td>17 (65.4)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>NOB1</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Low expression</td><td>23</td><td>8 (34.8)</td><td>15 (65.2)</td><td>0.011*</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;High expression</td><td>26</td><td>15 (57.7)</td><td>11 (42.3)</td><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*<italic>P</italic> values are calculated with chi-square test</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par28">In addition, the log-rank (Mantel-Cox) test of Kaplan-Meier analysis was performed to calculate the relationship between the expression of miR-363 and NOB1 and the 5-year overall survival of osteosarcoma patients. The results demonstrated that the 5-year overall survival of miR-363(&#x02212;) group was lower (log-rank <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) than that of the miR-363(+) group (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a). On the contrary, the 5-year overall survival of the NOB1(&#x02212;) group was higher than that of NOB1(+) group (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b).
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>The expression of miR-363 and NOB1 related to survival of osteosarcoma. <bold>a</bold> The results demonstrated that the miR-363(&#x02212;) group showed a lower 5-year overall survival than that of miR-363(+) group. <bold>b</bold> The 5-year overall survival was higher in the NOB1(&#x02212;) group than in the NOB1(+) group</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12957_2020_1859_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par29">Osteosarcoma is a primary malignant bone tumor with a high metastasis rate and a shorter 5-year survival rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Therefore, the study to investigate new biomarkers is essential to inhibit the metastasis of osteosarcoma. Increasing evidences demonstrated that miRNAs may play important functions in tumorigenesis and tumor progress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. It was found that miR-363 was discovered to be downregulated and acted a tumor-suppressive role in various tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In gastric cancer, miR-363 acted as a tumor suppressor and inhibited cell growth and migration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. A similar finding by Wang et al. demonstrated that miR-363 inhibited lung adenocarcinoma cell proliferation, colony formation, and tumor growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Our findings were consistent with all the reports that miR-363 was low expressed in osteosarcoma tissues and cell lines compared with the paracancerous tissues and matched normal cell line. What is more, overexpression of miR-363 could inhibit the proliferation, migration, and invasion, and induced cell apoptosis of osteosarcoma cell MG63. In contrast, eliminating miR-363 promoted the proliferative, migratory, and invasive abilities and inhibited the apoptosis ability of MG63 cells. In addition, we demonstrated that miR-363 inhibited the EMT of osteosarcoma cells MG63, which was consistent with the findings of Hu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Finally, the 5-year overall survival of the miR-363 low expression group was shorter than that of the high-expression group, and the expression of miR-363 was inversely related to tumor size, TNM stage, lymphatic metastasis, and the expression of NOB1. Our results were consistent with the findings of Yin et al. in hepatocellular carcinoma and osteosarcoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par30">NOB1 could cleave RNA substrate that contains the D site of pro-ribosomal RNA, thereby regulating protease functions and RNA metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. NOB1 acted as an oncogene and was upregulated in a variety of cancers that include cervical cancer, gastric cancer, epithelial ovarian cancer, and non-small cell lung cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Silencing of NOB1 could inhibit cell growth and metastasis of laryngeal cancer and colorectal cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. We discovered similar findings that NOB1 was upregulated in osteosarcoma tissues and cell lines. The expression of NOB1 was negatively correlated with the expression of miR-363 in osteosarcoma tissues. In MG63 cells, knocking down NOB1 could suppress the migration and invasion, which has the same effects as that of overexpressing miR-363. Furthermore, silencing NOB1 inhibited the EMT of MG63 cell, which was the first time to propose the association between the expression of NOB1 and EMT and was the novelty of our study. Then, we verified that NOB1 was a target gene of miR-363 and was mediated by miR-363, which was consistent with the findings of Lin et al. in ovarian cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. In addition, NOB1 gene silencing can inhibit tumor growth by inducing apoptosis in human colorectal cancer and prostate cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Our result also proposed that upregulation of NOB1 predicted poor survival of osteosarcoma patients.</p><p id="Par31">In conclusion, miR-363 suppressed the proliferation, migration, invasion, and EMT and induced cell apoptosis of MG63 cells. Interference of NOB1 could inhibit cell migration, invasion, and EMT, which is consistent with the effects of overexpressing miR-363. This study showed that miR-363 played a tumor-suppressive role in osteosarcoma, and the direct mechanism of NOB1 has revealed its potential mechanisms for proliferation, metastasis, and apoptosis. MiR-363 may be involved in the progression of osteosarcoma and represents a potential biomarker and target for the treatment of osteosarcoma.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>Quanbin Zhang as the co-corresponding author contributed to the conception of the study and contributed significantly to analyses. Yongtao Zhang as the first author performed the data and wrote the manuscript. Fang Wang as the second author contributed to the analyses. Lina Wang as the third author helped perform the analysis with constructive discussions. The authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No funding was received.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par32">This study was approved by the ethics committee of Zibo Central Hospital. Patients who participated in this research signed the informed consent and had complete clinical data. Signed written informed consents were obtained from the patients and/or guardians.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par33">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par34">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">AC H, A D, P T, KE S: Subsequent primary neoplasms among bone sarcoma survivors; increased risks remain after 30 years of follow-up and in the latest treatment era, a nationwide population-based study. British journal of cancer 2020.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Teot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorlick</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biology and therapeutic advances for pediatric osteosarcoma</article-title><source>Oncologist</source><year>2004</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/theoncologist.9-4-422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15266096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>QC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Downregulation of microRNA-26a is associated with metastatic potential and the poor prognosis of osteosarcoma patients</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2014</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1263</fpage><lpage>1270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/or.2014.2989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24452597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valinezhad Orang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Safaralizadeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazemzadeh-Bavili</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of miRNA-mediated gene regulation from common downregulation to mRNA-specific upregulation</article-title><source>Int J Genomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>2014</volume><fpage>970607</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/970607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25180174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Croce</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA signatures in human cancers</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>857</fpage><lpage>866</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc1997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17060945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendell</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs: critical regulators of development, cellular physiology and malignancy</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1179</fpage><lpage>1184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/cc.4.9.2032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16096373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volinia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Calin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ambs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cimmino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrocca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Visone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Iorio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roldo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferracin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A microRNA expression signature of human solid tumors defines cancer gene targets</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>2257</fpage><lpage>2261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0510565103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16461460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zhu JS: miR-363 promotes proliferation and chemo-resistance of human gastric cancer via targeting of FBW7 ubiquitin ligase expression</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>35284</fpage><lpage>35292</lpage><?supplied-pmid 27167197?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27167197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-363-3p inhibits papillary thyroid carcinoma progression by targeting PIK3CA</article-title><source>Am J Cancer Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28123856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28123856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Liu K: miR-363 inhibits the growth, migration and invasion of hepatocellular carcinoma cells by regulating E2F3</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>3677</fpage><lpage>3684</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29039555?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29039555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chen J, et al: miR-363-3p inhibits tumor growth by targeting PCNA in lung adenocarcinoma</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>20133</fpage><lpage>20144</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28423618?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28423618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">B S, J Y, C L, H Z, Y Z: Tumor suppressor role of miR-363-3p in gastric cancer. Medical science monitor : international medical journal of experimental and clinical research 2015, <bold>21:</bold>4074-4080.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Y W, T C, H H, Y J, L Y, Z L, H H, T L, B W, J C, et al: miR-363-3p inhibits tumor growth by targeting PCNA in lung adenocarcinoma. Oncotarget 2017, <bold>8:</bold>20133-20144.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">F H, J M, X C, L L, Z G, J H, X L: MiR-363-3p inhibits the epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition and suppresses metastasis in colorectal cancer by targeting Sox4. Biochemical and biophysical research communications 2016, <bold>474:</bold>35-42.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">F H, L F, Q Y: miR-363 acts as a tumor suppressor in osteosarcoma cells by inhibiting PDZD2. Oncology reports 2019, <bold>41:</bold>2729-2738.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Y Z, J N, G Z, J Y, W R, Y S, W T, L Y, S Z: Cloning, expression and characterization of the human NOB1 gene. Molecular biology reports 2005, <bold>32:</bold>185-189.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">T&#x02009;V, R M, JP W, BL W, E D-F, C S, R H, O M, MT B, J W, E S: Structural and functional analysis of the archaeal endonuclease Nob1. Nucleic acids research 2012, <bold>40:</bold>3259-3274.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MiR-139-3p induces cell apoptosis and inhibits metastasis of cervical cancer by targeting NOB1</article-title><source>Biomed Pharmacother</source><year>2016</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>850</fpage><lpage>856</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2016.07.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27505862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hua Y: miR-326 inhibits gastric cancer cell growth through downregulating NOB1</article-title><source>Oncol Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3727/096504016X14759582767486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27733214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-215 targets NOB1 and inhibits growth and invasion of epithelial ovarian cancer</article-title><source>Am J Transl Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>466</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28337275?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28337275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of NOB1 by microRNA-330-5p overexpression represses cell growth of non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>2572</fpage><lpage>2580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/or.2017.5927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28849232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">X G, J W, W B, W J, L W: NOB1 silencing inhibits the growth and metastasis of laryngeal cancer cells through the regulation of JNK signaling pathway. Oncology reports 2016, <bold>35:</bold>3313-3320.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">H D, K H, Z C, Q Z, S Z: Low-level miR-646 in colorectal cancer inhibits cell proliferation and migration by targeting NOB1 expression. Oncology letters 2017, <bold>14:</bold>6708-6714.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">X Z, D Z, F Q, Y H, J C, X P, L L, Y H, H H, L Y, et al: Knockdown of NOB1 expression inhibits the malignant transformation of human prostate cancer cells. Molecular and cellular biochemistry 2014, <bold>396:</bold>1-8.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Qi Y: miR-363-5p as potential prognostic marker for hepatocellular carcinoma indicated by weighted co-expression network analysis of miRNAs and mRNA</article-title><source>BMC Gastroenterol</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>81</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12876-017-0637-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28637446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang K, Yan L, Lu F. MiR-363-3p inhibits osteosarcoma cell proliferation and invasion via targeting SOX4. Oncol Res. 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOB1 silencing inhibits the growth and metastasis of laryngeal cancer cells through the regulation of JNK signaling pathway</article-title><source>Oncol Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>3313</fpage><lpage>3320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/or.2016.4707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27035645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-level miR-646 in colorectal cancer inhibits cell proliferation and migration by targeting NOB1 expression</article-title><source>Oncol Lett</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>6708</fpage><lpage>6714</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29391877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29391877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Y L, T X, S Z, M C: MicroRNA-363 inhibits ovarian cancer progression by inhibiting NOB1. Oncotarget 2017, <bold>8:</bold>101649-101658.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NOB1 is essential for the survival of RKO colorectal cancer cells</article-title><source>World J Gastroenterol</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>868</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v21.i3.868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25624720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Positive nin one binding protein expression predicts poor outcome in prostate cancer</article-title><source>Mol Med Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2671</fpage><lpage>2676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/mmr.2014.3066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25503472</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>