<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Endocrinol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Endocrinology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-2392</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7187788</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fendo.2020.00189</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Endocrinology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mutation of <italic>Isocitrate Dehydrogenase 1</italic> in Cholangiocarcinoma Impairs Tumor Progression by Inhibiting Isocitrate Metabolism</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xinglong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Lei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Miaomiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Zhifa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/867411/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Integrated Traditional and Western Medicine in Oncology, First Affiliated Hospital of Anhui Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Hefei</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Anhui University of Traditional Chinese Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Hefei</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Veronica Vella, University of Catania, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Sharon DeMorrow, University of Texas at Austin, United States; Remco Molenaar, Amsterdam University Medical Center, Netherlands</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Ping Li <email>ayliping2019@163.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Cancer Endocrinology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Endocrinology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>189</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020 Su, Zhang, Zheng, Wang, Zhu and Li.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Su, Zhang, Zheng, Wang, Zhu and Li</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><bold>Aim:</bold> Isocitrate dehydrogenase 1 (IDH1) is key enzyme involved in cellular metabolism and DNA repair. Mutations in IDH1 occur in up to 25% of cholangiocarcinomas. The present study aimed to explore the features of cellosaurus REB cells with mutant and wide-type <italic>IDH1</italic>.</p><p><bold>Methods:</bold> To compare the features of <italic>IDH1</italic> knockout and mutation in cholangiocarcinoma, we firstly constructed the <italic>IDH1</italic> knockout and <italic>IDH1</italic> mutation cell lines. We then evaluated the viability of these cell lines using the cell count assay and MTT assay. Next, we determined cell migration and invasion using the Transwell assay. Additionally, to evaluate the effects of IDH1 on cellular metabolism, the levels of &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate (&#x003b1;-KG) and nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate (NADPH) were determined using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. We then applied ChIPbase dataset to explore the genes that were regulated by <italic>IDH1</italic>.</p><p><bold>Results:</bold> High frequency of mutated <italic>IDH1</italic> was observed in the cholangiocarcinoma and <italic>IDH1</italic> R132C was presented in more than 80% of mutations. The results showed that <italic>IDH1</italic> knockout decreased cell proliferation, migration and invasion, whereas the overexpression of <italic>IDH1</italic> in <italic>IDH1</italic> knockout cell line recovered its proliferation, migration and invasion capacities. Additionally, <italic>IDH1</italic> mutation reduced the levels of NADPH and &#x003b1;-KG. Furthermore, investigation into the underlying mechanisms revealed that <italic>IDH1</italic> overexpression induced the expression of aldehyde dehydrogenase 1 thereby promoting cell proliferation, migration and invasion.</p><p><bold>Conclusion:</bold>
<italic>IDH1</italic> plays an important role in cholangiocarcinoma and its mutation impairs tumor progression in part by inhibition of isocitrate metabolism.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cholangiocarcinoma</kwd><kwd>isocitrate dehydrogenase 1</kwd><kwd>aldehyde dehydrogenase 1</kwd><kwd>&#x003b1;-ketoglutarate</kwd><kwd>NADPH</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="34"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="5267"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cholangiocarcinoma is an adenocarcinoma of epithelial cells that occurs in any areas of bile duct (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Although it is a rare type of cancer, its occurrence has increased in the past three decades (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Cholangiocarcinoma can be classified into intrahepatic, perihilar and distal types based on their clinical features. However, surgery and liver transplantation are the recommended therapeutic options for all types of cholangiocarcinoma in a minority of patients (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The 5-years survival rate is 15% for patients with early-stage intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma. However, if the intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma has spread to a distant part of the body, the 5-years survival rate is reduced to only 2% (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Many patients are diagnosed with cholangiocarcinoma in an advanced stage. Due to the fact that surgery cannot completely remove metastatic tumors, additional treatment is recommended (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>Genetic alternations are thought to play a critical role in the occurrence and development of cholangiocarcinoma (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Mutations in several oncogenes and tumor suppressor genes have been reported to be involved in the carcinogenesis of cholangiocarcinoma (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). For instance, activated <italic>KRAS</italic> has been reported to be associated with the development of cholangiocarcinoma (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Inactivated p53, a tumor suppressor gene, is observed in the tumor tissue of cholangiocarcinoma (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). In addition to those genes, other genes including <italic>SMAD4, PTEN, EGFR</italic>, and <italic>PDGFB</italic> have also been described to be associated with the occurrence and development of cholangiocarcinoma (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>Isocitrate dehydrogenase 1 (IDH1) is an enzyme encoded by <italic>IDH</italic>1, which is responsible for catalyzing isocitrate to produce &#x003b1;-ketoglutarate (&#x003b1;-KG) and generating nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate (NADPH) (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH are components of the tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle, which are thought to detoxify against oxidative stress (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Therefore, IDH1 indirectly regulates oxidative damage. Additionally, IDH1 has also been reported to play an important role in the process of glucose and lipid metabolism (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Recently, alternations of <italic>IDH1</italic> have been implicated in many types of cancer (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). In 2008, for the first time, Parsons and colleagues have demonstrated <italic>IDH1</italic> mutations in the human genome related to the glioblastoma multiforme (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). The following studies performed by other groups have further revealed that mutations in <italic>IDH1</italic> are associated with leukemia, colon cancer and prostate cancer (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). In 2012, Borger and colleagues have revealed <italic>IDH1</italic> mutations in cholangiocarcinoma (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Interestingly, mutations in <italic>IDH1</italic> have been frequently observed in poorly differentiated tumors (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). These results support that <italic>IDH1</italic> might be used as a potential biomarker for the detection of cholangiocarcinoma. In 2018, Khurshed et al. have reported that mutations in <italic>IDH1</italic> are associated with improved response to irradiation and chemotherapy in colon carcinoma and glioblastoma cells (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). More recently, they found that <italic>IDH</italic> mutation in gliomas depended on lactate and the neurotransmitter glutamate as metabolic substrates to rescue cells from the metabolic stress (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). These results suggested that <italic>IDH</italic> mutation might affect tumor progression by regulating metabolic stress. In the present study, we aimed to explore the effects of <italic>IDH1</italic> mutation on cholangiocarcinoma. Furthermore, we revealed the mechanisms of <italic>IDH1</italic> mutation underlying the tumor progression of cholangiocarcinoma.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Cell Line and Cell Viabilities</title><p>Cholangiocarcinoma RBE cell line was purchased from the First Affiliated Hospital of Anhui Medical University and cultured in complete Dulbecco modified eagle medium (DMEM) containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and 1% antibiotics under 37&#x000b0;C in the presence of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> at constant humidity.</p><p>Cell viability of RBE cell line and RBE IDH1 knockout or mutation cells was determined using the MTT assay and cell count assay. For MTT assay, an MTT solution (Sigma, St. Louis, MO, USA) was added into each well and the plate was incubated at 37&#x000b0;C. After 4 h, DMSO solution was added and the optical density was read at 570 nm using a microplate reader (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA, United States). For cell count assay, trypan blue staining solution was added to the cells and then the cell viabilities were calculated by counting live and dead cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Construction of IDH1 Knockout and IDH1 Mutation Cell Line</title><p>The IDH1 knockout (IDH1 KO) cell line was constructed using CRISPR-Cas9 (Shanghai Liangtai Biotech Company, Shanghai, China). In brief, when the IDH1 cells reached 70% confluency, the cells were transfected with CRISPR-Cas9 knockout plasmids containing guide RNA sequence of IDH1 and sequence of Cas9 protein.</p><p>The IDH1 R132C mutation cell line was constructed by transfecting the IDH1 KO cell line with IDH1 R132C mutation plasmids.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Invasion and Migration Assays</title><p>Cell invasion and migration assays were performed according to previously reported methods (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Transwell chamber consisted of a membrane filter coated with Matrigel was used in this study. In brief, the cells were detached using trypsin and then resuspended in serum-free DMEM medium. The cells were then seeded into the upper chamber and the complete DMEM medium was added into the lower chamber. The invaded cells which located in lower chamber were counted after incubation for 12 h. Crystal violet solution was used to stain the cells and then a microscope was used to count the cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Detection of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH</title><p>The levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH were determined using relevant qualification kits, according to the documents of the manufacturer (BioVision, Milpitas, CA, United States).</p></sec><sec><title>Xenograft Mouse Model</title><p>Male BALB/c nude mice (6 weeks old) were purchased from Guangzhou Laboratory Animal Center (Guangzhou, China). The mice were housed in a room on a 12-h light-dark cycle and fed under experimental conditions with a temperature of 22&#x02013;24&#x000b0;C and humidity of 50 &#x000b1; 5%. Animal procedures used in this study were approved by the First Affiliated Hospital of Anhui Medical University' Animal Care and Use Committee.</p><p>After 1 week acclimatization, the mice were subcutaneously injected with 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> REB IDH1 KO cells, or REB IDH1 KO cells transfected with wild-type IDH1 or IDH1 R132C mutation plasmids. After 1 week, the tumor volume was measured every 3 days, according to the formula: length &#x000d7; width<sup>2</sup> &#x000d7; 0.52.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunohistochemistry</title><p>After the mice were sacrificed, the tumor tissue was removed and washed with cold PBS, then fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde. The tissues were embedded into paraffin and the sections were then cut at 4-&#x003bc;m thickness. Ki67 (KeyGEN BioTECH, Nanjing, China) staining was performed according to a previously reported method (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and the sections were then observed under microscopy.</p></sec><sec><title>Quantitative Polymerase Chain Reaction (qPCR)</title><p>Trizol reagent was used to extract total RNA from the cells, according to the instructions of the manufacturer (TaKaRa, Dalian, China). Isolation of total RNA was performed under sterile condition. To remove DNA contamination, RNase-free DNase I was used. Primers for CDH1, TJP1, VIM, FN1, Snail, Twist, ZEB1, and &#x003b2;-actin were used for amplification of these genes. To analyze the accuracy of the PCR reaction, the melt curves were used. To evaluate the expressions of genes, 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup> values were calculated. The mRNA expression values of CDH1, TJP1, VIM, FN1, Snail, Twist, and ZEB1 were normalized to that of &#x003b2;-actin.</p></sec><sec><title>Western Blotting</title><p>Extraction and qualification of proteins were performed according to a previously reported method (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Radioimmunoprecipitation buffer was used to lysis the cells. Next, the lysate was centrifuged at 13,000 <italic>g</italic> to remove insoluble materials. The concentrations of protein were qualified using the BCA protein assay kit (Beyotime, Jiangsu, China).</p><p>Protein samples were loaded at equal amounts for each sample and 10% sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) gel was used to separate the samples. Next, the SDS gel was then transferred to a polyvinylidene fluoride membrane and 5% non-fat milk was used to block the membrane. The membrane was probed with primary antibody followed by an appropriated secondary antibody. An imaging system (Bio-Rad, CA, USA) was used to examine chemiluminescence. Expression values of protein were normalized to that of &#x003b2;-actin.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The TCGA cholangiocarcinoma dataset (MSK, Clin Cancer Res 2018) was downloaded and analyzed in cBioportal (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbioportal.org">www.cbioportal.org</ext-link>). SPSS 13.0 (SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA) was used to statistical analysis. All Data were expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (S.D.). To evaluate the significance, one-way analysis of variance with multiple comparisons and Student-Newman-Keuls (SNK) test were performed. A <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered as a statistical significance.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>IDH1 Mutation and Frequency in Cholangiocarcinoma</title><p>First, we explored the frequency of the mutated genes in cholangiocarcinoma. The results indicated that <italic>IDH1</italic> was mutated at the highest frequency among all mutated genes including TP53, ARID1A, BAP1, and KRAS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). We also noticed that mutated TP53 also appeared at a high frequency. It is known that TP53 mutations are frequently observed in the occurrence and development of many types of cancer and are implicated to be an important risk factor for tumorigenesis (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Therefore, we further analyzed the frequency of mutated TP53 in patients with wild-type (WT) or mutated <italic>IDH</italic>. Interestingly, we found mutated TP53 with higher frequency in patients with WT <italic>IDH</italic> than patients with mutated <italic>IDH</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). Additionally, we also detected the proportions of different mutation types of <italic>IDH1</italic>. The results showed <italic>IDH1</italic> R132C was presented in more than 80% of mutation types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>IDH1 was mutated in cholangiocarcinoma. The TCGA cholangiocarcinoma dataset (MSK, Clin Cancer Res 2018) was downloaded and analyzed in cBioportal (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbioportal.org">www.cbioportal.org</ext-link>). <bold>(A)</bold> The frequency of mutated genes in Cholangiocarcinoma. <bold>(B)</bold> The proportion of TP53 mutated patients in IDH1 wildtype (WT) or mutated group. <bold>(C)</bold> The proportion of IDH1 with different mutation types. The data were represented as mean &#x000b1; S.D. **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fendo-11-00189-g0001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>IDH1 Promoted Cell Proliferation of Cholangiocarcinoma</title><p>To explore the effects of <italic>IDH1</italic> on cell proliferation, the <italic>IDH1</italic> KO and WT cell lines were constructed. The IDH1 WT cell line was created in the <italic>IDH1</italic> KO cells transfected with WT <italic>IDH1</italic> expressing plasmid. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>, we did not find expression of <italic>IDH1</italic> in the <italic>IDH1</italic> KO cells, indicating <italic>IDH1</italic> was successfully knocked out. Cell count assay and MTT assay demonstrated that cell number and viability were significantly decreased after <italic>IDH1</italic> was knocked out (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2B,C</xref>). Next, the IDH1R132C cell line was created in the IDH1 KO cells with IDH1 R132C expressing plasmid. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>, the <italic>IDH1</italic> R132C mutation and the <italic>IDH</italic> WT cells were successfully constructed. The results showed that cell number and viability were significantly increased in the <italic>IDH</italic> WT cells when compared with those in cells transfected with vector control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2E,F</xref>). However, we did not find a significant difference in cell number and viability between <italic>IDH</italic> R132C mutation cells and cells transfected with vector control. Furthermore, a xenograft animal model was constructed. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2G</xref>, tumor volume in animals transplanted with the <italic>IDH</italic> WT cells were significantly increased when compared with that in animals transplanted with the IDH R132C mutation cells or cells transfected with vector control. Additionally, we found more Ki67 positive cells in tumor tissues from animals transplanted with the <italic>IDH</italic> WT cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2H</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The overexpression of IDH1 promoted cell proliferation of cholangiocarcinoma. <bold>(A)</bold> Western blot was used to determine the expressions of IDH1 in the IDH knockout (KO) REB cells. Cell count assay <bold>(B)</bold> and MTT assay <bold>(C)</bold> were used to determine the cell viabilities of REB and IDH1 KO REB cells. <bold>(D)</bold> qPCR was used to determine the relative expressions of IDH1 in IDH1 KO REB cells transfected with vector, plasmids containing wildtype IDH1 or plasmids containing IDH1 R132C mutation sequence. Cell count assay <bold>(E)</bold> and MTT assay <bold>(F)</bold> were used to determine cell viabilities of IDH1 KO cells transfected with vector, plasmids containing wildtype IDH1 or plasmids containing IDH1 R132C mutation type. <bold>(G)</bold> The tumor volume of xenograft mouse transplanted with IDH1 KO REB cells transfected with vector, wildtype IDH1 or IDH1 R132C mutation plasmid. <bold>(H)</bold> Immunohistochemistry demonstrated percentage of Ki67 positive in tumor tissue from each group. Data are shown as mean &#x000b1; S.D. **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ns indicates no significance.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fendo-11-00189-g0002"/></fig></sec><sec><title>IDH1 Promoted Cell Migration and Invasion of Cholangiocarcinoma</title><p>We then investigated the effects of <italic>IDH1</italic> on cell migration and invasion. In the <italic>IDH1</italic> KO cells, we found significant reductions in cell migration and invasion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3A,B</xref>). However, in the cells transfected with plasmids containing WT <italic>IDH1</italic>, we observed increased cell migration and invasion when compared with those in the cells transfected with vector control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3C,D</xref>). Additionally, no significant difference for cell migration and invasion between cells transfected with plasmids containing <italic>IDH1</italic> R132C and cells transfected with vector control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3C,D</xref>). Moreover, the results showed the relative expression of a panel of epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) markers including CDH1, TJP1, VIM, FN1, Snail, Twist, and ZEB1 were significantly changed after the cells were transfected with plasmids containing wild-type <italic>IDH1</italic>. We did not find cells transfected with plasmids containing <italic>IDH1</italic> R132C with those changes when compared with cells transfected with vector control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3E</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>IDH1 promoted cell migration and invasion and IDH1 knockout decreased cell migration and proliferation. <bold>(A)</bold> Cell migration and invasion of the REB and IDH1 KO REB cells were determined using Transwell and <bold>(B)</bold> the values in each group were shown as mean &#x000b1; S.D. <bold>(C)</bold> Cell migration and invasion of the IDH1 KO REB cells transfected with vector, wildtype IDH1, or IDH1 R132C mutation plasmid and <bold>(D)</bold> the values in each group were shown as mean &#x000b1; S.D. <bold>(E)</bold> qPCR was used to analyze the relative expressions of a panel of EMT relevant markers in IDH1 KO REB cells transfected with vector, wildtype IDH1 or IDH1 R132C mutation plasmid. Data were shown as mean &#x000b1; S.D. **<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ns indicates no significance.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fendo-11-00189-g0003"/></fig></sec><sec><title>IDH1 Mutation Reduced Levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH</title><p>We next explored the mutation effects of <italic>IDH1</italic> on &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH. First, we determined the levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH in RBE cells and <italic>IDH</italic> KO RBE cells. The results demonstrated that the levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH were significantly decreased in the <italic>IDH</italic> KO RBE cells when compared with those in the RBE cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4A,C</xref>). However, in the <italic>IDH</italic> KO cells transfected with plasmids containing WT <italic>IDH1</italic>, the levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH were increased, indicating <italic>IDH</italic> affected the levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4B,D</xref>). Interestingly, when we transfected the IDH KO cells with plasmids containing <italic>IDH1</italic> R132C, reductions in &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH were observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4B,D</xref>). Moreover, N-acetyl cysteine treatment could significantly rescue the cell loss and impairments in migration and invasion in the IDH1 KO cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4E,F</xref>). These results supported that <italic>IDH1</italic> mutation reduced levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH.</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>IDH1 mutation reduced NADPH and &#x003b1;-KG levels. <bold>(A,B)</bold> ELISA was used to determine the levels of &#x003b1;-KG in REB cells, IDH1 KO REB cells, IDH1 KO REB cells transfected with vector, wildtype IDH1 or IDH1 R132C mutation plasmid. <bold>(C,D)</bold> ELISA was used to determine the levels of NADPH in REB cells, IDH1 KO REB cells, IDH1 KO REB cells transfected with vector, wildtype IDH1 or IDH1 R132C mutation plasmid. <bold>(E)</bold> Cell count assay were used to determine the cell viabilities of REB cells or REB IDH1 K.O. cells treated with or without N-acetyl cysteine. <bold>(F)</bold> Cell migration and invasion assay of the REB cells or REB IDH1 K.O. cells treated with or without N-acetyl cysteine. Data were shown as mean &#x000b1; S.D. *<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ns indicates no significance.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fendo-11-00189-g0004"/></fig></sec><sec><title>IDH1 Regulated the Expressions of ALDH1 in Cholangiocarcinoma</title><p>We further investigated the effects of <italic>IDH1</italic> on ALDH1. First, we found that IDH was correlated to the expression of ALDH1 in patients with cholangiocarcinoma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>). We then found that The levels of ALDH1 were significantly decreased in IDH KO RBE cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>). Additionally, the levels of ALDH1 were significantly increased in <italic>IDH</italic> KO cells transfected with plasmids containing WT <italic>IDH1</italic>, whereas a reduction in ALDH1 was observed in the <italic>IDH</italic> KO cells transfected with plasmids containing <italic>IDH1</italic> R132C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>). Next, we successfully transfected the <italic>IDH</italic> KO cells with plasmids containing ALDH1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5D</xref>). Interestingly, the cell number and viability were increased in the <italic>IDH</italic> KO cells transfected with plasmids containing ALDH1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 5E,F</xref>). We also observed increased cell migration and invasion in the <italic>IDH</italic> KO cells with plasmids containing ALDH1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 5G,H</xref>). To further confirm if IDH1 regulated ALDH1 in such events, ALDH1 siRNA was employed to knock down the level of ALDH1 in REB cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5I</xref>). It was found that ALDH1 siRNA could obviously reduce the viability of REB cells transfected with vector control or IDH1 expression plasmid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5J</xref>), as well as significantly decrease cell migration and invasion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5K</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>IDH1 regulated the expressions of ALDH1. <bold>(A)</bold> The correlation of IDH1 and ALDH1 expression in the patients with cholangiocarcinoma was analyzed using ChIPbase dataset. <bold>(B,C)</bold> qPCR was used to determine the levels of ALDH1 in REB cells, IDH1 KO REB cells, and IDH1 KO REB cells transfected with vector, wildtype IDH1 or IDH1 R132C mutation plasmid. <bold>(D)</bold> qPCR was used to determine the relative expressions of ALDH1 in REB cells transfected with ALDH1 expression plasmid. <bold>(E,F)</bold> Cell count assay and MTT assay were used to determine the cell viabilities of REB cells transfected with vector or ALDH1 expression plasmid. <bold>(G,H)</bold> Cell migration and invasion assay of REB cells transfected with vector or ALDH1 expression plasmid were determined using Transwell and the values in each group were shown as mean &#x000b1; S.D. <bold>(I)</bold> qPCR was used to determine the relative expressions of ALDH1 in REB cells transfected with ALDH1 expression plasmid. <bold>(J)</bold> Cell count assay were used to determine the cell viabilities of REB cells transfected with vector or IDH1 expression plasmid in the presence or absence of ALDH1 siRNA. <bold>(K)</bold> Cell migration and invasion assay of the REB cells transfected with vector or IDH1 expression plasmid in the presence or absence of ALDH1 siRNA. *<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, ***<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; ns indicates not significance.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fendo-11-00189-g0005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In the present study, for the first time, <italic>IDH1</italic> was identified as a high frequency mutated gene in patients with cholangiocarcinoma. In our <italic>in vitro</italic> study, IDH promoted cell proliferation, invasion and migration, whereas those cellular events were inhibited in the IDH R132C mutation cells. In the <italic>in vivo</italic> study, tumor volume in mice transplanted with the <italic>IDH</italic> WT cells was significantly increased when compared with that in mice transplanted with the <italic>IDH</italic> R132C mutation cells. And more Ki67 positive cells were observed in tumor tissue from animals transplanted with the <italic>IDH</italic> WT cells. We further revealed that <italic>IDH1</italic> mutation reduced the levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH, and <italic>IDH1</italic> regulated the expressions of ALDH1 in cholangiocarcinoma. These results supported that <italic>IDH1</italic> promoted the development of cholangiocarcinoma in part by inhibiting isocitrate metabolism.</p><p><italic>IDH1</italic> mutations have been identified in many types of cancers including glioma, hepatoma, leukemia, colon cancer and prostate cancer (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). As a key metabolic enzyme, IDH1 is responsible for catalyzing isocitrate to produce&#x003b1;-KG and generating NADPH (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In the present study, we identified a high frequency of mutated IDH1 in cholangiocarcinoma.</p><p>Besides, we also found a high frequency of TP53 mutation in patients with <italic>IDH</italic> WT, whereas low frequency of TP53 mutation in patients was accompanied with mutated <italic>IDH</italic>. Adam and colleagues have demonstrated that <italic>IDH</italic> mutation occurs earlier in the development of glioma and its mutation precedes <italic>TP53</italic> mutation (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Therefore, we speculate that <italic>IDH</italic> mutation and <italic>TP53</italic> mutation occur at different stages in cholangiocarcinoma. By analyzing the proportions of different mutation types of <italic>IDH1</italic>, we revealed that <italic>IDH1</italic> R132C was presented in more than 80% of mutation types. These results are consistent with a previous finding, in which <italic>IDH1</italic> mutation was found in 16.88% of patients with cholangiocarcinoma and <italic>IDH1</italic> R132C was presented in 12.55% of patients (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p><p>In the present study, we further verified the effects of <italic>IDH1</italic> on cholangiocarcinoma. <italic>IDH1</italic> promoted cell proliferation, migration and invasion in REB cells, whereas those cellular events were not significantly changed in the <italic>IDH1</italic> R132C REB cells. Furthermore, we found that IDH1 regulated the expression of EMT markers including CDH1, TJP1, VIM, FN1, Snail, Twist, and ZEB1. These results suggested that <italic>IDH1</italic> promoted the development of cholangiocarcinoma and its mutation impaired the progression of cholangiocarcinoma. Many previous studies have demonstrated that <italic>IDH1</italic> plays an important role in the cellular redox state in part by regulating cellular &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH generation within the TCA cycle (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). It is well-known that TCA cycle is essential for cell growth, because many intermediates are required for production of lipids, proteins and nucleic acids (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Additionally, NADPH production in cancer cell mitochondria is critical to maintain glutathione and other scavenging molecules in a reduced state, thereby preventing oxidative damage to mitochondrial structures (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). However, the accumulation of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH may activate cancer-related proteins including mammalian target of rapamycin 1, thereby promoting tumorigenesis (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Regulation of &#x003b1;-KG levels is also essential in modulating the epigenetic landscape of cancer cells (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). In our study, the levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH were increased in the <italic>IDH</italic> KO cells transfected with plasmids containing WT <italic>IDH1</italic>. However, when we transfected the IDH KO cells with plasmids containing <italic>IDH1</italic> R132C, reduced &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH were observed. Therefore, we verified that <italic>IDH1</italic> was associated with the levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH in cholangiocarcinoma. The mutations in IDH1 affected the expression of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH, thereby impacting mitochondrial functions in cholangiocarcinoma.</p><p>ALDH1 is a group of detoxifying enzymes capable of catalyzing aldehydes into carboxylic acids (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). It is also a marker of stem cells and is widely expressed in many types of cancers including gastric cancer, ovarian cancer and lung cancer (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Additionally, ALDH1 is involved in cell differentiation and detoxification [32; Our results demonstrated that IDH1 regulated the levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH, which are thought to detoxify against oxidative stress. Interestingly, we also revealed that IDH was correlated with the expression of ALDH1 in patients with cholangiocarcinoma by analyzing the ChIPbase dataset. In our <italic>in vitro</italic> study, the levels of ALDH1 were significantly increased in <italic>IDH</italic> KO cells transfected with plasmids containing WT <italic>IDH1</italic>, whereas a reduction in ALDH1 was observed in the <italic>IDH</italic> KO cells transfected with plasmids containing IDH1 R132C. We further evaluated the cellular functions including cell proliferation, migration and invasion. Interestingly, in the cells transfected with ALDH1 expression plasmids, cellular functions including cell proliferation, migration and invasion were recovered. These results supported that the effects of <italic>IDH</italic> on cholangiocarcinoma was mediated in part by regulating ALDH1.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The present study has identified <italic>IDH1</italic> as a high frequency mutated gene in patients with cholangiocarcinoma. In our <italic>in vitro</italic> study, <italic>IDH</italic> promotes cell proliferation, invasion and migration. In the <italic>in vivo</italic> study, <italic>IDH</italic> increases the tumor volume in mice transplanted with the <italic>IDH</italic> WT cells. Further study reveals that <italic>IDH1</italic> regulates the levels of &#x003b1;-KG and NADPH and the expression of ALDH1. These results support that <italic>IDH1</italic> promotes the development of cholangiocarcinoma in part by inhibiting the isocitrate metabolism.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation, to any qualified researcher.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>Animal procedures used in this study were approved by the First Affiliated Hospital of Anhui Medical University' Animal Care and Use Committee.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>PL conceived and designed research and wrote the manuscript. LS, XZ, LZ, MW, and ZZ conducted experiments and analyzed data. All authors read and approved the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> The work was supported by National Natural Science Foundation of China (81673908).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor-Robinson</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cholangiocarcinoma</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>366</volume>:<fpage>1303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(05)67530-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16214602?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16214602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blechacz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gores</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cholangiocarcinoma: advances in pathogenesis, diagnosis, and treatment</article-title>. <source>Hepatology</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>308</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hep.22310</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18536057?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18536057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Razumilava</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gores</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cholangiocarcinoma</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>383</volume>:<fpage>2168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)61903-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24581682?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24581682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazzaferro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorgen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roayaie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Droz Dit Busset</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapisochin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Liver resection and transplantation for intrahepatic cholangiocarcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Hepatol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>364</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhep.2019.11.020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31954498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31954498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldin</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Heaton</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Karani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of cholangiocarcinoma: an update</article-title>. <source>Gut</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>1657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gutjnl-2011-301748</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22895392?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22895392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epigenetic regulation in the carcinogenesis of cholangiocarcinoma</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocel.2015.06.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26100596?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26100596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mutation detection and molecular targeted tumor therapies</article-title>. <source>STEMedicine</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>e11</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.37175/stemedicine.v1i1.11</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>KRAS and GNAS mutations and p53 overexpression in biliary intraepithelial neoplasia and intrahepatic cholangiocarcinomas</article-title>. <source>Cancer</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>119</volume>:<fpage>1669</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.27955</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23335286?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23335286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledano</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor-Robinson</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>p53 Mutations in human cholangiocarcinoma: a review</article-title>. <source>Liver Int</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>704</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1478-3231.2005.01106.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15998419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15998419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pawlik</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Selaru</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Streppel</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exome sequencing identifies frequent inactivating mutations in BAP1, ARID1A, and PBRM1 in intrahepatic cholangiocarcinomas</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1470</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2813</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24185509?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24185509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenkein</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer-associated isocitrate dehydrogenase mutations</article-title>. <source>Oncologist</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/theoncologist.2011-0429</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22234630?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22234630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellinghoff</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular pathways: isocitrate dehydrogenase mutations in cancer</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1837</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-13-1333</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26819452?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26819452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vatrinet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>De Luise</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Girolimetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasparre</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The alpha-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase complex in cancer metabolic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Cancer Metab.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40170-017-0165-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28184304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28184304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murugan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bojdani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification and functional characterization of isocitrate dehydrogenase 1 (IDH1) mutations in thyroid cancer</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>393</volume>:<fpage>555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2010.02.095</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20171178?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20171178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mclendon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>IDH1 and IDH2 mutations in gliomas</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>360</volume>:<fpage>765</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa0808710</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19228619?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19228619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borger</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>Fantin</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Straley</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Frequent mutation of isocitrate dehydrogenase (IDH)1 and IDH2 in cholangiocarcinoma identified through broad-based tumor genotyping</article-title>. <source>Oncologist</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/theoncologist.2011-0386</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22180306?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22180306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khurshed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aarnoudse</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulsbos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hira</surname><given-names>VVV</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Laarhoven</surname><given-names>HWM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilmink</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>IDH1-mutant cancer cells are sensitive to cisplatin and an IDH1-mutant inhibitor counteracts this sensitivity</article-title>. <source>FASEB J.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>6344</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.201800547R</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenting</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Khurshed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Heuvel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Lith</surname><given-names>SAM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic>Isocitrate dehydrogenase 1</italic>-mutated human gliomas depend on lactate and glutamate to alleviate metabolic stress</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>557</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.201800907RR</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30001166?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30001166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moutasim</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nystrom</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cell migration and invasion assays</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>731</volume>:<fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-61779-080-5_27</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21516419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21516419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ethanol extract of Ilex hainanensis Merr. exhibits anti-melanoma activity by induction of G1/S cell-cycle arrest and apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Chin J Integr Med</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11655-017-2544-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28741062?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28741062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ilexgenin A exerts anti-inflammation and anti-angiogenesis effects through inhibition of STAT3 and PI3K pathways and exhibits synergistic effects with Sorafenib on hepatoma growth</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>315</volume>:<fpage>90</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.taap.2016.12.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27986624?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27986624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A novel pentacyclic triterpenoid, Ilexgenin A, shows reduction of atherosclerosis in apolipoprotein E deficient mice</article-title>. <source>Int Immunopharmacol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2016.08.024</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27588911?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27588911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>TP53 mutations, expression and interaction networks in human cancers</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>624</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.13483</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27880943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27880943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bittinger</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Driggers</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cancer-associated IDH1 mutations produce 2-hydroxyglutarate</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>465</volume>:<fpage>966</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09132</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20559394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20559394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmen</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Colman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>IDH1 and IDH2 mutations in gliomas</article-title>. <source>Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>345</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11910-013-0345-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23532369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23532369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Consortium</surname><given-names>APG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>AACR Project GENIE: powering precision medicine through an international consortium</article-title>. <source>Cancer Discov</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>818</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-17-0151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28572459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cardaci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciriolo</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>TCA cycle defects and cancer: when metabolism tunes redox state</article-title>. <source>Int J Cell Biol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>2012</volume>:<fpage>161837</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/161837</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22888353?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22888353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mullen</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Boroughs</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Oxidation of alpha-ketoglutarate is required for reductive carboxylation in cancer cells with mitochondrial defects</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2014.04.037</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24857658?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24857658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciccarese</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciminale</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Escaping death: mitochondrial redox homeostasis in cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Front Oncol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2017.00117</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28649560?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28649560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reprogramming glucose metabolism in cancer: can it be exploited for cancer therapy?</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc.2016.77</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27634447?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27634447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perozich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hempel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The big book of aldehyde dehydrogenase sequences. An overview of the extended family</article-title>. <source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>463</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4615-4735-8_1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10352663?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10352663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aldehyde dehydrogenase 1A1 in stem cells and cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>11018</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.6920</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26783961?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26783961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Douville</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaulieu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Balicki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>ALDH1 as a functional marker of cancer stem and progenitor cells</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells Dev</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/scd.2008.0055</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18573038?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18573038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharrow</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Collector</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of aldehyde dehydrogenase 1 high ovarian cancer cells: towards targeted stem cell therapy</article-title>. <source>Gynecol Oncol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>142</volume>:<fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygyno.2016.03.022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27017984?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27017984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>