<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Plast Reconstr Surg Glob Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Plast Reconstr Surg Glob Open</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GOX</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery Global Open</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2169-7574</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wolters Kluwer Health</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4494493</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="art-access-id">00002</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/GOX.0000000000000401</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Musculoaponeurotic Area of the Hip and Clinicophotographic Scaling System</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mena-Ch&#x000e1;vez</surname><given-names>J. Alejandro</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>C&#x000e1;rdenas-Camarena</surname><given-names>L&#x000e1;zaro</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">*&#x02020;&#x02021;&#x000a7;&#x000b6;&#x02016;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">From the <label>*</label>Mexican Association of Plastic Esthetic and Reconstructive Surgery (AMCPER); <label>&#x02020;</label>International Confederation for Plastic Reconstructive and Aesthetic Surgery (IPRAS); <label>&#x02021;</label>International Society of Aesthetic Plastic Surgery (ISAPS); <label>&#x000a7;</label>Iberolatinoamerican Plastic Surgery Federation (FILACP); <label>&#x000b6;</label>Western Mexican Association of Plastic, Esthetic and Reconstructive Surgery (SCPERO); and <label>&#x02016;</label>Jalisco College of Plastic Surgeons.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">L&#x000e1;zaro C&#x000e1;rdenas-Camarena, MD, Innovare Cirugia Pl&#x000e1;stica Especializada, Av. Verona 7412, Villa Verona, Zapopan Jalisco, Mexico, E-mail: <email xlink:href="drlazaro@drlazarocardenas.com">drlazaro@drlazarocardenas.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e423</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2015 The Authors. Published by Wolters Kluwer Health, Inc. on behalf of The American Society of Plastic Surgeons. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 3.0 License, where it is permissible to download and share the work provided it is properly cited. The work cannot be changed in any way or used commercially.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="gox-3-e423.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>With the evolution of body contouring, few innovative alternatives have been developed for cosmetic treatment in the hip area.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>A multicenter controlled study was conducted, including a prior review of the literature regarding the hip area. Dissections were performed on 4 male cadavers, outlining the &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip.&#x0201d; The area was subdivided into anterior and posterior surfaces. A clinical study was conducted in 79 patients, obtaining a scale by using the most prominent points on the sides of both thighs as the main reference. With the lines marked on photographs and the measurements, a &#x0201c;clinicophotographic scaling system&#x0201d; was designed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The anterior surface corresponds to the tensor fasciae latae and its tendon as well as to the aponeurosis of the gluteus medius. The posterior surface corresponds with the iliotibial tract and the tendon insertions of the gluteus maximus. The average dimensions of the cadaver &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip&#x0201d; are as follows: length, 17.5 cm, and width, 11.5 cm. Using the &#x0201c;clinicophotographic scaling system,&#x0201d; the dimensions are as follows: length, 14.9 cm, and width, 10.3 cm.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions:</title><p>The &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip&#x0201d; was defined involving muscles, tendons, aponeurosis, fascia, subcutaneous cellular tissue, and skin. The borders were established using important anatomical points that determine the length and width of the area. The &#x0201c;clinicophotographic scaling system&#x0201d; was used to clinically calculate the length and width of the area. By examination and palpation, the borders and dimensions of this area could be determined.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>OPEN-ACCESS</meta-name><meta-value>TRUE</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Body contouring surgery has evolved over the years. The waist, buttocks, and hip are areas of great interest. From the outset, gluteoplasty has evolved so that adjacent areas have been involved. The last 5 decades have contributed anatomical and surgical expertise to body contouring. Methods using buttocks implants and autologous fat infiltration as well as techniques using combinations of these methods have been described. However, few innovative alternatives have been reported for adjacent areas. During the 1960s, Bartels et al<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> performed the first reconstructive gluteoplasty in a patient with idiopathic gluteal atrophy. In the following decade, Cocke and Ricketson<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> placed the first subcutaneous gluteal implant, for aesthetic reasons, in a patient with deficient hip development. The well-known indications and complications of subcutaneous and submuscular gluteal implants, alone<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> or in combination with autologous fat infiltration, were described.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Babuccu et al<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> studied the morphological changes of the buttocks and hip areas in women concluding that this region is very dynamic and its dimensions vary throughout life. Cuenca-Guerra and Quezada<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> analyzed many pictures at different angles and projections to find the harmonic balance of the best gluteal projection. Centeno and Young<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> described 8 aesthetic units as criteria on which to base surgical decisions involving the flanks of the back, sacral region, and buttocks as well as the triangle of light diamond area and thighs. Universal aesthetic ideals vary. Frequently, prominent buttocks and a narrow waist in combination with wide hips are preferred, predominantly in Hispanic, African American, and African Caribbean populations. This preference for buttock size and shape is influenced by culture and the appearance of public figures.<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> This phenomenon is seen through consultations and Internet forums: Female patients with narrow pelvises are known as &#x0201c;boy&#x02019;s hips.&#x0201d; Constantino and Mendieta<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> contributed significantly to the surgical approach by describing points A, B, and C and the following buttock shapes: A-shape, V-shape, Square, and Round. This contribution is useful in the selection of hip shapes. Two publications described aesthetic improvement of the hip area using hip implants. Benito-Ruiz et al<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> combine the Vergara and Marcos gluteoplasty technique and smooth oval implants placed at the greater trochanter below the fascia lata and report the possibility of communication between the 2 pockets, with consequent migration of the implants. Another reconstructive option corrects contour deformities of the hip region with a pedicled deep inferior epigastric perforator flap.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> C&#x000e1;rdenas-Camarena<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> recently described a technique similar to that of Benito-Ruiz et al<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> and achieved more natural results on the hip contour.</p><p>The following research is bibliographically supported by 46 hip area references. From these references, we selected 19 studies that most completely and helpfully support this research. However, the retrievable information that is helpful for improving aesthetic contouring of the hip area is very limited.</p><p>This research was conducted to describe and delimit an area that in the future might be used more easily and predictably for surgical procedures. We sought an innovative approach that would enable new techniques for aesthetically modifying the hip contour and facilitating reconstructive purposes, including providing for precise placement of implants.</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>PATIENTS AND METHODS</title><p>An analysis of the scientific literature was performed, in addition to a multicenter, controlled study. In March 2011, 2 anatomy textbooks, 2 plastic surgery textbooks, and 46 indexed articles in plastic surgery journals were consulted. The authors studied the importance of the soft tissues of the pelvis and thigh, including the skin, subcutaneous tissue, fascias, aponeurosis, and muscles. Specific attention was given to structures such as the fascia lata, tensor fasciae latae, and the blood supply,<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> as well as to other important structures adjoining this region, including the lateral cutaneous nerve of the thigh and Scarpa&#x02019;s triangle.<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup></p><p>During July and December 2011, dissections of the hip, thigh, and buttocks were conducted in 4 fresh cadavers. All of the cadavers were male, and the ages varied between 30 and 50 years. We chose male cadavers because most of the patients seeking cosmetic improvement of the hip area are women with anatomical characteristics very similar to those of men. The cadavers were anatomically intact in the pelvic and thigh regions. Measurements, photographs, and videos were obtained. The primary objective was to analyze and evaluate the anatomical constants specific to this region. The important structures adjoining the tensor fasciae latae that could be involved in surgical approaches were identified and analyzed. Based on the observations made during the dissections, the authors described and defined a &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip,&#x0201d; which encompasses soft tissues such as skin, subcutaneous cellular tissue, fascia, and musculoaponeurotic structures.</p><p>During the cadaver dissections, the &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip&#x0201d; boundaries were established and measured with the following lines:</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Line A (Anterior) is the line that extends from the anterosuperior iliac spine to the external tuberosity of the tibia.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Line P (Posterior) is the line that begins where the middle one-third joins the posterior one-third of the superior edge of the iliac crest and ends at the external tuberosity of the tibia.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Line S (Superior) is the horizontal line level in the anterosuperior iliac spine. This line corresponds to the level of point A mentioned by Babuccu et al.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup></p></list-item><list-item><p>Line I (Inferior) is the line parallel to line S in the most prominent points of the superior and lateral area of the thigh. This line corresponds with the level of point B mentioned by Constantino and Mendieta.<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup></p></list-item><list-item><p>The distance between S and I determines the length of the area. The distance between lines A and P determines the width.</p></list-item></list><p>The area enclosed within these 4 lines was divided and measured as the anterior surface (as) and the posterior surface (ps) (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>1, Tendon fibers of the gluteus maximus. 2, Aponeurosis of the gluteus medius. 3, Iliotibial tract. 4, Tensor fasciae latae. 5, Tendon fibers of the tensor fasciae latae. as, The anterior surface of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip. ps, The posterior surface of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip. A, The anterior line of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip. P, The posterior line of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip. S, The superior line of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip. I, The inferior line of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gox-3-e423-g001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>A, The anterior line of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip. P, The posterior line of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip. S, The superior line of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip. I, The inferior line of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip. as, The anterior surface of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip. ps, The posterior surface of the musculoaponeurotic area of the hip. 1, Anterosuperior iliac spine. 2, Tensor fasciae latae. 3, Tendon fibers of the gluteus maximus.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gox-3-e423-g002"/></fig><p>The center of the &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip&#x0201d; is closely related to the lateral depression of the buttock, point C (described by Constantino and Mendieta<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>), and to the greater trochanter of the femur.</p><p>The findings of the dissections, as well as the lines and their anatomical points of reference, were applied clinically and photographically for an anthropometric study, using 4 wooden meticulously constructing &#x0201c;modified vernier calipers&#x0201d; (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). These calipers were calibrated in millimeters, with the capacity to measure widths of up to 60 cm. A caliper was provided to each of the 4 photography studios.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>The modified wooden vernier caliper calibrated in millimeters and capable of measuring widths of up to 60 cm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gox-3-e423-g003"/></fig><p>A total of 79 patients (77 female and 2 male) were studied, photographed, and measured at the following clinical photography studios: 22 patients at the Instituto Jalisciense de Cirug&#x000ed;a Reconstructiva, &#x0201c;Dr. Jos&#x000e9; Guerrerosantos&#x0201d;; 43 patients at the Estudio de Fotograf&#x000ed;a Cl&#x000ed;nica Bejart; 9 patients at the Hospital Cl&#x000ed;nica &#x000c1;ngeles Chapalita; and 5 patients at the Hospital Innova M&#x000e9;dica.</p><p>The patients attended for abdominoplasty, liposuction, and augmentation gluteoplasty were included for the clinical and photographic evaluation. The patients were interviewed, measured, weighed, and photographed, with clinical photographs taken from the front and side being submitted for the analysis. The ethics committee of the Jalisco Institute of Reconstructive Surgery approved the study, and all the patients received written information regarding the purpose and the methods of the study; all of the patients gave consent to participate in the study.</p><p>Holding the &#x0201c;modified vernier caliper&#x0201d; level with line I, we measured the width of the patient&#x02019;s hips. We referred to this distance as the Trochanter-Trochanter or &#x0201c;TT&#x0201d; (expressed in centimeters). With a ruler, we measured this width on a photograph of the same patient and termed this distance &#x0201c;tt&#x0201d; (expressed in centimeters). We used these measurements to create the &#x0201c;clinicophotographic scaling system,&#x0201d; which consisted of the following: we divided TT by tt to obtain the &#x0201c;scale,&#x0201d; expressed in centimeters (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). We then marked on the photographs the lines, A, P, S, and I, in accordance with the identical anatomical references on the cadaver. The distance between S and I was measured on the photograph and multiplied by the scale to obtain the length of the area (LA), expressed in centimeters. The distance between A and P (at the midpoint between S and I) was multiplied by the scale to obtain the width of the area (AN), expressed in centimeters (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Calculating the scale with the &#x0201c;modified vernier caliper&#x0201d; using the &#x0201c;clinicophotographic scaling system.&#x0201d;</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gox-3-e423-g004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p>Determining the length (LA) and width (AN) using the &#x0201c;clinicophotographic scaling system.&#x0201d;</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gox-3-e423-g005"/></fig><p>The distance at which the photographs were taken in our studio varied between 1.5 and 2 m. After the scale between TT and tt was calculated, it became the constant that determined the actual dimensions of the &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip,&#x0201d; regardless of the distance at which the photographs were taken.</p><p>The measurement calculation and data summary sheet were completed, and the following data were recorded: the age, gender, weight, height, body mass index, TT, tt, scale, LA, and AN (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p>Measurement calculation and data summary sheet.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gox-3-e423-g006"/></fig><p>These measurements and calculations were performed to ascertain the relationship between the dimensions obtained using the &#x0201c;clinicophotographic scaling system&#x0201d; and those found during the cadaver dissections.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>RESULTS</title><sec><title>Literature Reviews</title><p>Of the 46 plastic surgery indexed journal arti cles and books on that we reviewed, 19<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> articles and 1 anatomy textbook were relevant to the hip area.<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> These publications were fundamental to our investigation, and of particular interest were points A and B, mentioned by Babuccu et al<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> and Constantino and Mendieta.<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Babuccu et al<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> describe point A as the anterosuperior iliac spine and point B as the most prominent point of the greater trochanter. Constantino and Mendieta<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> describe point A as the most prominent point on the superiolateral area of the hip and point B as the most prominent point on the lateral area of the thigh.</p></sec><sec><title>Cadaver Dissections</title><p>In the &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip,&#x0201d; line A (Anterior) corresponds with the anterior edge of the tensor fasciae latae and its tendon. Line P (Posterior) corresponds with the posterior edge of the insertions of the gluteus maximus and the posterior edge of the iliotibial tract. Line S (Superior) corresponds to the level of the anterior superior iliac spine. Line I (Inferior) corresponds to the level of the most prominent points of the superior and lateral areas of the thigh.</p><p>The mean length (LA) of the &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip&#x0201d; in cadavers was 17.5 cm. The mean width (AN) was 11.5 cm. The mean of the anterior surface (as) was 6 cm, and the mean of the posterior surface (ps) was 5.5 cm. These measurements, as well as the minimum and maximum values, are shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Dimensions of the &#x0201c;Musculoaponeurotic Area of the Hip&#x0201d;: Results in Cadavers</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gox-3-e423-g007"/></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Anthropometric and Photographic Study</title><p>A total of 79 patients (77 female and 2 male) were studied, photographed, and measured at 4 clinical photography studios as follows: 22 patients (27.8%) at the Instituto Jalisciense de Cirug&#x000ed;a Reconstructiva &#x0201c;Dr. Jos&#x000e9; Guerrerosantos&#x0201d;; 43 patients (54.4%) at the Estudio de Fotograf&#x000ed;a Cl&#x000ed;nica Bejart; 9 patients (11.4%) at the Hospital Cl&#x000ed;nica &#x000c1;ngeles Chapalita; and 5 patients (6.3%) at the Hospital Innova M&#x000e9;dica. The mean values for the following variables were as follows: age, 34.32 years; weight, 61.41 kg; height, 1.6 m (160 cm); body mass index, 23.98; TT, 35.15 cm; tt, 9.16 cm; scale, 3.97 cm; length (LA), 14.99 cm; and width (AN), 10.3 cm. These measurements, as well as the minimum and maximum values, were derived from our &#x0201c;clinicophotographic scaling system&#x0201d; (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Numerical Results of the Variables according to Our &#x0201c;Clinicophotographic Scaling System&#x0201d;</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gox-3-e423-g008"/></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Numerous surgeons have focused on and described methods of agreeable contouring in different parts of the human body. Many of these studies concentrate on areas such as the breasts and buttocks, and very precise anatomical and anthropometric descriptions, classifications, and surgical techniques exist for these areas.<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup></p><p>Regarding these studies, we aimed to identify the research concerning the hip area. Few anatomical, surgical, and anthropometric innovations have been reported regarding surgery in the hip area.<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> The hip area is generally an overlooked region that merits further study because present-day patients seek more aesthetic and reconstructive alternatives.</p><p>A range of social and cultural factors result in preferences regarding hip size and shape. A strong interest or preference exists for a rounded hip contour with Hispanic, Afro-American, Caribbean, and African characteristics. This interest results from the strong influence exerted by very attractive Latin American public figures, as described by Roberts et al<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> in their article. In our investigation, we retrieved 2 studies that specifically aimed to correct hip deformities from a reconstructive point of view. Benito-Ruiz et al<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> described the use of gluteal implants to provide volume to the hips of female HIV patients who had lost volume in this area as an effect of antiretroviral therapy. Schoeller et al<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> describe the use of a deep inferior epigastric perforator flap in a series of cases that involved sequelae or deformities in the hip area. Both articles primarily had reconstructive aims. We hypothesize that the first option has merit and could offer a good aesthetic alternative. In a recent study, C&#x000e1;rdenas-Camarena<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> used a combination of gluteal implants in the buttocks and hip for purely aesthetic reasons, and improved aesthetic hip contour results were reported.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> These studies do not rely on an anatomical and topographical study that could be applied clinically to achieve an optimal outcome.</p><p>The investigations and reports by Babuccu et al<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> and Constantino and Mendieta<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> provided detailed knowledge of the &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip.&#x0201d; Our line, specified as S, corresponds to the height of point A mentioned by Babuccu et al,<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> and the two have the anterosuperior iliac spine in common. This line does not correspond to point A, as mentioned by Constantino and Mendieta.<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> In our study, line I corresponds to Constantino and Mendieta&#x02019;s<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> point B, and the two have in common the most prominent point of the lateral area of the thigh. However, in our study, line I does not correspond to the most prominent point of the greater trochanter reported by Babuccu et al.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> In accordance with the length (LA), the lateral depression of the buttock, Constantino and Mendieta&#x02019;s<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> point C, and the greater trochanter correspond to the height of the middle third of the &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip.&#x0201d; For this reason, we disagree with the descriptions of point B suggested by Babuccu et al<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> because they describe the greater trochanter as being the point of greatest prominence, whereas, in our study, we found that the greater trochanter is more closely linked to the height of the lateral depression of the buttock and Constantino and Mendieta&#x02019;s<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> point C.</p><p>In anatomical, topographical, and clinical terms, the anterosuperior iliac spine, the iliac crest, the most prominent point of the hip, and the external tuberosity of the tibia are the most important anatomical references when determining the dimensions of the &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip.&#x0201d; Benito-Ruiz et al<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> and C&#x000e1;rdenas- Camarena<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> did not define the dimensions of the pocket that holds the implants in the hip area. Neither its dimensions nor borders, based on established anatomical references, are specified. We suggest that the description of the &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip&#x0201d; and the &#x0201c;clinicophotographic scaling system&#x0201d; are clinically useful for making a surgical decision pertaining to the hip. Our aim was not to define anatomical structures that have already been perfectly understood and described. The objective was to create a system of clinical and photographic evaluation using anatomical structures as references to define, as simply as possible, an area that could be modified. Determining the dimensions of the musculoaponeurotic hip area would be useful in selecting the suitable dimensions, undermining, and pocket size of an implant. Even without implant placement, defining this area could be useful for preoperative marking before modifying treatment in this area. The objective with these types of surgical procedures in this area is to increase the volume by the insertion of an implant or with autologous fat infiltration. These dimensions allow for proper planning.</p><p>We included the results from the dissections in the table of measurements obtained by our &#x0201c;clinicophotographic scaling system&#x0201d; to demonstrate that the measurements obtained with our method do not exceed those obtained in the dissections. The mean length was 14.99 cm, and the mean width was 10.3 cm. These dimensions are very similar to those at the base of a gluteal implant. We hypothesize that our study will be useful in future investigations similar to those described by Benito-Ruiz et al<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> and C&#x000e1;rdenas-Camarena.<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup></p><p>Some doubts and controversial questions could result from the characteristics of our study because most of our photographed patients are female, whereas the cadavers are male. The difference is justified because most female hip deficiencies result in a hip appearance that resembles male hip appearance, and the term &#x0201c;boy&#x02019;s hips&#x0201d; was created by some women. We aimed to develop a technique to transform hips with a masculine appearance into more feminine hips.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>This study defines the &#x0201c;musculoaponeurotic area of the hip,&#x0201d; which includes muscles, tendons, aponeurosis, fascia, subcutaneous tissue, and skin. Using the &#x0201c;clinicophotographic scaling system,&#x0201d; the length and width of the area could be calculated. The scaling system is easy, reproducible, and inexpensive. With inspection and palpation using anatomical points of reference, the borders and dimensions of the area could be clinically defined before surgery. This area is very important for the modifications of hip contouring and could be useful for the design of specific implants in the future.</p></sec><sec><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p>We gratefully acknowledge Drs. Jos&#x000e9; Mena Olalde and Francisco Ruvalcaba Ram&#x000ed;rez, as well as nurse Diana Guadalupe Murillo Coria and Tania Karina Ornelas Molina, for their assistance with photography and cadaver dissection. We also acknowledge the pro bono language editing services provided by Newmed Publishing Services.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="presented-at"><p>Presented at the residents&#x02019; convention &#x0201c;Dr. Jos&#x000e9; Barba Rubio&#x0201d; at the 39th Simposio Anual Internacional de Cirug&#x000ed;a Pl&#x000e1;stica y Est&#x000e9;tica del Dr. Jos&#x000e9; Guerrerosantos, October 30, 2012, City of Puerto Vallarta, Jalisco, Mexico, and at the residents&#x02019; convention &#x0201c;Dr. Fernando Ortiz Monasterio&#x0201d; at the XLIV Congreso Nacional de la Asociaci&#x000f3;n Mexicana de Cirug&#x000ed;a Pl&#x000e1;stica, Est&#x000e9;tica y Reconstructiva, April 16, 2013, City of Puerto Vallarta, Jalisco, Mexico.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Disclosure:</bold> The authors have no financial interest to declare in relation to the content of this article. The Article Processing Charge was paid for by the authors.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Malley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An unusual use of the Cronin breast prosthesis. Case report.</article-title><source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source><year>1969</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>500</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5345491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cocke</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricketson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gluteal augmentation.</article-title><source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source><year>1973</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>93</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4713827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Luiz S&#x000e9;rgio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gluteoplasty: personal modifications of the robles technique.</article-title><source>In: Annals of the International Symposium: Recent Advances in Plastic Surgery</source><year>1992</year><publisher-loc>Sao Paulo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Brazilian Society of Plastic Surgery</publisher-name><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>163, ilus</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Tournieux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pr&#x000f3;tese para a regiao gl&#x000fa;tea.</article-title><source>In: Atualiza&#x000e7;ao em Cir&#x000fa;rgia Pl&#x000e1;stica</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>Sao Paulo</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Robe Editorial</publisher-name><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>570</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vergara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intramuscular gluteal implants.</article-title><source>Aesthetic Plast Surg</source><year>1996</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8670394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Ulloa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gluteoplasty: a ten-year report.</article-title><source>Aesthetic Plast Surg</source><year>1991</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1994655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de la Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subfascial technique for gluteal augmentation</article-title><source>Aesthet Surg J</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19336166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Augmentation gluteoplasty: the XYZ method.</article-title><source>Aesthetic Plast Surg</source><year>2004</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15633021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>C&#x000e1;rdenas-Camarena</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Paillet</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combined gluteoplasty: liposuction and gluteal implants.</article-title><source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source><year>2007</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>1074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17312516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>C&#x000e1;rdenas-Camarena</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva-Gavarrete</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Arenas-Quintana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gluteal contour improvement: different surgical alternatives.</article-title><source>Aesthetic Plast Surg</source><year>2011</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>1125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21614658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babuccu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kargi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosnuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Morphology of the gluteal region in the female population 5 to 83 years of age.</article-title><source>Aesthetic Plast Surg</source><year>2004</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15870962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuenca-Guerra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Quezada</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What makes buttocks beautiful? A review and classification of the determinants of gluteal beauty and the surgical techniques to achieve them.</article-title><source>Aesthetic Plast Surg</source><year>2004</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15666052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Centeno</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical anatomy in aesthetic gluteal body contouring surgery.</article-title><source>Clin Plast Surg</source><year>2006</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16818093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>TL</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Weinfeld</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruner</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Universal&#x0201d; and ethnic ideals of beautiful buttocks are best obtained by autologous micro fat grafting and liposuction.</article-title><source>Clin Plast Surg</source><year>2006</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16818095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Constantino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendieta</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification system for gluteal evaluation</article-title><source>Clin Plast Surg</source><year>2006</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16818092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benito-Ruiz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontdevila</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Manzano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hip and buttock implants to enhance the feminine contour for patients with HIV.</article-title><source>Aesthetic Plast Surg</source><year>2006</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16402157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoeller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Huemer</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Otto-Schoeller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Correction of contour deformities of the hip region with a pedicled DIEP flap.</article-title><source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source><year>2007</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17255676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>C&#x000e1;rdenas-Camarena</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Placement of buttock and hip implants: an alternative for contour improvement in buttock and hips hypoplasia</article-title><source>Cir pl&#x000e1;st iberolatinoam</source><year>2012</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hubmer</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwaiger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Windisch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The vascular anatomy of the tensor fasciae latae perforator flap.</article-title><source>Plast Reconstr Surg</source><year>2009</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19568071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Testut</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Latarjet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plexo lumbar.</article-title><source>In: Anatom&#x000ed;a Humana</source><year>1981</year><volume>Vol. III</volume><publisher-loc>Barcelona</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Editorial Salvat</publisher-name><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>325</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Testut</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Latarjet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ramas terminales de la aorta.</article-title><source>In: Anatom&#x000ed;a Humana</source><year>1981</year><volume>Vol. II</volume><publisher-loc>Barcelona</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Editorial Salvat</publisher-name><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>345, 358, 362&#x02013;366</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Testut</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Latarjet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>M&#x000fa;sculos del miembro inferior.</article-title><source>In: Anatom&#x000ed;a Humana</source><year>1981</year><volume>Vol. I</volume><publisher-loc>Barcelona</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Editorial Salvat</publisher-name><fpage>1097</fpage><lpage>1148</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>