<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7243846</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.7797</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Radiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neurosurgery</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Aspirin Preventing Occlusion after Coil Migration into the Distal Anterior Cerebral Artery</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Craven</surname><given-names>Claudia L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>Sophie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rennie</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Toma</surname><given-names>Ahmed K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Neurosurgery, National Hospital for Neurology and Neurosurgery, London, GBR </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Neuroradiology, National Hospital for Neurology and Neurosurgery, London, GBR </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Claudia L. Craven <email>claudia.craven@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>4</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e7797</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2020, Craven et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Craven et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/24983-aspirin-preventing-occlusion-after-coil-migration-into-the-distal-anterior-cerebral-artery">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/24983-aspirin-preventing-occlusion-after-coil-migration-into-the-distal-anterior-cerebral-artery</self-uri><abstract><p>Endovascular coil embolization of cerebral aneurysm is a common procedure for managing cerebral aneurysms. We present a rare case of immediate silent coil migration into the pericallosal artery, without distal occlusion, following successful embolization. Despite the entire coil sitting within the lumen of the artery, good distal flow was observed. The patient remained asymptomatic throughout and had a good long-term (three years to date) outcome (modified Rankin Scale&#x000a0;score of 1). We believe that the novel protective factor was the routine use of a single anti-platelet post-procedure.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>aneurysm</kwd><kwd>endovascular coiling</kwd><kwd>coils</kwd><kwd>intraluminal migration</kwd><kwd>asymptomatic</kwd><kwd>complication</kwd><kwd>antiplatelet</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="disclaimer">The content published in Cureus is the result of clinical experience and/or research by independent individuals or organizations. Cureus is not responsible for the scientific accuracy or reliability of data or conclusions published herein. All content published within Cureus is intended only for educational, research and reference purposes. Additionally, articles published within Cureus should not be deemed a suitable substitute for the advice of a qualified health care professional. Do not disregard or avoid professional medical advice due to content published within Cureus.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Endovascular coil embolization of cerebral aneurysm is a common procedure for managing cerebral aneurysms. Endovascular coil migration is a potentially devastating event after endovascular embolization of cerebral aneurysms, often resulting in infarction and neurological deficit&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Migration can either occur intra-procedurally or be delayed after closure&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Coil migration has been reported in 0.3-6% of cases&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. However, there are only nine case reports on silent coil migration (ranging from three days to six months)&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>-<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. We present a rare case of immediate silent coil migration into the pericallosal artery, without distal occlusion following successful embolization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 62-year-old female with a history of type 2 diabetes, hypertension, and high cholesterol presented with sudden onset headache. She had no family history of intracranial pathology or connective tissue disease and was a non-smoker.</p><p>CT&#x000a0;imaging demonstrated a subarachnoid hemorrhage (SAH) of Fisher grade&#x000a0;4 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="FIG1">1</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="FIG1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>CT imaging demonstrated a subarachnoid hemorrhage of Fisher grade 4 (yellow arrows demonstrate hypodense regions of subarachnoid and bilateral intra-ventricular blood).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0012-00000007797-i01"/></fig><p>Digital subtraction angiography showed a large right saccular pericallosal aneurysm (fundus-to-neck ratio of 5:3), a smaller right pericallosal aneurysm, and a mirror left pericallosal aneurysm (Figures&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="FIG2">2A</xref>,&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="FIG2">2B</xref>). Due to the presence of multiple aneurysms (cloverleaf arrangement), the procedure was performed in two stages. The two right-sided aneurysms (including the ruptured aneurysm) were treated first, and the remaining (left-sided) mirror aneurysm was treated as a second-stage procedure. Coil embolization of the ruptured aneurysm took place under general anesthesia, with two 1.5 x 2 mm three dimensional (3D) Axium&#x02122; coils (Medtronic, Minneapolis, MN, USA) being placed into the large right pericallosal aneurysm and one 1.5 x 2 mm 3D Axium&#x02122; coils being placed in the smaller right pericallosal aneurysm.&#x000a0;The final angiogram showed good placement of the coils (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="FIG2">2C</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="FIG2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>(A) DSA showing a large right saccular pericallosal aneurysm (yellow arrow), a smaller right pericallosal aneurysm (blue arrow), and a left pericallosal aneurysm (red arrow). (B) DSA demonstrating pericallosal mirror aneurysms (yellow arrows). (C) DSA showing coil embolization of the large ruptured right aneurysm (yellow arrow)</title><p>DSA, digital subtraction angiography</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0012-00000007797-i02"/></fig><p>During the procedure, 5,000 units of heparin and 300 mg of aspirin were given. Post-procedure, the patient remained on 75 mg of aspirin daily.</p><p>The second coiling for the left (unruptured) pericallosal aneurysm was performed six days later. During the second angiogram, it was noted that one of the coils (from the larger aneurysm coiling procedure performed six days prior) had migrated into the pericallosal artery (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="FIG3">3A</xref>). The single coil placed into the smaller right adjacent aneurysm had not migrated (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="FIG3">3A</xref>). Despite the entire migrated coil sitting within the lumen of the artery, good distal flow was observed (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="FIG3">3B</xref>). The patient remained on 75 mg of aspirin daily for three months&#x000a0;(as was routine practice at this single center at the time of intervention).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="FIG3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>(A) Angiographic evidence of coil migration into the pericallosal segment (green arrow). Coils remain in the large right aneurysm (yellow arrow) and in the smaller right aneurysm (blue arrow). (B) DSA showing good distal flow maintained (red arrow).</title><p>DSA, digital subtraction angiography</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0012-00000007797-i03"/></fig><p>The previously ruptured aneurysm recurred and has since been secured with surgical clipping (two years post-procedure). The patient had a good long-term outcome (modified Rankin Scale score of 1 at three years after follow-up), with no motor, speech, or cognitive deficits. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) confirmed no evidence of infarction (Figures&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="FIG4">4A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FIG4">4B</xref>). This patient was known to have a normal clotting profile prior to the procedure and had no known intrinsic protective factors. The patient remains asymptomatic.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="FIG4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>(A and B) MRI showing normal ADC in the cortical regions supplied by anterior circulation.</title><p>MRI, magnetic resonance imaging; ADC, apparent diffusion coefficient</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0012-00000007797-i04"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Cases of coil migration are difficult to manage and may involve complex coil retrieval techniques. We present a case whereby the coil migration was silent, potentially owing to the standard use of post-procedure prophylactic aspirin.</p><p>Factors thought to increase the risk of coil migration include (a) coil related factors such as instability of the coil within the aneurysm, over- or under-packing of the coil, and type of coil, and (b) aneurysmal factors such as size, shape, and neck width relative to the fundus, the wall shear stress, and vortical flow within the aneurysm&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Dehydration, vasospasm, and the pro-thrombotic nature of SAH all increase the risk of distal occlusion after coil migration&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Concomitant stent placement has been advocated previously in cases with higher risks of coil migration&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. However, in this case report, there were no features suggesting a high risk of coil migration (with the aneurysm being saccular and a not too wide neck) and no clear indication for the placement of a stent.</p><p>A similar case report of coil migration into the pericallosal segment attributed the preservation of distal flow to spiral shape of a two-dimensional ultrasoft helical coil&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, here we report the maintenance of distal flow, even when using 3D coils.</p><p>Multiple different approaches to manage migrated coils - from medical to surgical - have been reported&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Kamide et al. reported that incidental use of the factor X inhibitor, rivaroxaban (for atrial fibrillation), may have been an important protective factor in preventing distal occlusion in their case report of delayed coil migration (identified at six months post-procedure)&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. This case of immediate coil migration is novel because it appears to be silent, with good distal flow, due to the continuation of prophylactic aspirin post-procedure.</p><p>Studies have shown no overall benefit or increased risk with the routine use of anti-platelet therapy&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].&#x000a0;Many patients who undergo endovascular coiling of a cerebral aneurysm do not receive post-intervention anti-platelet therapy routinely.</p><p>However, there are reports suggesting that&#x000a0;aspirin may be associated with reduced rates of thromboembolic events post-coiling&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The proposed mechanism of activity is both through the direct antiplatelet effect of aspirin and through reduction of the inflammatory response associated with perivascular blood&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Peri-procedural anti-platelet therapy is therefore standard in our center following coiling.</p><p>In our reported case of immediate coil migration, the individual was on a once-daily dose of single anti-platelet, (aspirin 75 mg). Given the lack of other protective factors (use of 3D coils and the lack of other post-procedure medications such as factor X inhibitor and normal clotting profile), aspirin appears to have been the main protective mechanism preventing occlusion. Despite having a coil sitting within the entire lumen of a small artery, the patient remarkably did not develop any occlusion.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>We conclude that maintaining patients on regular aspirin post-procedure could protect against the significant ischemic consequences following coil migration. Furthermore, in certain cases, medical management with regular aspirin may have a lower risk profile than alternative salvage methods such as pursuing the coil using retrieval techniques.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have declared financial relationships, which are detailed in the next section.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p>Ahmed K. Toma declare(s) a grant from National Institute of Health Research (NIHR). Ahmed K. Toma's research time was supported by the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR), University College London Hospitals Biomedical Research Centre. The other authors have no disclosures to report.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Human Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Consent was obtained by all participants in this study</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Retrieval of unintended migrated detached coil: case report</article-title><source>J Cerebrovasc Endovasc Neurosurg</source><person-group><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>268</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><volume>16</volume><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25340030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Coil migration during or after endovascular coiling of cerebral aneurysms</article-title><source>J Neurointerv Surg</source><person-group><name><surname>Abdalkader</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Piotin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><volume>12</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31662464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Delayed asymptomatic coil migrations toward different arteries after aneurysmal embolization: case report</article-title><source>Acta Neurochir (Wien)</source><person-group><name><surname>Kamide</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Misaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nambu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Uchiyama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>598</lpage><volume>159</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28110403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Late coil migration after embolization of cerebral aneurysms - case series</article-title><source>Brazilian neurosurg: arquivos Brasileiros de neurocirurgia</source><person-group><name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>LAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandeira Rocha</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Koppe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Demartini Z</surname><given-names>Jr</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><volume>37</volume><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Asymptomatic delayed coil migration from an intracranial aneurysm: a case report</article-title><source>Case Rep Vasc Med</source><person-group><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Guimaraens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuellar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>901925</fpage><volume>2011</volume><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22937468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Delayed coil migration from a small wide-necked aneurysm after stent-assisted embolization: case report and literature review</article-title><source>Neuroradiology</source><person-group><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><volume>48</volume><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16598480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Effect of antiplatelet therapy for endovascular coiling in aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage</article-title><source>Stroke</source><person-group><name><surname>Van den Bergh</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Algra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinkel</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Molyneux AJ. International Subarachnoid Aneurysm Trial Collaborative</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1969</fpage><lpage>1972</lpage><volume>40</volume><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19390079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Antiplatelet therapy for aneurysmal subarachnoid haemorrhage</article-title><source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source><person-group><name><surname>Dorhout Mees</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Bergh</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Algra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinkel</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>4</volume><year>2007</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Antiplatelet therapy for the prevention of peri-coiling thromboembolism in high-risk patients with ruptured intracranial aneurysms</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><person-group><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanzgiri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Corona</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dannenbaum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><fpage>1326</fpage><lpage>1332</lpage><volume>127</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28059659</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>