<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_ECLINM100345 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">EClinicalMedicine</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">EClinicalMedicine</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>EClinicalMedicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2589-5370</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7264975</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2589-5370(20)30089-4</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eclinm.2020.100345</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100345</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Accumulated environmental risk in young refugees &#x02013; A prospective evaluation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001"><name><surname>Begemann</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002"><name><surname>Seidel</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003"><name><surname>Poustka</surname><given-names>Luise</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004"><name><surname>Ehrenreich</surname><given-names>Hannelore</given-names></name><email>ehrenreich@em.mpg.de</email><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>Clinical Neuroscience, Max Planck Institute of Experimental Medicine, G&#x000f6;ttingen, Germany</aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>Department of Psychiatry &#x00026; Psychotherapy, University Medical Center, G&#x000f6;ttingen, Germany</aff><aff id="aff0003"><label>c</label>Department of Child &#x00026; Adolescent Psychiatry &#x00026; Psychotherapy, University Medical Center G&#x000f6;ttingen, Germany</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0001"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>ehrenreich@em.mpg.de</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="notep0001a">The authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>22</volume><elocation-id>100345</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0001"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Recently, we reported a strong, disease-independent relationship between accumulated preadult environmental risks and violent aggression later in life. Risk factors were interchangeable, and migration was among the explored risks. Alarmed by these data, we assessed collected risk load in young &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; refugees as a specific subgroup of current migration streams and evaluated first signals of behavioral abnormalities.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>In 9 German refugee centers, <italic>n</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;133 young refugees, not previously in contact with the health system, were recruited, many of them unaccompanied minors. Risk factors experienced apart from migration/refuge were carefully assessed: Traumatic experiences before/during/after flight (including war, genocide, human trafficking, torture, murder, slavery, terrorist attacks), urbanicity, physical and sexual abuse, problematic alcohol and cannabis use (lifetime). Evaluation comprised physical exam and psychopathology screening.</p></sec><sec><title>Findings</title><p>Refugees arrived in Germany via Eastern Mediterranean/Balkan route (34.6%), from Africa via Central Mediterranean route (39.1%), by plane (17.3%) or other routes, such as Western Mediterranean or Atlantic (9.0%). Flight reasons were war/expulsion (25.6%), persecution/threats to life (51.9%), economical/others (22.5%). On top of migration/refuge, 42.8% of subjects had &#x02265;3 risk factors; only 4.5% of refugees had no additional risks. Global level of functioning and severity of psychopathology were strongly associated with number of accumulated risks (Jonckheere&#x02013;Terpstra trend-test: <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;7.61&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup> and <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;3.62&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>, respectively).</p></sec><sec><title>Interpretation</title><p>Young refugees, arriving in hosting countries with alarming 'risk burden', should be considered as highly vulnerable towards development of global functional deficits, behavioral abnormalities, and neuropsychiatric disorders. Rapid proactive integration or sustainable support of those who will return to rebuild their countries are mandatory.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>The Max Planck Society supported this work.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="keys0001"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Migration</kwd><kwd>Flight routes</kwd><kwd>Trauma</kwd><kwd>Refugee minors</kwd><kwd>Psychopathology</kwd><kwd>Functioning</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="para1006"><boxed-text id="tbox0002a"><caption><title>Research in context</title></caption><sec id="sec1001a"><title><bold><italic>Evidence before this study</italic></bold></title><p id="para5006a"><bold>In 2005, we started assembling a neuropsychiatric disease population with thus far unprecedented level of phenotyping accuracy, including environmental risk factors. This deep phenotyping provided the ground for our recent discoveries that preadult accumulation of environmental risk factors is associated with a &#x0223c;10-year earlier onset of mental illness, and very robustly with the development of violent aggression/criminality in schizophrenia as well as in the general population. Migration was among the explored risks in these retrospective studies. This in turn led to the present work, aiming at a more prospective assessment of accumulated risks in young refugees and their immediate consequences for behavior, function and psychopathology. Conducting systematic literature searches (Medline, Google Scholar) in preparation of this publication revealed that an appreciable number of papers exists on psychological distress and mental disorders of migrants/refugees, mainly of earlier refuge waves, based on self-reports and questionnaires, but studies specifically targeting accumulation of environmental risk factors in the current refuge situation are rare, and definitely non-existing for young &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; refugees.</bold></p></sec><sec id="sec1002a"><title><bold><italic>Added value of this study</italic></bold></title><p id="para0007"><bold>In a situation where migration/refuge has become a major socio-political issue in whole Europe, and where nearly two million individuals sought asylum in Germany over the last 5 years, the present study demonstrates that young &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; refugees carry a considerable load of accumulated early risk factors. Only 6/133 (4.5%) of our young refugee cohort had no additional risks on top of migration. Global functioning and severity of psychopathology were strongly associated with the number of accumulated risks. Importantly, as we report, the risks are all interchangeable, just the number counts, still leaving room for prevention even after the flight.</bold></p></sec><sec id="sec1003a"><title><bold><italic>Implications of all the available evidence</italic></bold></title><p id="para0008a"><bold>Considering the strong association of preadult risk accumulation with violent aggression and criminality later in life, communities and society in general are challenged to proactively find ways of more efficient integration or to sustainably support the potential of those who will return to their native countries. Re-evaluation of these individuals in several years <italic>&#x02013; in case they are still contactable &#x02013;</italic> will allow to estimate the predictable consequence of societal inactivity, namely a threatening number of subjects that will have developed violent aggression, criminality and radicalism, or severe mental illness.</bold></p></sec><notes notes-type="alt-text" specific-use="for-accessibility" id="alte1a"><p>Alt-text: Unlabelled box</p></notes></boxed-text></p><sec id="sec0001"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="para0009">The impact of environmental risk on neuropsychiatric phenotypes has long been recognized <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. However, studies on accumulation of risk factors, their impact in relation to genetic risk, and their effects on human behavior are sparse. When we started working on preadult accumulation of environmental risk factors, first in schizophrenic individuals, we made several surprising discoveries. Accumulation of &#x02265;3 risk factors before the age of 18 years led to a nearly 10-year earlier onset of schizophrenia; the environmental risk factors were interchangeable, i.e. they could all replace each other, just the number was important; the impact of environmental risk was definitely stronger as compared to any common genetic risk [<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. From these robust findings, we moved on to compare extreme groups for exploring potential epigenetic alterations. Whereas epigenetic findings turned out to be minor, we encountered another unexpected observation during this follow-up study, namely that early accumulation of environmental risk was associated with violent aggressive and criminal behavior in adulthood <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. This finding was obtained in 6 independent samples, including healthy cohorts. Migration, both first and second generation, was again among the environmental risk factors <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. In fact, even once migrants have settled and formed families, their children, the second generation migrants, have an increased and even more pronounced risk of behavioral abnormalities and mental health problems <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p><p id="para0010">In recent years, refuge, a specific subgroup of migration, has become a major socio-political issue in Europe. Since 2014, nearly 2 million individuals sought asylum in Germany, thus attributing to this country the by far biggest share among EU nations [<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Furthermore, the overall number of refugees is highest ever worldwide and likely to increase further <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Reports speak about an enormous burden of mental health disorders in young refugees <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Similar information is available for earlier migration/refuge waves, all based on self-reports and questionnaires <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. However, data on load of accumulated risks and its consequences are completely lacking.</p><p id="para0011">In our previous work, we integrated retrospective data on migration (first and second-generation) as risk factors [<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. The present study was designed to start prospectively evaluating across German refugee asylums the accumulated environmental risk load of young migrants, many of them unaccompanied minors, who were not in previous contact with the health system. We demonstrate here a dramatic risk burden of these individuals on top of migration, and its stair-pattern like association with global functional deficits, behavioral abnormalities, and neuropsychiatric disorders. A follow-up study in several years will reveal data on the development of violent aggression, criminality and radicalism or of severe mental illness in this cohort.</p></sec><sec id="sec0002"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec0003"><label>2.1</label><title>Subjects and recruitment</title><p id="para0012">The Ethic Committee of the Georg-August-University, G&#x000f6;ttingen, approved the present study, complying with the Helsinki Declaration. All subjects gave written informed consent. For recruitment, we approached refugee centers and asked for their willingness to support our study. Of 15 centers contacted, only 9 felt able to provide us with suitable and willing participants (whom they pre-selected and informed). Upon positive feedback, we provided handouts, posters, flyers or other material (e.g. information and consent forms) for announcement through e.g. social workers/group meetings. Involved refugee centers (with refugee characteristics comparable all across) were: Waldkraiburg (34), G&#x000f6;ttingen (24), Bad-Fallingbostel-Oerbke (22), M&#x000fc;hldorf am Inn (18), Heilbad Heiligenstadt (18), Braunschweig (13), W&#x000fc;rzburg (2), Duderstadt (1), Heidelberg (1). Inclusion criteria were recent flight at young age, age at examination &#x02264;30 years, no previous contact with the health system (individuals considered &#x02018;healthy&#x02019;), and the ability to communicate in English or German to widely avoid the need of interpreters as a potential source of uncertainty.</p></sec><sec id="sec0004"><label>2.2</label><title>Sociodemographic data, level of functioning, and psychopathology parameters</title><p id="para0013">An examination booklet was composed for the purpose of the present study to assure a standardized procedure for evaluation (compare GRAS manual <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>). This manual included semi-structured interviews regarding sociodemographic and flight-related parameters, extracts from questionnaires, as well as ratings using established instruments, available in German and English and validated/routinely used across cultures. They comprised the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, both the Hamilton and Montgomery&#x02013;&#x000c5;sberg Depression Scales [<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], the Child Trauma Questionnaire (CTQ) <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF) <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, Clinical Global Impression Scale (CGI) <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, as well as a brief, language-independent cognition test (performance test system subtest-3; 'Leistungspr&#x000fc;fsystem Untertest-3&#x02032; <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>), and physical including neurological examination guidelines. As experienced neurologist and psychiatrist and recruiting expert since 2004 (GRAS study <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>), MB performed all recruitment travel, refugee explorations and examinations in collaboration with local institutions.</p></sec><sec id="sec0005"><label>2.3</label><title>Environmental risk exposure</title><p id="para0014">Specific information was derived from history-taking and semi-structured interviews. In 8 cases (6%) the support of an interpreter turned out to be necessary. Each subject, having immigrated to Germany, was dichotomously classified as having/not having been exposed to: (1) <italic>traumatic experiences before</italic> and (2) <italic>during flight</italic> (war, genocide, slavery, kidnapping, human trafficking, torture, assaults, murder, threats to physical integrity, terrorist attacks, witnessed death of others). Further risk factors were also dichotomously determined according to our previous studies [<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]: (3) <italic>Urbanicity</italic> was operationalized using information on places of residence and relocation. Each city the subjects lived in was allocated to one of four categories according to its total population. The category was then multiplied by the number of years that the person had spent living there. In cases of relocation, the same procedure was repeated for each new place of residence and values were added up to one urbanicity score per individual which was dichotomously grouped into rural and urban places of residence <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Moreover, (4) <italic>severe physical abuse</italic> (comprising unpredictability of violence, injury due to physical reprimand or objects for corporal punishment by family member or close persons), (5) <italic>sexual abuse</italic> (forced touches, kissing, attempted or real rape; any kind of clear sexual actions against the participant's will including negative sexual experiences during flight), (6) <italic>any cannabis consumption,</italic> and (7) <italic>alcohol abuse</italic> (lifetime) were assessed. In case of contradictory or missing information, subjects were rated &#x02018;negative&#x02019; for the respective risk factor analysis. This conservative approach ultimately led to the exclusion of &#x02018;perinatal/birth complications&#x02019; [<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] as an originally planned, yet unreliable risk factor in the present cohort, but did not apply to any other risk information. Single risk factors were then accumulated to obtain the combined influence on level of global functioning, behavior and mental state. To <italic>test for multicollinearity between the risk factors</italic> included in the accumulation model, we calculated the variance inflation factor (VIF). Our results suggest that none of the included factors significantly collinears with any other (VIF&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;1.38, tolerance &#x0003e; 0.72), allowing us to include them in our models.</p><p id="para0015"><italic>Consistency and truth of answers</italic> was systematically ensured by various questions targeting the same topic throughout the interview as well as by careful crosschecking of all obtained information including our extensive physical examination. The Rey Memory Test (RMT) <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> was used as additional indicator of simulating or aggravating behavior. RMT suggests that individuals with low score (i.e. &#x0003c;9 out of 15 correct answers) may simulate or aggravate severity of neurocognitive symptoms. In our sample, only 5 out of 133 participants (&#x0003c;4%) performed with such low score. However, in these cases, the following systematic examination and the use of all obtained information led us to the conclusion that their answering throughout our examination (including information on previous contact with the mental health system) was consistent and true.</p></sec><sec id="sec0006"><label>2.4</label><title>Statistical analysis of environmental risk</title><p id="para0016">Group differences for continuous variables were assessed using Mann&#x02013;Whitney-<italic>U</italic> or Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis-<italic>H</italic> test for comparison of &#x0003e;2 groups. Frequency differences between groups were assessed using Fisher's exact test. As trend tests, Jonckheere&#x02013;Terpstra or Cochran&#x02013;Armitage tests were applied. Bonferroni correction accounted for multiple testing (<italic>p</italic>-values withstanding correction denoted). All statistical analyses as well as the creation of <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>(A) have been carried out using R v3.5.2 (R-Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria) with RStudio v1.1.463 (RStudio Inc., Boston, United States).<fig id="fig0001"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Countries of origin and routes of flight to Germany as well as overview of the number of experienced risk factors. (A) Map integrating information on countries of origin and routes of flight to Germany (<italic>n</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;133). (B) Number of experienced risk factors. Note that 43% of subjects have an accumulation of 3 or &#x02265;4 risk factors on top of migration. (C) Dichotomous presentation of experienced risk.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec0007"><label>2.5</label><title>Role of funding</title><p id="para0017">The funder of the study had no role in study design, data collection, data analysis, data interpretation, or writing of the report. The corresponding author had full access to all the data in the study and had final responsibility for the decision to submit for publication.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec0008"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p id="para0018">In 9 German refugee centers, a total of <italic>n</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;133 young refugees (&#x0223c;80% males), not previously in contact with the health system, were recruited from June 2018 to May 2019, many of them unaccompanied minors (age at flight: 18.3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.1 years; age at arrival in Germany: 20.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.3; age at examination: 22.1&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.4). Those who agreed in the first place to participate in the study did complete it (no dropouts among the individuals pre-selected by the refugee centers). Flight routes and countries of origin of this sample of young &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; refugees are displayed in <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>(A). Refugees arrived in Germany via Eastern Mediterranean/Balkan route (34.6%), from Africa via Central Mediterranean route (39.1%), by plane (17.3%) or other routes, such as Western Mediterranean or Atlantic route (9.0%). Flight reasons were war/expulsion (25.6%), persecution and threats to life (51.9%), economical and others (22.5%). Most individuals had a passport from Afghanistan (27), or came from Nigeria (23), Syria (12) and Iraq (11). Distribution of countries of origin and sample composition may be somewhat biased by our request to avoid the need of interpreters, mainly to assure transparency of information. Except for 8 individuals, where interpreters had finally to be involved, communication in German or English was sufficiently possible. Around 60% of refugees traveled alone, 40% together with family or friends, but the accumulation of risks did not seem to be influenced by this fact (<italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.292), nor the degree of psychopathology or level of functioning (all <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003e;&#x0202f;0.3). Similarly, being post-flight in a close and stable relationship as a potentially protective factor (only 25%) did not affect accumulated risks nor outcome (all <italic>p</italic>&#x0202f;&#x0003e;&#x0202f;0.3).</p><p id="para0019">We assumed that the route, e.g. the highly dangerous African/Central-Mediterranean versus the Middle East/Eastern-Mediterranean route, would prime flight experiences. Nevertheless, there was no appreciable difference in assessed risk accumulation or outcome measures dependent on the flight route. Evaluation of experienced risks on top of migration identified 42.8% of subjects with &#x02265;3 risk factors; only 4.5% of refugees had no additional risks (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>(B)).</p><p id="para0020"><xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>(C) gives a dichotomous overview of the presence of risk factors. Over 50% of subjects suffered traumatic experiences before and during the flight, with most individuals coming from urban environment as an additional risk factor. Physical exam uncovered that many asylum seekers had suffered not only from psychological injuries. In fact, 54 individuals (40%) exhibited severe scars/wounds from externally inflicted injuries, such as gunshots, shrapnel or stab wounds, bomb explosions, burning or electrical shocks. All other readouts of physical exam were unremarkable; none of the subjects had any detectable neurological symptoms including soft signs.</p><p id="para0021">Additional physical and sexual abuse (apart from flight experiences) became evident in 27% and 14%, respectively. Drug consumption was, in good agreement with recent literature <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, relatively low, with cannabis and alcohol amounting to 15% and 7%. Importantly, however, among the consumers of cannabis, 4 unaccompanied male refugees (3%), still minors during the flight, revealed clear and thus far undetected psychotic symptoms, 2 of them with suicidality.</p><p id="para0022">Neuropsychiatric and functional outcome evaluation disclosed highly significant associations between accumulation of risk factors on top of migration and global functioning (GAF; <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(A)) as well as degree of psychopathology (<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(B)). These findings are illustrated using a psychopathology composite score, consisting of Clinical Global Impression (CGI), <italic>PANSS</italic> total, Hamilton Depression Scale, and Montgomery&#x02013;&#x000c5;sberg Depression Scale (Cronbach's alpha 0.952). Striking stair-patterns arise upon graphical presentation (<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). We tested our risk accumulation models additionally via linear regression and found comparable results for both GAF (intercept&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;99.45; amount of risk&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;&#x02212;5.85; <italic>F</italic><sub>(1; 131)</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;29.64; <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.48&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>; <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.185) and psychopathology composite score (intercept&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;&#x02212;0.76; amount of risk&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.34; <italic>F</italic><sub>(1; 131)</sub>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;28.07; <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.81&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup>; <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x0202f;=&#x0202f;0.177). Importantly, essentially all single psychopathology readouts by themselves were already significant (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).<fig id="fig0002"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Accumulation of environmental risk factors in young &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; flight migrants and their association with level of functioning and psychopathological outcome. (A) Risk accumulation and functional outcome rated by the Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF) scale; note the stair-like decrease in daily life functioning in relation to the amount of negative environmental risk experienced. (B) Risk accumulation and severity of psychopathology, rated as composite score of Clinical Global Impression (CGI), total score of Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale, <italic>PANSS</italic>, as well as Hamilton and Montgomery&#x02013;&#x000c5;sberg Depression Scales; note the stair-like increase in psychopathology with increasing numbers of risks; z-scores adjusted to positive values. Two-sided Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis <italic>H</italic>-test and one-sided Jonckheere&#x02013;Terpstra test for trends (below; italics) presented.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effects of accumulated environmental risk on functioning and psychopathology in young refugees</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002a">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Number of risk factors on top of migration:</th><th valign="top" align="center">0</th><th valign="top" align="center">1</th><th valign="top" align="center">2</th><th valign="top" align="center">3</th><th valign="top" align="center">&#x02265;4</th><th valign="top">p value</th><th valign="top">p value</th></tr><tr><th valign="top"/><th valign="top">n=6 (4.5%)</th><th valign="top">n=34 (25.6%)</th><th valign="top">n=36 (27.1%)</th><th valign="top">n=32 (24.0%)</th><th valign="top">n=25 (18.8%)</th><th valign="top"><bold>(&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>,&#x000a0;<italic>H</italic>)</bold></th><th valign="top"><bold>(z,&#x000a0;<italic>J</italic>)</bold>*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><bold>Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF)</bold></td><td valign="top">99.17 (2.04)</td><td valign="top">92.24 (11.94)</td><td valign="top">89.22 (11.14)</td><td valign="top">83.19 (18.79)</td><td valign="top">74.24 (17.03)</td><td valign="top"><bold>2.68&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10</bold><sup><bold>-5</bold></sup> (<italic>H</italic>=26.36)</td><td valign="top"><bold>7.61&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup></bold> (<italic>J</italic>=2189)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>Clinical Global Impression (CGI)</bold></td><td valign="top">1.00 (0.00)</td><td valign="top">1.50 (0.93)</td><td valign="top">1.75 (1.00)</td><td valign="top">2.34 (1.54)</td><td valign="top">3.04 (1.43)</td><td valign="top"><bold>9.44&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></bold> (<italic>H</italic>=28.60)</td><td valign="top"><bold>4.78&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup></bold> (<italic>J</italic>=4610)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold><italic>PANSS</italic> total</bold></td><td valign="top">30.17 (0.41)</td><td valign="top">31.21 (2.17)</td><td valign="top">33.19 (4.52)</td><td valign="top">36.38 (11.44)</td><td valign="top">39.08 (11.19)</td><td valign="top"><bold>9.16&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup></bold> (<italic>H</italic>=18.66)</td><td valign="top"><bold>4.17&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></bold> (<italic>J</italic>=4369)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold><italic>PANSS</italic> positive</bold></td><td valign="top">7.00 (0.00)</td><td valign="top">7.03 (0.17)</td><td valign="top">7.25 (0.76)</td><td valign="top">7.81 (2.66)</td><td valign="top">8.20 (2.61)</td><td valign="top">0.024 (<italic>H</italic>=11.27)</td><td valign="top">0.020 (<italic>J</italic>=3899)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold><italic>PANSS</italic> negative</bold></td><td valign="top">7.00 (0.00)</td><td valign="top">7.06 (0.24)</td><td valign="top">7.33 (0.86)</td><td valign="top">9.19 (6.18)</td><td valign="top">9.12 (3.58)</td><td valign="top"><bold>0.001</bold> (<italic>H</italic>=17.80)</td><td valign="top"><bold>0.002</bold> (<italic>J</italic>=4094)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold><italic>PANSS</italic> general</bold></td><td valign="top">16.17 (0.41)</td><td valign="top">17.12 (2.10)</td><td valign="top">18.61 (3.70)</td><td valign="top">19.38 (4.89)</td><td valign="top">21.76 (6.35)</td><td valign="top"><bold>0.002</bold> (<italic>H</italic>=17.23)</td><td valign="top"><bold>7.91&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></bold> (<italic>J</italic>=4330)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>Diagnoses**</bold></td><td valign="top">0 (0.0%)</td><td valign="top">7 (20.6%)</td><td valign="top">9 (25.0%)</td><td valign="top">14 (43.8%)</td><td valign="top">18 (72.0%)</td><td valign="top"><bold>9.19&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></bold> (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>=23.64)</td><td valign="top"><bold>1.63&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></bold> (<italic>z</italic>=-4.65)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>Hamilton Depression Scale</bold></td><td valign="top">0.17 (0.41)</td><td valign="top">1.71 (3.21)</td><td valign="top">2.64 (3.77)</td><td valign="top">3.69 (5.67)</td><td valign="top">8.00 (7.69)</td><td valign="top"><bold>3.56&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></bold> (<italic>H</italic>=25.75)</td><td valign="top"><bold>8.73&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></bold> (<italic>J</italic>=4459)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>Montgomery-&#x000c5;sberg Depression Scale</bold></td><td valign="top">0.17 (0.41)</td><td valign="top">1.50 (2.79)</td><td valign="top">3.00 (4.30)</td><td valign="top">4.59 (7.06)</td><td valign="top">8.64 (9.72)</td><td valign="top"><bold>2.24&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup></bold> (<italic>H</italic>=21.76)</td><td valign="top"><bold>1.13&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup></bold> (<italic>J</italic>=4444)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>Psychopathology composite score (<italic>z</italic>)</bold></td><td valign="top">-0.62 (0.05)</td><td valign="top">-0.38 (0.49)</td><td valign="top">-0.17 (0.62)</td><td valign="top">0.15 (1.08)</td><td valign="top">0.71 (1.24)</td><td valign="top"><bold>1.03&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup></bold> (<italic>H</italic>=28.42)</td><td valign="top"><bold>3.62&#x0202f;&#x000d7;&#x0202f;10<sup>&#x02212;7</sup></bold> (<italic>J</italic>=4624)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>Suicidality</bold></td><td valign="top">0 (0.0%)</td><td valign="top">2 (5.9%)</td><td valign="top">1 (2.8%)</td><td valign="top">0 (0.0%)</td><td valign="top">6 (24.0%)</td><td valign="top">0.009 (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>=15.48)</td><td valign="top">0.013 (<italic>z</italic>=-2.24)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Urbanicity, physical abuse, sexual abuse, problematic alcohol use, cannabis use, traumatic experiences before flight, and traumatic experiences during flight are included in the accumulation model; data are uncorrected means (SD) or n (%); for statistical analysis, Kruskal-Wallis-<italic>H</italic> or Fisher's exact test was used. <italic>PANSS</italic>, Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale; psychopathology composite score consists of scores of Clinical Global Impression, <italic>PANSS</italic> total, Hamilton Depression Scale, and Montgomery-&#x000c5;sberg Depression Scale, yielding a Cronbach's alpha of 0.952; suicidality, individuals with recent suicide attempts. <bold>The p values withstanding Bonferroni correction are bolded.</bold> *To test for statistical trends, one-sided Cochran-Armitage trend (qualitative traits) or Jonckheere-Terpstra trend (quantitative traits) tests were used. **&#x02019;Diagnoses&#x02019; refer to mental disease diagnoses obtained during exam of refugees, previously considered &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; (mainly PTSD).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec0009"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="para0023">In the present investigation, a substantial load of accumulated environmental risk factors became obvious in young &#x02018;healthy&#x02019; refugees on top of migration/refuge.</p><p id="para0024">Pre-flight and flight experiences of these young individuals frequently included extreme poverty, genocide, war, experience of terror, torture, persecution for ethnic or religious reasons or sexual orientation, kidnapping, slavery, human trafficking, sexual exploitation, forced labor, physical maltreatment, separation trauma, experiencing or witnessing assaults, massacres, rape and other threats to physical integrity, as well as murder and terrorist attacks.</p><p id="para0025">Post-flight experiences, i.e. problems upon arrival in the hosting country, <italic>here Germany</italic>, comprised problematic living conditions, multiple relocations, non-access to education and labor, maladaptation to language and culture, uncertain legal and residential status. In addition, social exclusion and hostility towards foreigners and refugees constitute post-flight reality. Especially in young refugees, this devastating situation adds to their already severe identity crisis with all its consequences for self and society. This may at least partly explain the increased suicidality of young migrants seen here and reported elsewhere <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>.</p><p id="para0026">As in our previous work [<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], also in the present study, which directly targeted refugees, the deleterious effect of preadult risk accumulation on human behavior, level of functioning and well-being becomes drastically evident. Again, the composition of risk factors, the 'risk cocktail', is apparently less relevant for the overall outcome of individuals as compared to the number of accumulated risks, which ultimately determines the result. The harm to the juvenile brain, both psychological and physiological, seems to add up in a venomous fashion on brain functions in the sense of <italic>dosis facit venenum</italic>. It is thus not too surprising, that there was no appreciable difference in outcome measures, global functioning and psychopathology, dependent on the flight route. It appears that environmental hazards, striking at a vulnerable time of brain development, differ in their initial mechanisms of action on the brain, but likely feed into final common deleterious pathways downstream. Knowledge on hypothetical biological mechanisms underlying this accumulation effect are mainly derived from animal models. Molecular pathways and functions affected seem multifaceted, ranging from neuroendocrine and neurotransmitter systems, neuronal/synaptic plasticity and neurogenesis, to changes in the adaptive immune system and interference with developmental myelination, affecting brain connectivity and network function [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p><p id="para0027">Coping and help-search strategies are to an essential degree influenced by social status, education, familial, religious, and sociocultural values. We chose mainly individuals with whom communication in German or English was sufficiently possible. This certainly introduced some bias towards higher educational level of included subjects, likely evolving as a protective factor, boosting resilience. Surprisingly, however, we did not see in our sample any appreciable effect of supposed protective factors, e.g. flight alone versus with company, or of being in a close relationship post-flight, on number of accumulated risks or on outcome. This lack of associations may be due to the still relatively small sample size, but strong effects at least are unlikely.</p><p id="para0028">Empathic attitude in the host country toward young refugees, addressing health and educational needs as well as secure sheltering, will generate confidence and stability, thus ultimately contributing to a positive outcome of these individuals. However, we should not forget the strong associations shown in 6 independent cohorts of accumulated preadult risk with violent aggression and criminality later in life <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, imposing a clear threat to societal inactivity with regard to integration. Predictable consequences may include a threatening number of subjects that will have developed severe aggression, criminal behavior, and potentially even radicalism, apart from those suffering from severe mental illness.</p><p id="para0029">In fact, also to prevent such consequences, communities and society in general are challenged either to find successful and proactive ways of fast integration in the German/European heritage or to swiftly but sustainably support the potential of those who will return for rebuilding and/or contributing to prosperity and welfare in their native countries. Re-evaluation of still contactable individuals in several years will allow estimating the predictable consequences of societal dormancy, namely a considerable number of high-risk subjects that will have developed violent aggression, criminality and radicalism. Reducing this number should be our common goal.</p><p id="para0030">An important impulse, expected from the present study, is to inform current policies and guidelines and to encourage respective innovative strategies. These include careful initial physical examination, regular health check-ups of refugees and prevention of further risk accumulation. This might be achieved through generation of alternatives to typical refugee accommodations and ghettos, integration from scratch by distributing refugees immediately among other citizens as well as keeping them positively busy. Refugees should be enabled to move away from just being cared-for to self-help plans. A somewhat provocative but ultimately successful idea would be to provide instantaneously jobs/contracts and let them earn their own modest living by supportive work. This requires perhaps modifications of existing legislation, but could then start immediately after the refuge and should be accompanied by regular social worker visits and language training/courses, until the decision of staying or leaving has been made by the authorities. Meanwhile refugees should be free to search in parallel for more adequate jobs with respect to their education or for apprenticeships.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title><p id="para0031">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebibl1"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0001"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Os</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutten</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The environment and schizophrenia</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>468</volume><issue>7321</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21068828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The environment and susceptibility to schizophrenia</article-title><source>Prog Neurobiol</source><volume>93</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20955757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lederbogen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirsch</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>City living and urban upbringing affect neural social stress processing in humans</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>474</volume><issue>7352</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21697947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orlovska</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benros</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortensen</surname><given-names>P.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agerbo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordentoft</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Head injury as risk factor for psychiatric disorders: a nationwide register-based follow-up study of 113,906 persons with head injury</article-title><source>Am J Psychiatry</source><volume>171</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>469</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24322397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McEwen</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasca</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress effects on neuronal structure: hippocampus, amygdala, and prefrontal cortex</article-title><source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source><volume>41</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26076834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nemeroff</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paradise lost: the neurobiological and clinical consequences of child abuse and neglect</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>89</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>892</fpage><lpage>909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26938439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ehrenreich</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of environment on abnormal behavior and mental disease: to alleviate the prevalence of mental disorders, we need to phenotype the environment for risk factors</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28348000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stepniak</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papiol</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accumulated environmental risk determining age at schizophrenia onset: a deep phenotyping-based study</article-title><source>Lancet Psychiatry</source><volume>1</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>444</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26361199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saher</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uncoupling the widespread occurrence of anti-NMDAR1 autoantibodies from neuropsychiatric disease in a novel autoimmune model</article-title><source>Mol Psychiatry</source><volume>24</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1489</fpage><lpage>1501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29426955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantor-Graae</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Selten</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Schizophrenia and migration: a meta-analysis and review</article-title><source>Am J Psychiatry</source><volume>162</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15625195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0011"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR)</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Global trends: forced displacement in 2018</chapter-title><year>2019</year><publisher-name>Author</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mental-health crisis among migrants</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>538</volume><issue>7624</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27734887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demazure</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaultier</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinsault</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dealing with difference: a scoping review of psychotherapeutic interventions with unaccompanied refugee minors</article-title><source>Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29214387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Awad</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fathi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petermann</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinelt</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Promoting mental health in unaccompanied refugee minors: recommendations for primary support programs</article-title><source>Brain Sci</source><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Werthern</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigorakis</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vizard</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mental health and wellbeing of unaccompanied refugee minors (URMs)</article-title><source>Child Abuse Negl</source><volume>98</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104146</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henssler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk of psychosis among refugees: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Psychiatry</source><volume>76</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>1140</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derluyn</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eurelings-Bontekoe</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinhoven</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing psychological distress, traumatic stress reactions, and experiences of unaccompanied refugee minors with experiences of adolescents accompanied by parents</article-title><source>J Nerv Ment Dis</source><volume>195</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17435478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eurelings-Bontekoe</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinhoven</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Course and predictors of mental health of unaccompanied refugee minors in the Netherlands: one year follow-up</article-title><source>Soc Sci Med</source><volume>64</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>1204</fpage><lpage>1215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17188787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vervliet</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lammertyn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derluyn</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal follow-up of the mental health of unaccompanied refugee minors</article-title><source>Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source><volume>23</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23979476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vervliet</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer Demott</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakobsen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heir</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Derluyn</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The mental health of unaccompanied refugee minors on arrival in the host country</article-title><source>Scand J Psychol</source><volume>55</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25130065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0021"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derluyn</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mels</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mental health problems in separated refugee adolescents</article-title><source>J Adolesc Health</source><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19237116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0022"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derluyn</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuyten</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Temmerman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-traumatic stress in former Ugandan child soldiers</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>363</volume><issue>9412</issue><year>2004</year><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15031032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0023"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagdev</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunniff</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk and resilience for psychological distress amongst unaccompanied asylum seeking adolescents</article-title><source>J Child Psychol Psychiatry</source><volume>49</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18492037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0024"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sleijpen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeije</surname><given-names>H.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleber</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooren</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Between power and powerlessness: a meta-ethnography of sources of resilience in young refugees</article-title><source>Ethn Health</source><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26107385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smid</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lensvelt-Mulders</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knipscheer</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gersons</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleber</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Late-onset PTSD in unaccompanied refugee minors: exploring the predictive utility of depression and anxiety symptoms</article-title><source>J Clin Child Adolesc Psychol</source><volume>40</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>742</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21916692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0026"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0026"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ribbe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedrichs</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Begemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cross-sectional GRAS sample: a comprehensive phenotypical data collection of schizophrenic patients</article-title><source>BMC Psychiatry</source><volume>10</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>91</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21067598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0027"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0027"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiszbein</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Opler</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The positive and negative syndrome scale (PANSS) for schizophrenia</article-title><source>Schizophr Bull</source><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1987</year><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3616518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0028"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rating scale for depression</article-title><source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source><volume>23</volume><year>1960</year><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14399272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0029"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new depression scale designed to be sensitive to change</article-title><source>Br J Psychiatry</source><volume>134</volume><issue>4</issue><year>1979</year><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">444788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahluvalia</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pogge</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Handelsman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validity of the childhood trauma questionnaire in an adolescent psychiatric population</article-title><source>J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</source><volume>36</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1997</year><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9055514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0031"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0031"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders</chapter-title><edition>4th ed., Text Revision</edition><year>2000</year><publisher-name>Author</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0032"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0032"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Clinical Global Impressions</collab></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><source>ECDEU assessment manual for psychopharmacology</source><year>1976</year><publisher-name>US Department of Health, Education, and Welfare Public Health Service Alcohol, Drug Abuse, and Mental Health Administration</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Rockville, MD</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0033"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0033"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>L-P-S Leistungspr&#x000fc;fsystem</chapter-title><edition>2 ed.</edition><year>1983</year><publisher-name>Hogrefe</publisher-name><publisher-loc>G&#x000f6;ttingen</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0034"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0034"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitjans</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Begemann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Violent aggression predicted by multiple pre-adult environmental hits</article-title><source>Mol Psychiatry</source><volume>24</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1549</fpage><lpage>1564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29795411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>The clinical examination in psychology</chapter-title><year>1964</year><publisher-name>University Press of France</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0036"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0036"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dykxhoorn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollander</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkbride</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substance use disorders in refugee and migrant groups in Sweden: a nationwide cohort study of 1.2 million people</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><volume>16</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1002944</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0037"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0037"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corcoran</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeley</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mental health difficulties and suicidal behaviours among young migrants: multicentre study of European adolescents</article-title><source>BJPsych Open</source><volume>3</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29234521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0038"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0038"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korosi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naninck</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oomen</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early-life stress mediated modulation of adult neurogenesis and behavior</article-title><source>Behav Brain Res</source><volume>227</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21821065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0039"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0039"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nave</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrenreich</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myelination and oligodendrocyte functions in psychiatric diseases</article-title><source>JAMA Psychiatry</source><volume>71</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>582</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24671770</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0001"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by the <funding-source id="gs0001"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004189</institution-id><institution>Max Planck Society</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>. The authors thank all subjects for participating in the study.</p></ack></back></article>