<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Nanobiotechnology</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Nanobiotechnology</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Nanobiotechnology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1477-3155</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5877387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">354</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12951-018-0354-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Nanoparticles engineered to bind cellular motors for efficient delivery</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dalmau-Mena</surname><given-names>Inmaculada</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>del Pino</surname><given-names>Pablo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pelaz</surname><given-names>Beatriz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cuesta-Geijo</surname><given-names>Miguel &#x000c1;ngel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Galindo</surname><given-names>Inmaculada</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moros</surname><given-names>Mar&#x000ed;a</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de la Fuente</surname><given-names>Jes&#x000fa;s M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0862-6177</contrib-id><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>Covadonga</given-names></name><address><email>calonso@inia.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2300 669X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419190.4</institution-id><institution>Dpt. Biotecnolog&#x000ed;a, </institution><institution>Instituto Nacional de Investigaci&#x000f3;n y Tecnolog&#x000ed;a Agraria y Alimentaria (INIA), </institution></institution-wrap>Carretera de la Coru&#x000f1;a km 7.5, 28040 Madrid, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2152 8769</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11205.37</institution-id><institution>Instituto de Nanociencia de Arag&#x000f3;n, Universidad de Zaragoza, </institution></institution-wrap>Mariano Esquillor, s/n, 50018 Zaragoza, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000109410645</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11794.3a</institution-id><institution>Centro Singular de Investigaci&#x000f3;n en Qu&#x000ed;mica Biol&#x000f3;xica e Materiais Moleculares (CiQUS), Departamento de F&#x000ed;sica de Part&#x000ed;culas, </institution><institution>Universidad de Santiago de Compostela, </institution></institution-wrap>15782 Santiago de Compostela, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1763 291X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.429738.3</institution-id><institution>Aragon Materials Science Institute (ICMA), </institution><institution>CSIC-University of Zaragoza and CIBER-BBN, </institution></institution-wrap>C/Pedro Cerbuna 12, 50009 Zaragoza, Spain </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>33</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Dynein is a cytoskeletal molecular motor protein that transports cellular cargoes along microtubules. Biomimetic synthetic peptides designed to bind dynein have been shown to acquire dynamic properties such as cell accumulation and active intra- and inter-cellular motion through cell-to-cell contacts and projections to distant cells. On the basis of these properties dynein-binding peptides could be used to functionalize nanoparticles for drug delivery applications.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">Here, we show that gold nanoparticles modified with dynein-binding delivery sequences become mobile, powered by molecular motor proteins. Modified nanoparticles showed dynamic properties, such as travelling the cytosol, crossing intracellular barriers and shuttling the nuclear membrane. Furthermore, nanoparticles were transported from one cell to another through cell-to-cell contacts and quickly spread to distant cells through cell projections.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">The capacity of these motor-bound nanoparticles to spread to many cells and increasing cellular retention, thus avoiding losses and allowing lower dosage, could make them candidate carriers for drug delivery.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12951-018-0354-1) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Nanoparticles</kwd><kwd>Biomimetic synthetic peptides</kwd><kwd>Drug delivery</kwd><kwd>Microtubule motors</kwd><kwd>Dynein</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Ministerio de economia, industria y competitividad de Espa&#x000f1;a</institution></funding-source><award-id>AGL2012-34533</award-id><award-id>AGL2015-69598-R</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>Covadonga</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Ministerio de economia, industria y competitividad</institution></funding-source><award-id>SAF2014-54763-C2-2-R</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>de la Fuente</surname><given-names>Jes&#x000fa;s M.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000781</institution-id><institution>European Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>239931-NANOPUZZLE</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>de la Fuente</surname><given-names>Jes&#x000fa;s M.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>UE COST Action</institution></funding-source><award-id>CA15138 Transautophagy</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>Covadonga</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Conselleria de Cultura, Educacion y Ordenacion Universitaria</institution></funding-source><award-id>2016&#x02013;2019</award-id><award-id>ED431G/09</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>del Pino</surname><given-names>Pablo</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par4">Motor proteins are biological molecules that transform chemical energy into mechanical force at the nanoscale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. These molecular motors can be integrated into hybrid biological and synthetic systems to functionalize nanoparticles (NPs) for biotechnological applications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par5">Engineered nanocomposites have been built in order to overcome intracellular barriers and to mimic how intracellular pathogens such as viruses transfer their genetic material into the cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Several design strategies have been tested in order to increase NPs translocation through cellular membranes, thereby enhancing transfection efficiency. Ligands conjugated to the surface of engineered NPs such as sugars [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] can influence the mode of cellular internalization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Nevertheless, NPs of the same composition may use alternative mechanisms for cell entry in different cell types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Once inside the cell and given the crowded gel-like composition of the cytoplasm, the movement of organelles and macromolecules is restricted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Furthermore, eukaryotic cells are compartmentalized by endomembrane systems and cytoskeleton filaments of actin, and microtubules are used as tracks for transport. This transport relies on energy-dependent molecular motors that are necessary for communication between compartments. To move in a crowded cellular environment poses problems to NP displacement and thus, vector design strategies have included different mediators of intracellular trafficking in order to facilitate this transport, some of them considering the cytoskeleton [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In fact, viruses, strictly depending on their capacity to invade and control the intracellular environment, have developed specific strategies to bind microtubule motors to facilitate their transport along these filaments to reach the perinuclear area and initiate replication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Microtubule motor binding is crucial for the replication and dissemination of several viruses. In-depth knowledge of some of these strategies of virus-cell interaction can be exploited to design virus-free delivery systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">We used a biomimetic approach based on selected peptide sequences from viral proteins known to bind dynein. Dynein is a microtubule motor acting as a hub protein within the microtubule-motor complex, which exerts several functions related to movement in mammalian cells. This protein is responsible for cargo transport within cells, up to organelle-size cargoes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. It is also responsible of nuclear positioning within the cell and has several functions in mitosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Onset of mitosis is marked by centrosome migration for the mitotic spindle formation that requires dynein. Also, dynein action on microtubules leads to nuclear envelope breakdown at early mitosis and to its reorganization after the end of cell division [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The loss of nuclear compartmentalization induced by the breakdown of the nuclear envelope is characterized by increased permeability together with the initiation of the nuclear pore disassembly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Thus, dynein has the potential capability to drive nuclear envelope disassembly and permeate this layer, that is, a particularly important property since the nuclear membrane is the &#x0201c;last barrier&#x0201d; for gene delivery in non-dividing cells.</p><p id="Par8">Dynein exists within a complex of several subunits and adapters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] and contains two heavy chains and several intermediate, light intermediate and light chains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. One of the light chains is DYNLL1, a highly evolutionarily conserved protein that is hijacked by a number of viral proteins for transport [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The high affinity interaction of viral proteins with DYNLL1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] and its ability to form long half-live molecular complexes make this molecule especially appropriate to build supramolecular structures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Then, we used peptide sequences from viral proteins interacting with DYNLL1 to modify NPs based in the hypothesis that this modification could confer dynamic properties to the NPs, enhancing their motility and dispersion in the intracellular environment.</p><p id="Par9">In the present work, gold NPs (Au NPs) have been modified with short peptide sequences taken from viral proteins that bind dynein. We found a highly active intracellular trafficking and cellular uptake of those modified carriers in several cell lines. Dynein-binding peptides (DBPs) modified NPs were motile throughout the cytosol and travelled from cell-to-cell favoring the propagation of this uptake. By this active cellular transport, NPs acquired the property to shuttle the nuclear membrane in non-dividing cells.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Dynein-binding peptides modified nanoparticles design</title><p id="Par10">Here, we report the production of water-soluble and stable Au NPs modified with DBPs as an efficient approach for cargo delivery. Au NPs of different sizes have been widely used because of lack of apparent toxicity, and easy elimination by renal clearance in case NPs are small enough (sizes bellow 10&#x000a0;nm) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Coating NPs with organic molecules and/or macromolecules has been typically employed in order to improve NP stability and prevent aggregation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], as for instance Au NPs coated with tiopronin (Au@tiopronin) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Tiopronin is a thiolated derivative of the amino acid glycine. Au@tiopronin were prepared using the procedure originally reported by Murray et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. These NPs consist of small (typically, core diameter&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;3&#x000a0;nm) Au NPs stabilized with the non-natural aminoacid tiopronin (<italic>N</italic>-2-mercaptopropionylglycine), which has a free terminal carboxyl group, allowing to functionalize Au@tiopronin with aminated molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], such as the DBPs sequences, by carbodiimide chemistry, <italic>cf</italic>. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The reaction was executed in a methanolic/acetic acid mixture, dissolving HAuCl<sub>4</sub> and tiopronin to give a stable solution. The addition of NaBH<sub>4</sub> as reducing agent provided a dark solution by reduction of the gold salt and formation of the NPs. Acidic conditions are very important to guarantee the protonation of tiopronin carboxylic groups, and provide an efficient and dense self-assembled monolayer of tiopronin onto the NPs. The obtained NPs were colloidally stable in aqueous solution. The excess of tiopronin and salts was eliminated by dialysis. The purified NPs were characterized by TEM and UV/Vis, <italic>cf</italic>. Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1. TEM images showed a mean diameter of 2.8&#x000a0;nm for the Au core (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). The UV/Vis absorption spectra showed an almost non-detectable surface plasmon band consistent with the small NP size of the NPs, <italic>cf.</italic>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>&#x000a0;Scheme of NPs synthesis (Au@tiopronin) and functionalization with dynein-binding peptides (DBP) and PEG. <bold>b</bold>&#x000a0;TEM image of Au@tiopronin. Scale bar: 20&#x000a0;nm</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12951_2018_354_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par11">Using the reactivity of the tiopronin carboxylic group, further functionalization with aminated molecules was carried out using a procedure previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>): 1) Aminated poly(ethylene glycol) (PEG) derivative (CH<sub>3</sub>O-PEG-NH<sub>2</sub>); 2) different peptide sequences (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) and 3) fluorescent dye TAMRA-CAD (<italic>i.e.</italic>, tetramethylrhodamine 5-carboxamide cadaverine), which was used to optimize carbodiimide coupling conditions. PEG molecules were selected to avoid unspecific interactions. A dense layer of PEG confers anti-fouling properties to nanomaterials, thereby increasing their colloidal stability in aqueous solution and reducing unspecific interactions with other molecules such as plasma proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Alias, sequence and molecular weight (MW) of the peptides used to surface modify the Au@tiopronin NPs</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Alias</th><th align="left">Amino acid sequence</th><th align="left">MW (Da)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">DynPro</td><td align="left">GGGGK(TAMRA)-HPAEPGSTVTTQNTASQTMS-RRRRRRRR</td><td char="." align="char">4063.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ShortPro</td><td align="left">GGGGGGGGK(TAMRA)-YTTQNTASQTMS-RRRRRRRR</td><td char="." align="char">3578.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TrasnRb</td><td align="left">GGGGGGGGK(TAMRA)-FPNPSGRSSEDKSTQTAG-RRRRRRRR</td><td char="." align="char">4112.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IntCt</td><td align="left">GGGGK(TAMRA)-SLVSSDESVLHGSHESGEHV-RRRRRRRR</td><td char="." align="char">4110.5</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par12">The selected dynein-binding peptide (DBP) sequences were synthetic peptides spanning the dynein-binding domain of different proteins, <italic>cf.</italic> Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. We selected three peptides: DynPro (dynein-propelled) derived from the product of the E183L gene of the African swine fever virus (p54) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]; ShortPro, a shorter sequence of the same protein based on the critical amino acids for dynein-binding; and TransRb derived from the Rabies virus P protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. As a negative control, a non-dynein-binding amino acid sequence (IntCt) was selected. To guarantee the proper presentation of the peptides and minimize steric hindrance due to a dense packaging of molecules on the NP surface, a tetra- or octa-glycine tail was added to DynPro and IntCt, or ShortPro and TransRb, respectively. After the glycine-tail, a lysine residue was added. Primary amine moieties of the lysine residues were used for fluorescent labeling with 5-carboxytetramethylrhodamine (TAMRA). Finally, an octa-arginine tail was added to these peptides&#x02019; end, including to the control peptide IntCt, to increase the positive charge of the peptides, thereby enhancing cellular uptake, <italic>cf.</italic> Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><p id="Par13">NPs&#x000b4;carboxyl groups and primary amines of the selected ligands (PEG derivative, TAMRA-CAD and DBPs) were crosslinked with the water-soluble carbodiimide N-[3-(dimethylamino)propyl]-N&#x02019;-ethylcarbodiimide hydro-chloride (EDC). N-hydroxysulfosuccinimide (sulfo-NHS) was also included in the reaction mixture to improve the efficiency of the carbodiimide-mediated amide-forming reaction by producing hydrolysis-resistant active ester reaction intermediates (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The resultant library of NPs was analyzed by &#x003b6;-potential, UV/Vis and fluorescence spectroscopy, probing that the molecules were incorporated to the NPs and the absence of aggregation after peptide coupling, <italic>cf</italic>. Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S3.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Modified nanoparticles internalization</title><p id="Par14">NPs covalently functionalized with TAMRA-labeled peptides were visualized by live-cell imaging, which allowed tracking of their movement at the intracellular level. The cellular uptake of Au@tiopronin NPs modified with DBPs (Au@DBPs; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b, e&#x02013;h) was significantly more efficient compared to those functionalized with the control peptide IntCt (<italic>i.e.</italic>, Au@IntCt) in Vero cells (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c). Similar results were obtained with other cell lines, such as the neuroblastoma cell line SK-N-MC, the epithelial cell line MDCK, HeLa (derived from a human epithelial carcinoma) and HEK293T cell line (human kidney embryonic transformed cell line; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d&#x02013;h). Time-dependent intracellular accumulation was observed from 20 to 120&#x000a0;min with Au@DBPs and Au@IntCt (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>i). Concentration of Au@DBPs increased until 180&#x000a0;min, remaining stable thereafter and visible up to 12&#x000a0;h. Quantitative fluorescence percentages were also analyzed by flow cytometry with increasing doses of NPs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>j). Overall, the cellular distribution among the functionalized Au@DBPs was similar (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a&#x02013;c). Au@DBPs were rapidly internalized and distributed widely within the cell and throughout the culture. While NPs stability in cell culture media was clearly observed, PEG modification did not result in significant modification of Au@DBPs uptake in cells incubated with 0.2&#x000a0;mg/ml NPs (ca. 1.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M NPs) for several times 1, 2 or 3&#x000a0;h (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S4).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Cellular distribution of NPs. <bold>a</bold>, <bold>d</bold>&#x000a0;Mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) of intracellular Au@tiopronin modified with DynPro (Au@DynPro) or IntCt (Au@IntCt) after 1&#x000a0;h incubation with Vero cells (<bold>a</bold>) and other cell lines (<bold>d</bold>). Differences in MFI between Au@DBPs and Au@IntCt (control) were statistically significant <italic>p</italic> value of 0.001 (&#x003b1;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05). In contrast, differences among Au@DBPs were not significant with a <italic>p</italic> value of 0.3 (&#x003b1;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05; not shown).&#x000a0;<bold>b</bold> Representative confocal images of Vero cells incubated with Au@DynPro or <bold>c</bold> Au@IntCt. <bold>e</bold>&#x02013;<bold>h</bold>&#x000a0;Representative confocal images of SK-N-MC (<bold>e</bold>), HeLa (<bold>f</bold>), 293T (<bold>g</bold>) and MDCK cells incubated with Au@DynPro.&#x000a0;Scale bar: 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m. <bold>i</bold> Time-dependent accumulation of Au@DynPro at several time points between 20 and 120&#x000a0;min, as indicated. <bold>j</bold> Fluorescence intensity percentages at increasing doses of Au@DynPro quantified by flow cytometry</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12951_2018_354_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Representative confocal images at low magnification of <bold>a</bold> Vero cells with Au@DynPro <bold>b</bold> HEK293T cells with Au@ShortPro and <bold>c</bold> MDCK cells with Au@TransRb. Representative images showed similar NP dispersion throughout the culture and cell-to-cell transfer of Au@DynPro through short (<bold>b</bold>) or long (<bold>c</bold>) projections.&#x000a0;<bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold> Representative time-lapse images of the linear progression of Au@DBP inside the cell and the resulting trajectories (circles).&#x000a0;<bold>f</bold> Comparison with the non-linear movement obtained with control NPs Au@IntCt. Scale bar: 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12951_2018_354_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Nanoparticles dynamic properties</title><p id="Par15">Time-lapse videomicroscopy unraveled Au@DBP bidirectional movement across the cytosol and a continuous flow to cell projections reaching neighboring or distant cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a-c and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Movie 1). Also, we observed bidirectional movement towards the cell periphery, to cell projections and intercellular cell-to-cell transport. No differences were found among Au@DBPs in terms of distribution and dynamic properties (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a&#x02013;c, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Movies 1, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Movies 2). Au@DBPs exhibited high-speed mobility (median speed 0.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m/s). This movement followed linear trajectories allowing progression of Au@DBPs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d, e). In contrast, the movement of NPs functionalized with control peptide (Au@IntCt) was non-progressive, non-linear (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>f).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Microtubule-dependent transport of nanoparticles</title><p id="Par16">Linear movement of Au@DBPs, with occasional pauses and alternating directions, suggested that this was a microtubule-dependent transport. During the first minutes after incubation, Au@DBPs were rapidly internalized, moved and accumulated near the nucleus at the microtubule-organizing center (MTOC) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). This preferential localization of Au@DBPs at the MTOC was found in non-polarized cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). Conversely, in polarized cells, movement was directed to the cell periphery and to cell projections (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c). Linear movement of Au@DBPs was bidirectional, reached the cell periphery and projections being transported from one cell to another. These characteristics were found for all Au@DBPs tested.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Accumulation of Au@DynPro at the MTOC near the nucleus&#x000a0;(N). <bold>b</bold> Progression of Au@DynPro towards the MTOC, or <bold>c</bold> nucleus and projections (arrows) in GFP-tubulin transfected cells. <bold>d</bold>&#x02013;<bold>i</bold> Au@DynPro&#x000b4;s mobility was sensitive to microtubule-depolimerizing drugs.&#x000a0;<bold>d</bold>, <bold>g</bold>&#x000a0;Widespread cellular distribution of Au@DynPro before depolymerizing drug treatment,&#x000a0;<bold>e</bold> Au@DynPro transport blockade and accumulation after 1&#x000a0;h drug incubation with 2.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M Nocodazole, and <bold>f</bold> mobility and dispersion recovery after washing.&#x000a0;<bold>g</bold> Vero cells treated with 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M Au@DynPro and then&#x000a0;<bold>h</bold> incubated for 1&#x000a0;h with 0.1&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M actin depolymerizing-drug LatrunculinA. This drug produced cell shrinkage because of actin cytoskeleton collapse that was not recovered after washing (<bold>i</bold>). However, Au@DynPro transport was still preserved within cells and projections. Scale bar: 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12951_2018_354_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par17">Au@DBP dispersed distribution, movement and spread (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>d) was reversibly stopped with the microtubule depolymerizing agent Nocodazole (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>e). After washing and media replacement, movement and dispersion of Au@DBPs in the culture were recovered (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>f). In contrast, drugs that depolymerize the actin cytoskeleton, such as Latrunculin A, did not stop the motion of the Au@DBP between cells through projections, even under conditions of cell collapse after actin cytoskeleton depolimerization (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>g&#x02013;i). This effect was not reversible by washing and media replacement as expected.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Efficient transport of Au@DBP across the nuclear membrane</title><p id="Par18">Au@DBPs crossed the nuclear envelope and travelled the nuclear compartment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). This property was found for all the different Au@DBPs tested but not for the control Au@IntCt (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c). Au@DBPs produced a visible imprint of their movement along the nucleus that was physically evident using bright field microscopy as linear protrusions as Au@DBPs moved through the nuclear area and the nucleolus (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a, b, g).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>&#x000a0;Nuclear penetration capacity of Au@DynPro&#x000a0;(n: nucleus). <bold>c</bold>&#x02013;<bold>e</bold> Nuclear envelope appeared discontinuous as Au@DynPro shuttle the nucleus in Vero cells transfected with GFP-laminB receptor (<bold>c</bold>) and GFP-laminB1 (<bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold>) as shown in equatorial optical sections. Sample images show NPs entering the nucleus and nuclear lamina folding at sites of NPs entry.&#x000a0;<bold>f</bold> Peptides shuttle the nucleus in Vero cells transfected with GFPB23 nucleolin (<bold>g</bold>) Au@DynPro in their way across the nucleus with visible imprints of their paths&#x000a0;(<bold>b</bold>, arrow). Scale bar: 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12951_2018_354_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par19">Au@DBPs travelled across the nuclear envelope and the nuclear lamina, as shown in GFP-laminB receptor (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c) and GFP-laminB1 transfected cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d, e). In fact, Au@DBPs produced invaginations of the nuclear envelope at multiple sites (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c&#x02013;e).</p><p id="Par20">In the nucleolus, peptides colocalized with GFP-B23 nucleolin as they crossed the nucleolus, without affecting the morphology of this structure (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>f). Similarly, Au@DBPs entered nucleolus (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>g).</p><p id="Par21">It is important to note that cell viability and cell proliferation were unaffected with any Au@DBP formulation (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S5).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par22">Molecular motors have previously allowed developing nanoscale transport systems powered by biomolecular motors or molecular shuttles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Peptides binding to a cellular protein that is highly evolutionarily conserved (DYNLL1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and a molecular hub building long-life molecular complexes in cells, made this transport very efficient in a number of cell lines tested, including mammalian cells and some of non-mammalian origin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">Here, the dynamic properties of DBPs were successfully translated into Au NPs (<italic>i.e.</italic>, Au@DBPs), which may be highly useful in the drug delivery area. These results are in agreement with previous reports that employed soft carriers, such as microspheres [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>] or liposomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], functionalized with dynein light chain 8 (LC8) peptide binding motifs. Similarly, in the present work, we selected peptides able to bind a dynein chain with very high affinity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], which were linked to hard Au@tiopronin NPs. In our study, non-significant differences regarding dynamic properties between Au@DBPs and &#x0201c;bare&#x0201d; DBPs were observed. Probably, this fact occurs due to the small size of our Au NPs, limiting the interaction of one dynein with one NP. Moreover, a previous theoretical work suggested that motor protein binding molecules attached to solid carriers work collectively rather than cooperatively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">NPs are small particles (from a few to 200&#x000a0;nm in diameter) especially useful for delivery as can be aerosolized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], can be made highly biocompatible, allow site specific targeting to a specific cell population, permit controlled drug release and can be designed to biodegrade in an acceptable time span [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. The stability found for Au@DBPs and long times of persistence inside the cultured cells, make them suitable candidates for drug delivery. The Au@DBPs ability for spreading to neighboring cells remaining intracellular would improve efficacy and optimize dosage for compounds to be delivered.</p><p id="Par25">Dynein has a central role in the formation of the mitotic spindle during mitosis and interacts dynamically with the nuclear envelope directing assembly and reassembly of nuclear lamins. The penetration capacity of Au@DBPs could rely on the ability of dynein to interact dynamically with the nuclear envelope and thus direct the disassembly of nuclear lamins as it occurs at early stages of mitosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Other cell delivery mechanisms allow entering the nucleus efficiently only in dividing cells, because of nuclear envelope rearrangements naturally occurring at prometaphase. In contrast, Au@DBPs are virus-free delivery vehicles that elicited nuclear envelope reorganization also in non-dividing cells. Hence, Au@DBPs were able to take advantage of these properties, move in the crowded cellular environment and change the permeability of the nucleus compartment.</p><p id="Par26">Targeting of drugs and NPs to tumors poses particular difficulties in delivery; drugs only penetrate few cells around blood vessels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. This problem is particularly found in solid tumors, which are poorly perfused because blood vessels and lymphatics are usually dysfunctional. The leakiness of tumor vessels impairs enhanced permeability and retention effect of compounds delivered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The capacity of Au@DBPs to be transferred from one cell to another could boost spreading of therapeutic NPs reaching neighboring cells. This would allow optimal dosage, increasing therapeutic effect and minimizing side effects.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par27">We have shown dynein-motor powered NP motility in the crowded cellular environment and across the nuclear envelope. The dynamic properties of these Au@DBPs made them especially appropriate to load compounds and achieve the desired requirements of intracellular delivery to all compartments. Moreover, the quick spreading of these functionalized NPs between cells, remaining intracellular, reduces exposure to the extracellular environment minimizing eventual loses. These characteristics, together with their intracellular accumulation capacity would in turn allow reductions on administration doses of a given drug or therapy because of its better biodisponibility in a handful of applications.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Peptides and cell lines</title><p id="Par28">Peptide sequences spanned the DYNLL1 binding domain of viral proteins (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), that is, African swine fever virus p54 (DynPro) and a shorter sequence including critical amino acids for binding (ShortPro), Rabies virus P protein (TransRb), and control non-dynein-binding amino acid sequence (IntCt). An octa-arginine tail was added to all these peptides, which were also labeled with TAMRA. Peptides were synthesized and purified by HPLC over 95% of purity by Genecust. The following cell lines were tested: Vero kidney epithelial cells (ATCC CCL-81), Madin-Darby Canine Kidney Epithelial Cells (MDCK; ATCC CCL-34), Human embryonic kidney cells transformed with adenovirus 5 (HEK293T/17; ATCC CRL-11268), and Epidermal cancer cells (HeLa; CCL-2). Cells were cultured in DMEM with FBS from Lonza. SK-N-MC human neuroblastoma cells were cultured in EMEM with pyruvate (ATCC HTB-10). These mammalian cells were incubated in sterile 35-mm culture dishes with 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M peptides, or 1.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M NPs, in a CO<sub>2</sub> incubator at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;h and then imaged.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Chemicals for nanoparticle synthesis</title><p id="Par29">All the chemicals were of reagent grade and were used without further purification. Hydrogen tetrachloroaureate (III) trihydrate (99.9%), (N-(3-dimethylaminopropyl)-N&#x000b4;-ethylcarbodiimide hydrochloride, Tris(hydroxymethyl) aminomethane (TRIS,&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;98.8%) and 2-[N-morpholino] ethanesulfonic acid (99.5%) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich; N-(2-mercaptopropionyl) glycine (&#x0003e;&#x02009;98%) and N-hydroxysulfosuccinimide (&#x0003e;&#x02009;97%) were purchased from Fluka and NaBH<sub>4</sub> (98%) from Lancaster. Dynein binding peptides (DBPs, <italic>i.e.</italic> DynPro, ShortPro and TransRb) and the control peptide (IntCt) were purchased from Genecust; &#x003b1;-methoxy-&#x003c9;-amino polyethylene glycol (CH<sub>3</sub>O-PEG-NH<sub>2</sub>, 750&#x000a0;Da) was obtained from Rapp-Polymere. Tetramethylrhodamine 5&#x02013;carboxamide cadaverine (TAMRA-CAD) was purchase from Anaspec. Phosphate buffer saline (PBS) was obtained from Lonza. House distilled water was further purified using a Milli-Q reagent grade water system (Millipore). Buffers were prepared according to standard laboratory procedure. Other chemicals were reagent grade and used as received.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Nanoparticle synthesis and characterization</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Characterization</title><p id="Par30">UV&#x02013;Vis spectra were carried out with Varian Cary 50 spectrophotometer. Florescence spectra were carried out with a LS-55 Fluorescence Spectrometer. &#x003b6;-potential measurements were done using a ZetaPALS analyser from Brookhaven. All spectra were collected in MilliQ water; for &#x003b6;-potential characterization the aqueous solution was adjusted to 1&#x000a0;mM KCl. For TEM examinations, a single drop (5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l) of the aqueous solution (0.1&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) of the Au NPs was placed onto a copper grid coated with a carbon film. The grid was left to dry in air for several hours at room temperature. TEM analysis was carried out on a Tecnai 20 FEI microscope operated at 200&#x000a0;kV. Particle size distribution of the Au NPs was evaluated from several micrographs using a program for image processing and analysis (ImageJ).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Au@tiopronin</title><p id="Par31">Hydrogen tetrachloroaureate(III) trihydrate (0.15&#x000a0;g, 0.4&#x000a0;mmol) and N-(2-mercaptopropionyl) glycine (tiopronin; 0.19&#x000a0;g, 1.2&#x000a0;mmol) were codissolved in 20&#x000a0;ml of 6:1 methanol/acetic acid, giving a ruby red solution. NaBH<sub>4</sub> (0.30&#x000a0;g, 8.0&#x000a0;mmol) in 7.5&#x000a0;ml of H<sub>2</sub>O was added with rapid stirring. The black suspension that was formed was stirred for an additional 30&#x000a0;min after cooling, and the solvent was then removed under vacuum at 40&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. The crude Au@tiopronin was completely insoluble in methanol but quite soluble in water. It was purified by dialysis, in which the pH of 130&#x000a0;mg of crude product dissolved in 20&#x000a0;ml of water was adjusted to 1 by dropwise addition of concentrated HCl. This solution was loaded into 15&#x000a0;cm segments of seamless cellulose ester dialysis membrane (Sigma, MWCO 10&#x000a0;kDa), placed in 4&#x000a0;l beakers of water, and stirred slowly, recharging with fresh water approximately every 10&#x000a0;h over the course of 72&#x000a0;h. The dark blue Au@tiopronin solutions were collected from the dialysis tubes and were lyophilized. Yield: 96&#x000a0;mg.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Au@peptides/TAMRA-CAD/PEG</title><p id="Par32">N-(3-Dimethylaminopropyl) -N&#x000b4;-ethylcarbodiimide hydro-chloride (EDC; 1&#x000a0;mg, 5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;mol) and N-hydroxysulfosuccinimide (sulfo NHS; 3&#x000a0;mg, 13.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;mol) were added to 1&#x000a0;ml of Au@tiopronin (1&#x000a0;mg) in 2-[N-morpholino] ethanesulfonic acid (MES) (50&#x000a0;mM, pH 6.5). NPs were left to react with EDC (carbodiimide activation) over 30&#x000a0;min at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C under mild stirring conditions. NPs were then purified of excess EDC and sulfo NHS) over a PD-10 column (GE Healthcare). The peptide DynPro (27.5&#x000a0;nmol) or ShortPro (27.5&#x000a0;nmol) or TransRb (27.5&#x000a0;nmol) or IntCt3 (27.5&#x000a0;nmol) or TAMRA-CAD (55&#x000a0;nmol) were added and the mixture was stirred over 1&#x000a0;h at room temperature before the addition of CH<sub>3</sub>O-PEG-NH<sub>2</sub> (750&#x000a0;Da; 2.6&#x000a0;&#x000b5;mol) for coupling to remaining activated carboxylic groups; then samples were left under mild stirring conditions at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C overnight. Then, this solution was loaded into centrifugal filters (Amicon Ultra-0.5&#x000a0;ml, MWCO 10&#x000a0;kDa) for three consecutive steps of purification of potentially uncoupled peptide, TAMRA or PEG, and concentration of the mixture prior to suspension in water. For preventing the possible absorption (non-covalently attached to the NPs) of TAMRA or any of the peptides, samples (0.5&#x000a0;ml at 2&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;mL<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) were loaded into ca. 1&#x000a0;cm segments of seamless cellulose ester dialysis membrane (Sigma, MWCO 10&#x000a0;kDa), placed in 1&#x000a0;l beakers of a solution 1&#x000a0;M NaCl in MilliQ water, and stirred slowly over the course of 72&#x000a0;h, recharging with fresh saline solution approximately every 10&#x000a0;h. Then, samples were desalted over a PD-10 column, concentrated with centrifugal filters (Amicon Ultra-0.5&#x000a0;ml, MWCO 10&#x000a0;kDa), suspended in PBS (for cell cultures) or water (for characterization) at 2&#x000a0;mg&#x000a0;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and filtrated over 0.22&#x000a0;&#x000b5;m cellulose filters for sterilization. &#x003b6;-potential measurements are shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1; UV&#x02013;Vis and fluorescence spectra are shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figures S1 and S2.</p><p id="Par33">Control samples were prepared for all of the peptide types and TAMRA using the same conditions with the exception of EDC and S-NHS, aiming to prove that unspecific absorption of the peptides on the NPs was avoided. Theses samples were cleaned as the activated samples and they were characterized by UV/Vis and fluorescence spectroscopy, showing the absence of observable unspecific absorption (<italic>i.e.</italic>, lack of fluorescence).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Incubation of cells with nanoparticles</title><p id="Par34">All the experiments were carried out under sterile conditions working with microbiological class II safety cabinets. The NPs were resuspended in H<sub>2</sub>O, with a degree of purity milliQ and sterile, to obtain stock solutions at different concentrations. Special attention was paid to avoid turbidity in the solution and tips were always used with a filter to avoid possible cross contaminations. 500&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l aliquots were stored at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until the time of use. Working solutions of the NPs were made from stock solutions in DMEM SC medium (10% Foetal bovine serum (FBS), 1% penicillin/streptomicyn (PS), 1% Glutamine (G)) and adjusted to 0.2&#x000a0;mg/ml (1.5 &#x003bc;M NPs). The maximum number of NPs used per cell was estimated to be 2.7&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;NPs/cell, that is, 300&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of a solution of 1.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M NPs that was added to 10<sup>5</sup> cells. In order to perform in vitro assays, Vero cells were cultured in 35&#x000a0;mm glass plates overnight. The cells were washed in DMEM SC (10% FBS, 1% PS, 1% G) and the existing medium was replaced by 300&#x000a0;ml of the solutions containing the NPs at optimal concentration of 1.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M. The NPs were incubated in incubation chambers at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and 5% CO2 and observed with the confocal microscope. The incubation time periods ranged from 20&#x000a0;min to 3&#x000a0;h to observe different degree of accumulation in the cells.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Plasmids and transfections</title><p id="Par35">A vector encoding enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP)-LBR (Lamin B receptor) was kindly provided by Loren Fong from UCLA. Plasmid encoding EGFP-Lamin B1 was a generous gift of Howard Worman from Columbia University New York. EGFP-tubulin and &#x02013;actin, were from Clontech. A vector encoding B23 nucleolar protein was kindly provided by Carmen Rivas from Centro Nacional de Biotecnolog&#x000ed;a, Madrid.</p><p id="Par36">Transfections were performed by using the TransIT 2020 Transfection Reagent from Mirus according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations. Briefly, Vero cells were grown on 35&#x000a0;mm tissue culture plates, in DMEM (5% FBS, 1% PS, 1% G), until 80% confluence. Separately, 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of DMEM, serum- and antibiotics-free, was mixed with 0.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g of DNA and 1.3&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of TransIT 2020. The mixture was incubated for 20&#x000a0;min at room temperature before addition to cells. To minimize cytotoxicity and increase the efficiency of the transfection, cells medium was replaced by 300&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of fresh DMEM 5% serum and antibiotics-free before adding the DNA-TransIT mixture. Similarly, after 4&#x000a0;h, the transfection mixture was removed from cells and 500&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of fresh medium (5% FBS, 1% PS, 1% G) was added. At 24&#x000a0;h after transfection, cells were incubated with the NPs as explained below and analyzed by confocal microscopy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Inhibition assays</title><p id="Par37">Nocodazole was used at concentration of 2.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M and actin depolymerizing Latrunculin A at 0.1&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M. We first ensured that cytotoxicity, determined by the trypan blue exclusion method, did not exceed 10% of cell death after drug incubation at the indicated working concentrations. Cells were pretreated for 30&#x000a0;min with inhibitors at the indicated working concentrations in growth medium for 30&#x000a0;min at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, further incubated with 1.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M of NPs for 30&#x000a0;min at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and then imaged. After 2&#x000a0;h, culture medium was replaced and washed for 1&#x000a0;h and then imaged.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Cell viability and proliferation assays</title><p id="Par38">To evaluate cell viability after incubation with peptides and NPs, Vero cells seeded in 24 well plates were incubated in DMEM containing delivery DBP or negative control IntCt at concentrations ranging from 0 to 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M of each peptide. For NPs the concentrations were ranging from 0 to 1&#x000a0;mg/ml (1&#x02013;7.5&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M NPs). After incubation with peptides or nanoparticles for 24&#x000a0;h, cells were harvested and the number of viable cells present in the cell suspensions was determined by Tripan blue dye exclusion assay (Sigma). Briefly, 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of PBS with Tripan Blue 0.08% (w/v) were added to equal volume of cell suspension and mixed. After 2&#x000a0;min, blue cells (dead cells) were counted using a hematocytometer and a conventional light microscope.</p><p id="Par39">To evaluate cell proliferation 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> Vero cells/well seeded in 96 well plates were incubated in 50&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l DMEM containing DBPs and negative control or NPs at the range of concentrations previously used in the cell viability assays. After 24&#x000a0;h incubation, cell proliferation was determined using CellTiter 96 Aqueous&#x02122; (Promega) assay, following manufacturer&#x000b4;s indications.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Flow cytometry</title><p id="Par40">Vero cells seeded in 24-well plates were incubated for 120&#x000a0;min at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with Au@DBPs at several concentrations. Then, cells were washed with PBS, harvested by trypsinization and washed again with flow cytometry buffer (PBS, 0.01% sodium azide and 0.1% bovine serum albumin). In order to determine the fluorescence intensity per dose, 10,000 cells/per each Au@DBPs concentration were scored and analysed in a FACS Canto II flow cytometer (BD Sciences).</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Time-lapse video microscopy</title><p id="Par41">Confocal microscopy was carried out using a Leica TCS SPE confocal microscope that included a humidified incubation chamber, a CO<sub>2</sub> controller and a heating unit. Selected stacks were recorded every 10-s using the Leica Microsystems LAS AF program and the films were displayed at 1&#x02013;5 frames/s.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Fluorescence quantification</title><p id="Par42">To quantify the intracellular accumulation of different DBP, cytoplasmic and background regions were selected and mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) quantified. Final MFI was calculated as indicated (cytoplasmic region&#x02014;background). Quantitative analysis of MFI was performed with the Leica LAS-AF imaging program. At least thirty cells from three independent experiments were examined for each formulation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par43">One-way analysis of variance was performed with the statistical package GraphPad InStat. Bonferroni&#x02019;s correction was applied for multiple comparisons. Data were presented as mean standard deviations. Differences were considered statistically significant with a <italic>p</italic> value of 0.001 (&#x003b1;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec25"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12951_2018_354_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Figure S1.</bold> UV/Vis spectra of &#x0201c;bare&#x0201d; NPs (Au@tiopronin) before the modification, and peptide, PEG or TAMRA-CAD modified NPs. a) DBP (red line, Au@tiopronin-DynPro), IntCT (cyan line, Au@tiopronin-IntCt) and TAMRA (blue line, Au@tiopronin-IntCt-TAMRA-CAD); b) DBP-PEG (red line, Au@tiopronin-DynPro/PEG), IntCT-PEG (cyan line, Au@tiopronin-IntCt/PEG) and TAMRA-PEG (blue line, Au@tiopronin-IntCt-TAMRA-CAD/PEG). <bold>Figure S2.</bold> Fluorescence spectra of &#x0201c;bare&#x0201d; NPs (Au@tiopronin) before the modification, and peptide, PEG or TAMRA-CAD modified NPs. a) DBP (red line, Au@tiopronin-DynPro), IntCT (cyan line, Au@tiopronin-IntCt) and TAMRA (blue line, Au@tiopronin-IntCt-TAMRA-CAD); b) DBP-PEG (red line, Au@tiopronin-DynPro/PEG), IntCT-PEG (cyan line, Au@tiopronin-IntCt/PEG) and TAMRA-PEG (blue line, Au@tiopronin-IntCt-TAMRA-CAD/PEG).<bold> Figure S3.</bold> &#x003b6;-potential bar diagram of &#x0201c;bare&#x0201d; NPs (Au@tiopronin) before the modification, and modified peptide or TAMRA-CAD modified NPs: DBP (Au@DynPro), IntCT (Au@IntCt), TAMRA (Au@TAMRA-CAD), DBP-PEG (Au@DynPro/PEG), IntCT-PEG (Au@IntCt/PEG) and TAMRA-PEG (Au@TAMRA-CAD/PEG).<bold> Table S1.</bold> &#x003b6;-potential values of &#x0201c;bare&#x0201d; NPs (Au@tiopronin) before the modification, and peptide, PEG or TAMRA-CAD modified NPs: DBP (Au@DynPro), IntCT (Au@IntCt), TAMRA (Au@TAMRA-CAD), DBP-PEG (Au@DynPro/PEG), IntCT-PEG (Au@IntCt/PEG) and TAMRA-PEG (Au@TAMRA-CAD/PEG).<bold> Figure S4.</bold> The figure shows the cellular uptake (according to intracellular MFI) of Au@DynPro, Au@DynPro-PEG, compared to nanoparticles modified with internal control peptide (IntCt), Au@IntCt and Au@IntCt-PEG. Mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) of modified NPs after 1 h incubation.<bold> Figure S5.</bold> This figure shows the absence of cytotoxic effect of the NPs in Vero cells. Cell viability (a) and cell proliferation (b) were analyzed after incubation of cells with increasing concentrations of the different Au@DBP that exceeded those used in this study. A significant decrease in cell counts or cell proliferation was not observed.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12951_2018_354_MOESM2_ESM.avi"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 2: Movie 1.</bold> Motion beyond cell boundaries. This movie shows a general view of Au@DBP motion and dispersion in 293T cells incubated with 0.2&#x000a0;mg/ml of Au@DynPro during 1.5&#x000a0;h. Au@DBP displayed short and long tracks of bidirectional motion along a cell projection connecting a neighboring cell. Movement results in transfer of Au@DynPro to the latter. The time lapse covers about 7&#x000a0;min at a rate of 5&#x000a0;frames/s.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12951_2018_354_MOESM3_ESM.avi"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 3: Movie 2.</bold> Intracellular movement of NPs linear trajectories. This movie displays a Vero cell incubated with Au@DynPro at 0.2&#x000a0;mg/ml during 1.5&#x000a0;h showing linear and stable tracks of directed motion in the perinuclear area. The time lapse covers 40&#x000a0;s at a rate of 3&#x000a0;frames/s.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12951-018-0354-1) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>ID, PdP, JMF and CA designed the research plan and experiments. ID, PdP, BP, MAC-G, IG and MM carried out the experiments. ID, PdP, JMF and CA wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="Par44">We thank H. Worman from Columbia University for EGFP-LaminB1, L. Fong from UCLA for the EGFP-Lamin B receptor and C. Rivas at CNB-UAM, Madrid for the EGFP-B23 nucleolar protein. We also thank P. Lammerding, Y. Hern&#x000e1;ndez and V. Graz&#x000fa; for suggestions. The authors thank I. Echaniz and S. Rivera for technical assistance.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par45">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par46">All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article (and its additional files).</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par47">All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par48">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par49">The present work was supported by grants from the Spanish Ministry of Economy, Industry and Competiveness AGL2012-34533, AGL2015-69598-R, SAF2014-54763-C2-2-R, Fondo Social de la DGA (grupos DGA), ERC-Starting Grant 239931-NANOPUZZLE and COST Action CA15138 Transautophagy. PdP and BP thanks financial support from the Conseller&#x000ed;a de Cultura, Educaci&#x000f3;n e Ordenaci&#x000f3;n Universitaria (Centro singular de investigaci&#x000f3;n de Galicia accreditation 2016&#x02013;2019, ED431G/09), and the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF).</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par50">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Engineering applications of biomolecular motors</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biomed Eng</source><year>2011</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-bioeng-071910-124644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21639779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolomeisky</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Motor proteins and molecular motors: how to operate machines at the nanoscale</article-title><source>J Phys Condens Matter</source><year>2013</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>463101</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0953-8984/25/46/463101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24100357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falanga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitiello</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantisani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarallo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Guarnieri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mignogna</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A peptide derived from herpes simplex virus type 1 glycoprotein H: membrane translocation and applications to the delivery of quantum dots</article-title><source>Nanomedicine</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>925</fpage><lpage>934</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nano.2011.04.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21664490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moros</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernaez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Garet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Saez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Grazu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Monosaccharides versus PEG-functionalized NPs: influence in the cellular uptake</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1565</fpage><lpage>1577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nn204543c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22214244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bareford</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaan</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endocytic mechanisms for targeted drug delivery</article-title><source>Adv Drug Deliv Rev</source><year>2007</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>748</fpage><lpage>758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addr.2007.06.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17659804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Varela</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of transport inhibitors on the cellular uptake of carboxylated polystyrene nanoparticles in different cell lines</article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e24438</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0024438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21949717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular shuttles based on motor proteins: active transport in synthetic environments</article-title><source>J Biotechnol</source><year>2001</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11999714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruenraroengsak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Florence</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biphasic interactions between a cationic dendrimer and actin</article-title><source>J Drug Target</source><year>2010</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>811</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/1061186X.2010.521159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20932230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pun</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bio-mimetic surface engineering of plasmid-loaded nanoparticles for active intracellular trafficking by actin comet-tail motility</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>958</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2008.10.059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19046764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barua</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rege</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of mediators of intracellular trafficking on transgene expression efficacy of polymer-plasmid DNA complexes</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>5894</fpage><lpage>5902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2010.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20452664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Miskin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernaez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez-Zapatero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Soto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Canto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>African swine fever virus protein p54 interacts with the microtubular motor complex through direct binding to light-chain dynein</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2001</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>9819</fpage><lpage>9827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.75.20.9819-9827.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11559815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leopold</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral strategies for intracellular trafficking: motors and microtubules</article-title><source>Traffic</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0854.2006.00408.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16643275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherer</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez-Soto</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Horensavitz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pypaert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mothes</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retroviruses can establish filopodial bridges for efficient cell-to-cell transmission</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb1544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17293854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Enquist</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Break ins and break outs: viral interactions with the cytoskeleton of Mammalian cells</article-title><source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.18.012502.105920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12142276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Narita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nuclear transport of Epstein-Barr virus DNA polymerase is dependent on the BMRF1 polymerase processivity factor and molecular chaperone Hsp90</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2013</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>6482</fpage><lpage>6491</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.03428-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23552409</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dodding</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Way</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coupling viruses to dynein and kinesin-1</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2011</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>3527</fpage><lpage>3539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2011.283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21878994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelkar</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Crystal</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Leopold</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein mediates adenovirus binding to microtubules</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2004</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>10122</fpage><lpage>10132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.78.18.10122-10132.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15331745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Samulski</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoplasmic trafficking, endosomal escape, and perinuclear accumulation of adeno-associated virus type 2 particles are facilitated by microtubule network</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2012</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>10462</fpage><lpage>10473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00935-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22811523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kardon</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulators of the cytoplasmic dynein motor</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>854</fpage><lpage>865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm2804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19935668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Holzbaur</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein and dynactin in cell division and intracellular transport</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0955-0674(99)80006-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10047518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal clear insights into how the dynein motor moves</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.120725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23525020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raaijmakers</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanenbaum</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Medema</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic dissection of dynein regulators in mitosis</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201208098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23589491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodoor</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroer</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattner</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein as a facilitator of nuclear envelope breakdown</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(01)00628-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11792324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaudouin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerlich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Daigle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Eils</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear envelope breakdown proceeds by microtubule-induced tearing of the lamina</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(01)00627-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11792323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shekhar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lele</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein: tension generation on microtubules and the nucleus</article-title><source>Cell Mol Bioeng</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>74</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12195-012-0257-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23646068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kutay</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hetzer</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reorganization of the nuclear envelope during open mitosis</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceb.2008.09.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18938243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siglin</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Poenie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lear</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynein and dynactin leverage their bivalent character to form a high-affinity interaction</article-title><source>PloS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e59453</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0059453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23577064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Holzbaur</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cytoplasmic dynein nomenclature</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200508078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16260502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schroer</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynactin</article-title><source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.20.012103.094623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15473859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Moreno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro-Lerida</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Roncal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Albar</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavilanes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recognition of novel viral sequences that associate with the dynein light chain LC8 identified through a pepscan technique</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>2003</year><volume>544</volume><fpage>262</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(03)00516-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12782328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hernaez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarrago</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Giralt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Escribano</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small peptide inhibitors disrupt a high-affinity interaction between cytoplasmic dynein and a viral cargo protein</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2010</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>10792</fpage><lpage>10801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01168-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20686048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radnai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapali</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Suveges</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Molnar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Affinity, avidity, and kinetics of target sequence binding to LC8 dynein light chain isoforms</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>38649</fpage><lpage>38657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.165894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20889982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelaz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Charron</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Fuente</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interfacing engineered nanoparticles with biological systems: anticipating adverse nano-bio interactions</article-title><source>Small</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1573</fpage><lpage>1584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/smll.201201229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23112130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Templeton</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wuelfing</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monolayer-protected cluster molecules</article-title><source>Acc Chem Res.</source><year>2000</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ar9602664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10639073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de la Fuente</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Riehle</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nanoparticle targeting at cells</article-title><source>Langmuir</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>3286</fpage><lpage>3293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/la053029v</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16548590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romberg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennink</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Storm</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sheddable coatings for long-circulating nanoparticles</article-title><source>Pharm Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11095-007-9348-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17551809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>del Pino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelaz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Kantner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Basic physicochemical properties of polyethylene glycol coated gold nanoparticles that determine their interaction with cells</article-title><source>Angew Chem Int Ed</source><year>2016</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>5483</fpage><lpage>5487</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201511733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelaz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>del Pino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Maffre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallego</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera-Fernandez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Surface functionalization of nanoparticles with polyethylene glycol: effects on protein adsorption and cellular uptake</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>6996</fpage><lpage>7008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.5b01326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26079146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raux</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Flamand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Blondel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of the rabies virus P protein with the LC8 dynein light chain</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2000</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>10212</fpage><lpage>10216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.74.21.10212-10216.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11024151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urnavicius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Diamant</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Motz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlager</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The structure of the dynactin complex and its interaction with dynein</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2015</year><volume>347</volume><fpage>1441</fpage><lpage>1446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaa4080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25814576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parassol</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bienvenu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Boglio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiorucci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerezo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X-M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vivo characterization of dynein-driven nanovectors using Drosophila oocytes</article-title><source>PLoS One.</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e82908</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0082908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24349395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Enoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Harashima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Particle tracking analysis for the intracellular trafficking of nanoparticles modified with African swine fever virus protein p54-derived peptide</article-title><source>Mol Ther</source><year>2013</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mt.2012.235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23164937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Granek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nucleus-Targeted Drug Delivery: Theoretical Optimization of Nanoparticles Decoration for Enhanced Intracellular Active Transport</article-title><source>Nano Lett.</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2515</fpage><lpage>2521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/nl500248q</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24646130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fytianos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chortarea</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Lorenzo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Blank</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>von Garnier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Petri-Fink</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aerosol delivery of functionalized gold nanoparticles target and activate dendritic cells in a 3D lung cellular model</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.6b06061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27973764</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sriwastawa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhati</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Drug delivery systems: an updated review</article-title><source>Int J Pharm Investig</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2230-973X.96920</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hait</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hambley</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeted cancer therapeutics</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>1263</fpage><lpage>1267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-08-3836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19208830</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Khaled</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploiting the enhanced permeability and retention effect for tumor targeting</article-title><source>Drug Discov Today</source><year>2006</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drudis.2006.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16935749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugahara</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Teesalu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Karmali</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotamraju</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Agemy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tissue-penetrating delivery of compounds and nanoparticles into tumors</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2009.10.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19962669</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>