<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_IJSCR4506 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Surg Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Surg Case Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Surgery Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2210-2612</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7229421</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2210-2612(20)30264-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijscr.2020.04.071</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Granulomatous reaction to migrating silicone oil clinically mimicking a xanthelasma: A case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0005"><name><surname>Alrashed</surname><given-names>Saleh Hamad</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0010"><name><surname>Alkatan</surname><given-names>Hind Manaa</given-names></name><email>hkatan@ksu.edu.sa</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0015"><name><surname>Alsuhaibani</surname><given-names>Adel H.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Department of Ophthalmology, College of Medicine, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</aff><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Department of Pathology, College of Medicine, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author at: College of Medicine, Departments of Ophthalmology &#x00026; Pathology, King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. <email>hkatan@ksu.edu.sa</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>5</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>70</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>3</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0005"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="lis0005"><list-item id="lsti0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0005">Distant silicone oil migration may occur following retina surgery.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0010">Silicone oil in periocular tissue results in granulomatous reaction.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0015">It may resemble a periocular xanthelasma-like skin lesion.</p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="par0020">Tissue diagnosis is essential for confirmation in such cases.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Silicone oil has been used for many years in retinal surgeries for retinal detachment. One of its reported complications is oil migration to the periorbital area, resulting in granulomatous reaction.</p></sec><sec><title>Presentation of case</title><p>A 56-year-old lady, with history of retinal detachment that was repaired by vitrectomy, silicone oil removal and epi-retinal membrane peeling, presented to us with unilateral ptosis and a skin lesion that resembled xanthelasma.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Histopathology of this lesion showed silicone oil infiltrating the surrounding connective tissue and fat with absence of foamy histiocytes.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We are reporting a case of silicone oil migration with pseudo-xanthelasma lesion. This has been reported only twice to the best of our knowledge in the English-written literature.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group id="kwd0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Silicone oil migration</kwd><kwd>Xanthelasma</kwd><kwd>Pseudo-xanthelasma</kwd><kwd>Case report</kwd><kwd>Granuloma</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="par0025">Silicone oil has been used for many years in retinal surgeries for retinal detachment. Silicone oil has its complications, and silicone oil migration has been reported several times in the literature [<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>]. This infiltration often results in extensive spread with intense inflammatory response. This inflammation may weaken the levator muscle, and cause ptosis [<xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. We report a case of silicone oil migration causing ptosis and xanthelasma-like picture. Other than our case to the best of our knowledge, his has been only reported twice in the English-written literature [<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><label>2</label><title>Presentation of case</title><p id="par0030">A 56-year-old lady, who is medically free presented to our hospital in December 2018 with the complaint of a drooping right upper eyelid, following a recent retina procedure elsewhere. She had undergone five retinal surgeries because of recurrent retinal detachment, but her last surgery involved epi-retinal membrane peeling, silicone oil removal, and peeling of the internal limiting membrane two months earlier.</p><p id="par0035">The patient&#x02019;s visual acuity (VA) of her right eye was hand motion, while it measured 20/40 in her left eye. The intraocular pressure (IOP) measured 21 and 20 mmHg in her right and left eye respectively. The extraocular motility (EOM) was normal on both sides. She had 2 mm of right upper eyelid ptosis, with a superficial scar along the skin of her right upper lid crease. Multiple slightly raised yellowish skin masses were noted on her upper eyelid, which we thought to be due to migrating silicone oil. xanthelasma-like lesion was also noted in the medial canthal region (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>a). Multiple pockets of silicone oil were also observed in the subconjunctival/sub-tenon area in all 4 quadrants of the conjunctival fornices (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b). She had a clear cornea, and deep/quite anterior chambers in both eyes. She was also observed to have a stable posterior chamber intraocular lens (IOL) in her right eye, and immature cataract in the left. The retina was flat in both eyes. She underwent surgical ptosis repair, combined with upper eyelid blepharoplasty, and excisional biopsy of the xanthelasma-like lesion from the upper lid in September 1, 2019.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>A:</bold> The clinical appearance of the right upper eyelid masses with a yellowish flat xanthelasma-like area near the medial canthus (Blue arrow). <bold>B:</bold> Subconjunctival collection of silicone oil in the right eye inferior fornix. <bold>C:</bold> The histopathological appearance of the skin in the same area showing the empty silicone oil round spaces surrounded by epithelioid cells and giant cells (Original magnification X200 Hematoxylin and eosin). <bold>D:</bold> Higher power of the silicone oil and the surrounding granulomatous reaction (Original magnification X400 Hematoxylin and eosin). (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="par0040">Histopathology of the excised skin showed marked fibrosis with several empty spaces representing pools of silicone oil. The silicone oil infiltrated the surrounding connective tissue and fat. In many areas, surrounding numerous epithelioid cells representing ill-defined granulomas was present in addition to other chronic inflammatory cells: lymphocytes and plasma cells (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>c &#x00026; d). However, there were no foamy histiocytes to support the diagnosis of xanthelasma even in the areas that were clinically identified as such.</p><p id="par0045">In the last follow-up of the patient in February 9, 2020, she had a good outcome and mild local scarring. Information was obtained and reported in a manner that was compliant with the standards set forth by the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act and the Declaration of Helsinki as amended in 2013. General informed written consent was obtained from the patient including anonymous use of information for presentations and contributions.</p></sec><sec id="sec0015"><label>3</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="par0050">Silicone oil has been used in retinal surgery for retinal detachment with the following possible complications: cataract, glaucoma, corneal edema and retinal toxicity. Silicone oil migration has been reported in the literature. Several theories have been proposed for silicone oil migration. The most agreed upon was silicone oil migration though the sclerotomy wound. Therefore, proper closure of the sclerotomy wound &#x02013; with careful removal of any excess leaking silicone oil &#x02013; has been strongly recommended. Migration of the silicone oil has been reported to migrate in several locations. Its migration into the subconjunctival space usually results in the presentation of a cystic or shiny subconjunctival swelling [<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Migration to the brain was also reported, with a variety of CNS-related symptoms such as: seizures, stroke, headache, and dizziness, while some being asymptomatic [<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. There were two previously reported cases -other than but identical to ours &#x02013; with silicone oil migration to the upper eyelid causing blepharoptosis and xanthelasma-like lesions [<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. One of these was a case of a 48-year-old female, who presented with the complaint of blepharoptosis and xanthelasma-like lesion of her left periocular area in 2011. She had history of retinal detachment with silicone oil being used as a tamponade three months before her presentation. Histopathology of these lesions was consistent with silicone oil [<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The second more recent paper in 2018 described a 68-year-old patient who presented with similar clinical features and history of retinal detachment procedure (with silicone oil) as well as Baerveldt implant two years prior to presentation <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Similarly, silicone migration into the periorbital tissue and orbit has been reported during evisceration in a patient with history of repeated retinal surgeries and also as chronic inflammation with silicone granuloma formation after the use of silicone implant in anophthalmic sockets [<xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p id="par0055">Our case has been prepared and reported in line with the updated SCARE guidelines in: "The SCARE 2018 statement: Updating consensus Surgical CAse REport (SCARE) guidelines." International Journal of Surgery 2018; 60:132&#x02013;136. The authors further stress that they have no financial disclosures related to their recommendations [<xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec0020"><label>4</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="par0060">Silicone oil migration is not an uncommon phenomenon. Vitreoretinal surgeons should be alerted and advocated about possible extra ocular silicone oil migration. It is recommended to make sure that all sclerotomies are tightly sealed especially after the use of silicone oil. Some even recommended giving antiglaucoma medication after theses surgeries. Oculoplastic surgeons on the other hand should be oriented with the possible presentation of silicone granuloma as a xanthelasma-like skin lesion in the periocular area due to its migration.</p></sec><sec id="sec0025"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="par0065">None.</p></sec><sec id="sec0030"><title>Source of funding</title><p id="par0070">None.</p></sec><sec id="sec0035"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="par0075">IRB is not required for case reports. However, information was obtained and reported in a manner that was compliant with the standards set forth by the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act, and the Declaration of Helsinki as amended in 2013.</p></sec><sec id="sec0040"><title>Consent</title><p id="par0080">General informed written consent was obtained from the patient including anonymous use of information for presentations and contributions.</p></sec><sec id="sec0045"><title>Author contribution</title><p id="par0085"><bold>Saleh Hamad Alrashed:</bold> Data collection, Data interpretation, Drafting the text.</p><p id="par0090"><bold>Hind Manaa Alkatan:</bold> Study design, Writing the paper.</p><p id="par0095"><bold>Adel H. Alsuhaibani:</bold> Supervision.</p></sec><sec id="sec0050"><title>Registration of research studies</title><p id="par0100">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="sec0055"><title>Guarantor</title><p id="par0105">Hind M. Alkatan.</p></sec><sec id="sec0060"><title>Provenance and peer review</title><p id="par0110">Not commissioned, externally peer-reviewed.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bibl0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bib0005"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deguchi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeno</surname><given-names>Takatoshi</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>Yuichi</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Migration of intraocular silicone oil from the vitreous cavity into the upper eyelid causing ptosis</article-title><source>Case Rep. Ophthalmol.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000365647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25202267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0010"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quintyn</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Genevois</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranty</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Retout</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicone oil migration in the eyelid after vitrectomy for retinal detachment</article-title><source>Am. J. Ophthalmol.</source><volume>136</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>540</fpage><lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12967812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0015"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boren</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cloy</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retrolaminar migration of intraocular silicone oil</article-title><source>J. Neuroophthalmol.</source><volume>36</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27636746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0020"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osaki</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osaki</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allemann</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osaki</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Silicone migration: an unusual eyelid complication following intraocular surgery</article-title><source>Aesthetic Surg. J.</source><volume>36</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/asj/sjv155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0025"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donker</surname><given-names>D.L.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paridaens</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooy</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Bosch</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blepharoptosis and upper eyelid swelling due to lipogranulomatous inflammation caused by silicone oil</article-title><source>Am. J. Ophthalmol.</source><volume>140</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>934</fpage><lpage>936</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16310482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0030"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>E.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orbital, eyelid, and nasopharyngeal silicone oil granuloma presenting as ptosis &#x00026; pseudo-xanthelasma</article-title><source>Am. J. Ophthalmol. Case Rep.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajoc.2018.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29978139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0035"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>K.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subconjunctival and orbital silicone oil granuloma (Siliconoma) complicating intravitreal silicone oil tamponade</article-title><source>Case Rep. Ophthalmol. Med.</source><volume>2014</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/686973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0040"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dehghani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavallali</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dastborhan</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Upper eyelid silicone oil migration after sutureless 23-Gauge vitrectomy</article-title><source>Adv. Biomed. Res.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>58</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2277-9175.206698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28584812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0045"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhende</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gopal</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subconjunctival cysts following silicone oil injection: a clinicopathological stud of five cases</article-title><source>Indian J. Ophthalmol.</source><volume>47</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10858773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0050"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorovoy</surname><given-names>I.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>360&#x000b0; subconjunctival silicone oil after unsutured 23-Gauge vitrectomy</article-title><source>Eye</source><volume>27</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>894</fpage><lpage>895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23598676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0055"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santaella</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carbon dioxide laser-induced combustion of extravasated intraocular silicone oil in the eyelid mimicking xanthelasma</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Plast. Reconstr. Surg.</source><volume>27</volume><year>2011</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/IOP.0b013e31820b0348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0060"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemaitre</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vahdani</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Escalas</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orbital leakage of intraocular silicone oil: case reports and literature review</article-title><source>Ophthalmic Plast. Reconstr. Surg.</source><issue>January (23)</issue><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/IOP.0000000000001588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0065"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galindo-Ferreiro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>AlGhafri</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elkhamary</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic inflammation in an anophthalmic socket due to a room temperature vulcanized silicone implant</article-title><source>Case Rep. Ophthalmol.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000445496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27462246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib0070"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agha</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borrelli</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farwana</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koshy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orgill</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>SCARE group</surname></name></person-group><article-title>The SCARE 2018 statement: updating consensus surgical CAse REport (SCARE) guidelines</article-title><source>Int. J. Surg.</source><volume>60</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijsu.2018.10.028</pub-id><comment>Epub 2018 Oct 18</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30342279</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>None.</p></ack></back></article>