<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?subarticle pmed.1003093.r001?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1549-1277</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">7108713</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PMEDICINE-D-19-03328</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care</subject><subj-group><subject>Socioeconomic Aspects of Health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Public and Occupational Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Socioeconomic Aspects of Health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental Health and Psychiatry</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Human Capital</subject><subj-group><subject>Economics of Migration</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and places</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographical locations</subject><subj-group><subject>Europe</subject><subj-group><subject>European Union</subject><subj-group><subject>Germany</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and Places</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographical Locations</subject><subj-group><subject>Asia</subject><subj-group><subject>Syria</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Public and Occupational Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Behavioral and Social Aspects of Health</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and Places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Age Groups</subject><subj-group><subject>Children</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and Places</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Groupings</subject><subj-group><subject>Families</subject><subj-group><subject>Children</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Care</subject><subj-group><subject>Health Statistics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pre-migration socioeconomic status and post-migration health satisfaction among Syrian refugees in Germany: A cross-sectional analysis</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Socioeconomic status and refugee health</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6331-4061</contrib-id><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>Jan Michael</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>Tilman</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Validation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zeeb</surname><given-names>Hajo</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Funding acquisition</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Resources</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Management, Society and Communication, Copenhagen Business School, Copenhagen, Denmark</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label>
<addr-line>Leibniz Institute for Prevention Research and Epidemiology&#x02014;BIPS, Bremen, Germany</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff003"><label>3</label>
<addr-line>Health Sciences Bremen, University of Bremen, Bremen, Germany</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Spiegel</surname><given-names>Paul B.</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>zeeb@leibniz-bips.de</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e1003093</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>2</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Bauer et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bauer et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pmed.1003093.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec001"><title>Background</title><p>The large increase in numbers of refugees and asylum seekers in Germany and most of Europe has put the issue of migration itself, the integration of migrants, and also their health at the top of the political agenda. However, the dynamics of refugee health are not yet well understood. From a life-course perspective, migration experience is associated with various risks and changes, which might differ depending on the socioeconomic status (SES) of refugees in their home country. The aim of this paper was to analyze the relationship between pre-migration SES and self-reported health indicators after migration among Syrian refugees. Specifically, we wanted to find out how their SES affects the change in health satisfaction from pre- to post-migration.</p></sec><sec id="sec002"><title>Methods and findings</title><p>We used data from the 2016 refugee survey, which was part of the German Socio-Economic Panel (GSOEP). Although cross-sectional by design, this survey collected information referring to the current situation as a refugee in Germany as well as to their situation before migration. Using a sample of 2,209 adult Syrian refugees who had entered Germany between 2013 and 2016, we conducted a cross-sectional and a quasi-longitudinal (retrospective) analysis. The mean &#x000b1; SD age was 35 &#x000b1; 11 years, with 64% of the participants being male. Our results showed a positive association between pre-migration self-reported SES and several subjective health indicators (e.g., health satisfaction, self-reported health, mental health) in the cross-sectional analysis. However, the quasi-longitudinal analysis revealed that the socioeconomic gradient in health satisfaction before migration was strongly attenuated after migration (SES-by-time interaction: &#x02212;0.48, 95% CI &#x02212;0.61 to &#x02212;0.35, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; unstandardized regression coefficients, 5-point SES scale and 11-point health outcome scale). Similar results were produced after controlling for sociodemographic characteristics, experiences during the migration passage, and the current situation in Germany. A sex-stratified analysis showed that while there was some improvement in health satisfaction among men from the lowest SES over time, no improvement was found among women. A limitation of this study is that it considers only the first months or years after migration. Thus, we cannot preclude that the socioeconomic gradient regains importance in the longer run.</p></sec><sec id="sec003"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our findings suggest that the pre-migration socioeconomic gradient in health satisfaction is strongly attenuated in the first years after migration among Syrian refugees. Hence, a high SES before crisis and migration provides limited protection against the adverse health effects of migration passage.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="toc"><p>Zeeb and colleagues report the changes in health satisfaction among Syrian refugees before and after migrating to Germany.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title>Author summary</title><sec id="sec004"><title>Why was this study done?</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Refugees are a vulnerable group because of the adversities and uncertainties they experience before, during, and after migration.</p></list-item><list-item><p>It is not clear how the social rank in society before their flight affects the health of refugees when they arrive in the host country.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Therefore, we analyzed the relationship between socioeconomic status before migration and (the change of) indicators of subjective health status among refugees.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>What did the researchers do and find?</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>We found that a higher socioeconomic status was associated with a slightly better subjective health status after migration.</p></list-item><list-item><p>However, we also found that the difference in health satisfaction between refugees of high and low socioeconomic status became much smaller after migration.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>What do these findings mean?</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Our findings provide new insight into the relationship between socioeconomic status and the health of refugees.</p></list-item><list-item><p>A high socioeconomic status does not necessarily protect refugees from the negative influences during migration and the first months or years in the new country</p></list-item></list></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="20"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>Data are collected by the German Institute for Economic Research (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.diw.de/en">https://www.diw.de/en</ext-link>). The authors are not legally permitted to share the data used for this study, but interested parties may contact the DIW representative Philipp Kaminsky to inquire about accessing this proprietary data (<email>soepmail@diw.de</email>). Further details about the data and access are provided here: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.diw.de/en/diw_01.c.592731.en/soep.iab_bamf_soep_mig.2016.html#592737">https://www.diw.de/en/diw_01.c.592731.en/soep.iab_bamf_soep_mig.2016.html#592737</ext-link>. The core file should allow and easy replication of our findings using the S1 Data Analyses and S2 Data Codebook files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>Data are collected by the German Institute for Economic Research (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.diw.de/en">https://www.diw.de/en</ext-link>). The authors are not legally permitted to share the data used for this study, but interested parties may contact the DIW representative Philipp Kaminsky to inquire about accessing this proprietary data (<email>soepmail@diw.de</email>). Further details about the data and access are provided here: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.diw.de/en/diw_01.c.592731.en/soep.iab_bamf_soep_mig.2016.html#592737">https://www.diw.de/en/diw_01.c.592731.en/soep.iab_bamf_soep_mig.2016.html#592737</ext-link>. The core file should allow and easy replication of our findings using the S1 Data Analyses and S2 Data Codebook files.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec007"><title>Introduction</title><p>According to the International Organisation for Migration, the estimated number of international migrants increased between 2000 and 2015 from 155 million to 244 million worldwide [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Since 2005, Germany hosts the second largest number of international migrants after the United States [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], and has recently witnessed a marked increase in the number of refugees and asylum seekers. While displaced persons such as refugees make up only a small proportion of all migrants [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], they deserve heightened attention because they are in a particularly vulnerable situation [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Among the migrants who recently arrived in Germany, refugees from Syria constitute the largest single group [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The large increase in numbers of refugees has put the issue of migration itself, the integration of migrants, and also their health at the top of the political agenda [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Migration can be viewed as a fundamental life-course transition that is often accompanied by a massive change in social and physical exposures. Therefore, Spallek and colleagues [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] suggest that exposures before, during, and after migration should be distinguished from each other. Before migration, exposures during critical or sensitive periods early in life, as well as driving factors of migration such as economic desperation, political oppression, war, or natural disasters play a role. During their journey, migrants, especially refugees, may be exposed to stark adversities when crossing deserts or the seas. They may become victims of trafficking, spend time in detention, or be exposed to physical or sexual violence. Shortly after arrival, access to better healthcare, sanitation, and nutrition may have a positive impact on migrants&#x02019; health, but their legal status, housing conditions, economic prospects, and the contexts of reception may also play a role. With regards to healthcare, it has to be noted that access for refugees in Germany is restricted to some basic level, in many cases excluding treatment of chronic conditions until the individual refugee status has been clarified [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Thus, while this level of access to healthcare may mean improvement for some refugees, others who might have been able to afford high-standard care in their country of origin may find themselves temporarily&#x02014;or in some cases for an extended period of time&#x02014;in a worse situation.</p><p>The positive relationship between socioeconomic status (SES) and health has been found across a broad range of indicators and in diverse populations [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Even though the mechanisms behind the SES&#x02013;health relationship are far from straightforward [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], one would expect that individuals with a higher SES before migration are better able to reduce or avoid risks during times of crisis and migration, which allows them to maintain a better health status for themselves and their families. These dynamics might have been amplified in the specific context of the crisis in Syria. Before the conflict, compared to other countries in the region, Syria could credit itself with having improved the living standards of its citizens over the last decades and providing them with an adequate healthcare system [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. This progress was pushed back substantially by the civil war and subsequent economic sanctions. Job loss and rising prices for food and medicine resulted in serious health consequences, particularly for vulnerable groups and the chronically ill (i.e., children, pregnant women, and the elderly). Through various pathways, such negative health effects can be long-term [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] or even considered irreversible, particularly for the most vulnerable [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. This prior evidence stipulates that a high precrisis SES of citizens might mitigate the health effects of a conflict, which could result in a widening of health disparities along the SES gradient even before the refugees have to leave their home countries.</p><p>However, status inconsistencies [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] or downward social mobility, which can occur due to migration, may affect refugees starting from a higher SES more strongly than those with a lower SES. For instance, the SES for those coming from very poor and deprived areas may improve or stay the same. On the other hand, others leave their country of origin where they had a high SES and may face great difficulties in trying to attain the same status in the host country. There is evidence that some migrants with high educational degrees only find low occupational positions because their qualifications are not recognized in the host country [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Shortly after their arrival, refugees from different SES may find themselves in the same position regarding their housing situation in large refugee accommodations and their legal status, which does not allow them to seek employment. In other words, pre-migration SES differences are diminished and leveled to an overall low position.</p><p>Our analysis focuses on the relationship between pre-migration SES and post-migration health, specifically on the question of whether pre-migration SES moderates the change in health status from pre- to post-migration. To this end, we rely on large-scale survey data from recently arrived refugees from Syria in Germany, which provide a rich set of health indicators from different time periods, including the pre-migration period. Such retrospective data provide the opportunity to gain new insights into the complex health dynamics linked to the migration process, which is the main motivation for this study. Refugees are a vulnerable group and studying the underlying dynamics of their health trajectories can improve our ability to identify and help those particularly at risk. Additionally, these data capture the disruption of life courses through the Syrian crises and provide a unique opportunity to gain novel insights into the relationship between SES and health that are interesting from a scientific perspective and expand our current understanding. In summary, this study investigates two competing hypotheses: (1) A higher pre-migration SES allows refugees to maintain a better health throughout the migration period and within the destination countries. Hence, the migration process increases health disparities along the SES distribution. Alternatively, (2) pre-migration differences in health status across SES might be reduced after migration due to the leveling of SES and possibly status inconsistencies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec008"><title>Methods</title><p>This study is a retrospective, quasi-longitudinal analysis of a refugee survey that covers information about living circumstances and health before and after migration. The survey is part of the German Socio-Economic Panel (GSOEP) administered by the German Institute for Economic Research (DIW). The GSOEP is one of the longest running representative panel studies in the world that is frequently supplemented by other data with specific focus on areas within Germany. All data are publicly available for scientific research use. The present study relies on a subsample of the GSOEP reflecting the population of adult refugees predominately entering Germany between 2013 and the end of January 2016 [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. As a response to the growing number of refugees in late 2015, the data were collected in collaboration with the Institute for Employment Research (IAB) and the Research Centre of the Federal Office for Migration and Refugees (BAMF-FZ). The dataset contains information about sociodemographics, health, attitudes, and living conditions in the migrants&#x02019; country of origin. The sampling was based on the German Central Register of Foreigners (Ausl&#x000e4;nderzentralregister) using a multistage clustered sampling design. Data were collected through face-to-face interviews in seven different languages. Individuals selected from the register represented so-called &#x0201c;anchor respondents&#x0201d; for their household and answered the survey for themselves as an individual and as a representative for the household. Furthermore, all household members above 18 years were interviewed, while information about children and adolescents was captured through proxy data provided by the adult household members. The response proportion was 48.6% [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. A detailed description of the survey methodology is available elsewhere [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The data can be accessed for scientific purposes upon registration on the DIW&#x02019;s website [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>The total refugee sample consists of 4,527 individuals from more than 20 countries. In this analysis, we exclusively focus on participants with a Syrian nationality, who make up nearly half of all refugees. The focusing on the Syrian sample helps reduce potential confounding by minimizing differences in the time line of the migration history and culture between refugee groups from different countries. We excluded 20 individuals who indicated that they entered Germany prior to 2013, leaving a core sample of 2,209 adults (18 years and older). Even though this dataset is cross sectional by design, the questionnaire collects information from different time periods. Questions referred to the current situation as a refugee in Germany (T1) or to the situation before the crisis in Syria (T0). For several constructs, the same questions were asked for both time periods.</p><sec id="sec009"><title>Health indicators</title><p>In our analysis we used five indicators for health and relied on health satisfaction as an indicator for subjective health status in our main outcome. Health satisfaction was measured with a single question for the current situation as well as retrospectively for the situation before &#x0201c;the crisis, the war or the conflict in [the] country of origin.&#x0201d; For the latter, the participants were asked, &#x0201c;How satisfied were you with your health at that time?&#x0201d; with the possible responses ranging from 0 &#x0201c;totally dissatisfied&#x0201d; to 10 &#x0201c;totally satisfied.&#x0201d; The question was mirrored with specific reference to the current situation, &#x0201c;How satisfied are you with your current health?&#x0201d; and had the same response scale. The survey also assessed general life satisfaction in a similar way, asking about life in general rather than health specifically. Additional health measures, which were only collected at T1, were the self-rated health state (five-point item from &#x0201c;poor&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;very well&#x0201d;) and a measure of worries about health (three-point scale from &#x0201c;No, I don&#x02019;t worry at all&#x0201d; to &#x0201c;Yes, I worry a lot&#x0201d;). Furthermore, mental health was measured with the 4-item Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-4), which has been shown to reliably and validly measure depression and anxiety in the general population [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The longer version (PHQ-9) has also been validated in diverse migrant populations [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. We inverted all scales where higher values corresponded to worse health outcomes.</p><p>We provide a correlational and graphical analysis of all constructs in the supporting information (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s001">S1 Table</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s010">S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s011">S2</xref> Figs). The construct validity of health satisfaction as our main dependent variable has been shown between different cohorts spanning over 60 years [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. As <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s001">S1 Table</xref> shows, health satisfaction was highly correlated with self-rated health (r = 0.82), which has been widely used as an indicator for health status in population-based studies and has proven to be a valid predictor of objective health measures such as mortality [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Health satisfaction was also correlated with the PHQ-4, showing that the measure of health satisfaction is related to symptoms of depression and anxiety.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>SES before migration</title><p>SES was assessed using a subjective measure of economic rank in the time before &#x0201c;the crisis, the war or the conflict.&#x0201d; The question used was, &#x0201c;How would you estimate your financial situation at that time with the income of other people in your country?&#x0201d; and had five response options, ranging from &#x0201c;well below average&#x0201d; (0) to &#x0201c;well above average&#x0201d; (4). Such subjective measures of SES go back to Adler and colleagues [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], have been validated in cross-country studies [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], and have also been used in a number of studies linking subjective SES to health outcomes [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Measures of subjective SES have been shown to predict health outcomes independent of objective characteristics such as income and education [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Despite some evidence to the contrary [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>], in a recent meta-analysis, an independent association between the most-used measures of subjective SES and physical health was observed [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The authors, however, also highlighted some methodological challenges. When SES and health outcomes are both self-reported, relationships might be inflated due to common method variance, correlated reporting bias, and confounding [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. However, while these methodological concerns are important, prior research supports the construct validity of subjective social status measures [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] and concludes that &#x0201c;subjective social status reflects the cognitive averaging of standard markers of socioeconomic situation and is free of psychological biases&#x0201d; [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Covariates</title><p>Sociodemographic covariates included age, sex, marital status, educational attainment (i.e., certificate obtained from the last school visited in the home country), and number of children. Last income and region of origin in Syria were included as variables referring to the context before migration. Furthermore, variables related to the migration process and the post-migration period were assessed. A count variable of negative incidences or events during the migration passage covering deception, shipwreck, getting mugged, physical and sexual violence, extortion, and spending time in detention was created. The duration of the migration passage in years as well as the duration of residence (year of arrival) in Germany were included. With reference to the post-migration period, we used current employment status and context of reception. The latter was assessed with a single question asking whether the respondents had felt welcome when they arrived in Germany. The question had five response options ranging from &#x0201c;not at all&#x0201d; (0) to &#x0201c;fully agree&#x0201d; (4). A summary of all variables is provided in <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pmed.1003093.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of Syrian refugees included in this study.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pmed.1003093.t001g" xlink:href="pmed.1003093.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Full sample</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Sex-stratified sample</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Individual measures</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sex</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">810 (36%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,399 (64%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age (years, mean)</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5 (10.6, 18&#x02013;75)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.8 (10.2, 18&#x02013;72)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.4 (10.9, 18&#x02013;75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Marital status</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Single</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">582 (26%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (12%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">487 (35%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Married</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1555 (71%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">665 (82%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">890 (64%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Divorced</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Widowed</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (1%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (&#x0003c;1%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of children</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 (2.2, 0&#x02013;19)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48 (2.1, 0&#x02013;13)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 (2.2, 0&#x02013;19)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Precrisis measures/Syria (T0)</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Educational attainment at T0</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Left with no qualifications</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">526 (24%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (23%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">331 (24%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Middle school</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">458 (20%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163 (21%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">295 (22%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Further practical-based</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">195 (9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139 (10%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Further general-based</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">635 (29%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242 (31%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">393 (29%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Other certificate</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (3%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (3%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Educational details N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">334 (13%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133 (14%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201 (13%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Income in T0</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;1st quartile</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">313 (14%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (11%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220 (16%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2nd quartile</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">310 (14%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241 (17%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;3rd quartile</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">320 (14%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (9%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251 (18%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;4th quartile</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297 (13%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (2%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277 (20%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Income N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">969 (42%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">559 (69%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410 (28%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health satisfaction at T0 (mean)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (2.2, 0&#x02013;10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 (2.1, 0&#x02013;10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4 (2.3, 0&#x02013;10)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Life satisfaction at T0 (mean)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6 (2.6, 0&#x02013;10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (2.5, 0&#x02013;10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (2.6, 0&#x02013;10)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subjective SES at T0 (mean)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (1.0, 0&#x02013;4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (.9, 0&#x02013;4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (1.0, 0&#x02013;4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Postcrisis measures/Germany (T1)</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health satisfaction at T1 (mean)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 (2.4, 0&#x02013;10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7 (2.5, 0&#x02013;10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1 (2.4, 0&#x02013;10)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Life satisfaction at T1 (mean)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3 (2.3, 0&#x02013;10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (2.0, 0&#x02013;10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1 (2.4, 0&#x02013;10)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003">*</xref> at T1 (mean)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0 (2.7, 0&#x02013;12)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.8 (2.6, 0&#x02013;10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1 (2.7, 0&#x02013;10)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Worries about health<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn003">*</xref> at T1 (mean)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (0.7, 0&#x02013;2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5 (0.7, 0&#x02013;2)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6 (0.7, 0&#x02013;2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-rated health at T1 (mean)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (1.1, 1&#x02013;5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (1.1, 1&#x02013;5)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0 (1.1, 1&#x02013;5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unemployed at T1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,011 (91%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">778 (96%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,233 (88%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Migration experience</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of negative experiences (mean)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (1.2, 0&#x02013;7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 (1.0, 0&#x02013;7)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 (1.2, 0&#x02013;7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Duration of migration</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;less than 1 year</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,156 (52%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">422 (52%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">734 (52%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;1 year</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">381 (17%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155 (19%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226 (16%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">268 (12%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (11%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181 (13%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;3 years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145 (7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;4 year or more</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 (5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (4%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Duration N/A</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138 (6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (6%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 (6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeling welcome</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (0.8, 0&#x02013;4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (0.8, 0&#x02013;4)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6 (0.8, 0&#x02013;4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Year of arrival</bold></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2013</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (7%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (4%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2014</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">532 (24%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199 (25%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">333 (24%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2015</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,447 (66%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">494 (61%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">953 (68%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;2016</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118 (5%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (8%)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (4%)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>Cell numbers are absolute frequencies (%) or means (standard deviation, range).</p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p>Mental health is the sum score of the four PHQ-4 items. Descriptive statistics are based on data for the specific cells (maximum <italic>n</italic> = 2,209). Variables with an asterisk</p></fn><fn id="t001fn003"><p>(*) were inverted so that higher numeric values correspond to better health in all measures.</p></fn><fn id="t001fn004"><p>Abbreviations: N/A, not available; PHQ-4, 4-item Patient Health Questionnaire; SES, socioeconomic status.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Analysis</title><p>As has already been stated, the main interest of this study is to identify the effect of refugee SES in their home country, Syria (T0), on their current health status in Germany (T1). In a first step, we estimate the effect of subjective SES on health (measured by various indicators). Using multivariate regression allows for the adjustment of covariates, such as sociodemographic information, migration experience, and current situation. The following equation describes the model:
<disp-formula id="pmed.1003093.e001"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pmed.1003093.e001.jpg" id="pmed.1003093.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>
The health of individual <italic>i</italic> in time 1 (i.e., 2016 in Germany) is measured by five different indicators: health satisfaction, self-rated health, mental health, health worries, and life satisfaction. <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub>1</sub> is the coefficient of interest, subjective SES in precrisis Syria, while the vector <italic>X</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> captures a set of covariates that refer to the individual or both time periods. The intercept is indicated by <italic>a</italic> and <inline-formula id="pmed.1003093.e002"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pmed.1003093.e002.jpg" id="pmed.1003093.e002g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> captures the error term.</p><p>Our second analytical step exploits the fact that our questionnaire measures the main outcome variable (i.e., health satisfaction) for both time periods (T0 and T1). This data structure allows for the construction of a quasi-longitudinal dataset based on participants&#x02019; self-assessed health satisfaction at different time points. This approach provides a suitable way to address the problem of starting from a higher baseline value, which might obscure any decline when simply comparing health satisfaction according to SES at T1. Our modeling is built on a two-period panel dataset and uses a difference-in-difference approach to control for differences in health satisfaction at T0. For our main results, we analyze the change in health satisfaction between T0 and T1 by using SES as a continuous &#x0201c;treatment&#x0201d; variable that moderates potential differences between both periods. A nonparametric specification of SES is also presented to validate the assumption of this linear relationship. The estimation approach is explained through the following regression equation:
<disp-formula id="pmed.1003093.e003"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pmed.1003093.e003.jpg" id="pmed.1003093.e003g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(2)</label></disp-formula>
We estimate the health satisfaction (health) of individual <italic>i</italic> at time <italic>t</italic>. Time <italic>t</italic> is a dummy variable indicating 0 for T0 and 1 for T1. Self-reported socioeconomic status at T0 is used as an indicator for SES. Hence, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic><sub>3</sub> captures an interaction term between SES and the change in health between the two time periods, while controlling for baseline differences and the change in health experienced by all refugees. Similar to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pmed.1003093.e001">Eq 1</xref>, <italic>X</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> captures a set of covariates, <italic>a</italic> is the intercept, and <inline-formula id="pmed.1003093.e004"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pmed.1003093.e004.jpg" id="pmed.1003093.e004g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b5;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the error term, which we cluster on the individual level. Throughout the analysis, we used pairwise deletion of cases with missing data, with the exception that we created &#x0201c;missing&#x0201d; categories for categorical variables with high shares of missing data (e.g., income) and included them in the analysis in order to retain a sufficient sample size. Due to the pairwise deletion, the numbers of observations between the statistical models vary. Even though our main outcome measures of health are mostly ordered variables, we rely on ordinary least squares (OLS) as this method has been shown to yield minor differences only, compared to specific ordered response models, and also eases interpretation [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Results from an ordered-logit model provide comparable results and are provided in the supporting information (see specific results for reference). We also present the results of an individual fixed-effects model for robustness. This model aims to capture time-invariant unobserved individual heterogeneity in our quasi-longitudinal analysis. Additional analyses to assess the consistency of the findings include separate analyses for men and women as well as repeated analysis with an alternative outcome variable (life satisfaction).</p><p>No prospective analytical protocol was created. The main research question about the importance of social economic status for Syrian refugee health was formulated prior to data inspection and originated from the theories discussed in the introduction. The authors quickly settled on the initial difference-in-difference approach using retrospective survey information and later supplemented the core results by further robustness and subgroup analyses based on collegial feedback (e.g., generic cross-sectional analyses) and reviewer comments (e.g., refined analyses of ceiling effects). These data provide robustness checks to highlight the link between our main outcome and more objective health measures, as well as the problem of potential ceiling effects.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec013"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec014"><title>Descriptive statistics</title><p>We present the descriptive statistics of our main estimation sample in <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The sample consists of 64% men, and the average age of participants was 35 years. While the study covers a broad age range (18&#x02013;75 years), only a small proportion of the sample (10%) is older than 50 years. Furthermore, (unaccompanied) minors are not included. The participating Syrian refugees are predominately married (&#x0003e;70%) and have two children on average. Looking at different health indicators, on average the respondents report their self-rated health as &#x0201c;good,&#x0201d; even though health satisfaction between T0 and T1 declined by 0.5 points on an 11-point scale. A similar development can be observed for life satisfaction. The participants report mild levels of mental health issues. Upon arrival, which happened mostly in the years 2014 and 2015, around 90% of refugees felt &#x0201c;totally&#x0201d; or at least &#x0201c;mostly&#x0201d; welcomed. Only minor differences can be observed between women and men. On average, women are more likely to be married and report lower income. They are also less likely to report information on income at T0. Furthermore, women mostly score lower on health indicators but report higher levels of life satisfaction. A comparison of the descriptive statistics by SES is provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s002">S2 Table</xref>, showing that objective SES measures (i.e., education and income) generally follow the subjective self-reports.</p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Cross-sectional analysis</title><p>Following our analytical strategy, <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents the results of our cross-sectional regressions, measuring the effect of subjective SES in Syria on various health indicators measured after the migration experience in Germany. In <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, we add variables from Panels A to D that could mitigate the relationship of interest in chronological order, starting with characteristics set before the refugees&#x02019; migration experience, followed by assessments of the migration period itself and variables capturing their experience in Germany. In Panel A, where we only control for age and sex, all outcome variables point towards a positive relationship between higher SES and health. This relationship is statistically significant for health satisfaction, self-rated health, and (the absence of) health worries. For these three indicators, the findings remain robust after adding different sets of covariates, including sociodemographic information, migration experience, and variables measuring the experience in Germany (see Panels B&#x02013;D). Adding objective measures of SES such as education and income reduces the point estimates for health satisfaction and self-rated health but does not fully explain the self-reported SES&#x02013;health relationship.</p><table-wrap id="pmed.1003093.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Cross-sectional analysis of the association between self-reported SES before migration (T0) and self-assessed health indicators (OLS regression analysis).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pmed.1003093.t002g" xlink:href="pmed.1003093.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SES measure, descriptors</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health Satisfaction</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-rated Health</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental<break/>Health</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health Worries</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Life Satisfaction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic>Panel A: Covariates: sex and age</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SES at T0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.06&#x02013;0.29]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.02&#x02013;0.12]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.04 to 0.23]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.03&#x02013;0.09]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.05 to 0.16]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,152</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,152</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,010</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,141</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,140</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adjusted <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic>Panel B: Covariates: sociodemographics</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SES at T0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.04&#x02013;0.29]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.01&#x02013;0.12]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.03 to 0.26]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.03&#x02013;0.09]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.02 to 0.21]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,082</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,082</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,945</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,071</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,070</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adjusted <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic>Panel C: Covariates: sociodemographics + migration experience</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SES at T0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.05&#x02013;0.29]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.01&#x02013;0.12]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.01 to 0.28]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.03&#x02013;0.09]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.02 to 0.21]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,082</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,082</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,945</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,071</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,070</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adjusted <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic>Panel D: Covariates: sociodemographics + migration experience + experience in Germany</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SES at T0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn003">**</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn002">*</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t002fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.04&#x02013;0.29]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.01&#x02013;0.12]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.01 to 0.28]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.03&#x02013;0.10]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.03 to 0.20]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,065</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,065</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,936</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,058</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,057</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adjusted <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>Coefficients are unstandardized regression coefficients. Covariates included in Panel A: sex, age, and age<sup>2</sup>. Added in Panel B: marital status, income at T0, educational certificate in T0, number of children, and Syrian birth region dummies. Panel C: negative migration experience and duration of migration. Panel D: employment status at T1, feeling of welcome, and year of arrival. <italic>N</italic> = number of individuals. CIs (95%) based on heteroskedastic robust standard errors in brackets.</p></fn><fn id="t002fn002"><p>*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.1,</p></fn><fn id="t002fn003"><p>**<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05,</p></fn><fn id="t002fn004"><p>***<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></fn><fn id="t002fn005"><p>Abbreviations: OLS, ordinary least squares; SES, socioeconomic status.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Mental health and life satisfaction do not show a significant relationship with SES in the most parsimonious model (Panel A). However, after adding sociodemographic variables and indicators for migration experience, both coefficients increase and become marginally significant. This runs against the expectation that higher SES is generally associated with a less troublesome migration experience. When looking more closely into the data, we find that individuals with higher SES are more likely to report experiencing financial exploitation and fraud during migration, which has negative effects on mental health, in particular (lower values on the inverted mental health score), and thereby attenuates the positive relationship between mental health measures at T1 and SES at T0 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s003">S3 Table</xref>).</p><p>Overall, the results shown in <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> support the notion that high precrisis SES is associated with some positive health outcomes among Syrian refugees in Germany. Results using an ordered-logit model support these findings and generally provide more precise estimates, rendering the positive relationship between SES and mental health as well as SES and life satisfaction statistically significant (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s004">S4 Table</xref>). However, as this first analytical step only assesses the residual relationship after migration, the next analysis puts focus on the actual change in health outcomes by accounting for retrospective (i.e., T0) measures.</p></sec><sec id="sec016"><title>Quasi-longitudinal analysis</title><p>The results of our analysis of health changes, where we focus exclusively on the measure of health satisfaction available in both periods, are presented in <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The estimates of the most parsimonious model (column 1) indicate that higher SES is associated with better health satisfaction at T0. Our model predicts a 0.6-point increase in health satisfaction for each step increase in SES, which translates into an approximately 3-point difference on an 11-point scale between the lowest and highest SES at T0. Given that we modelled the relationship between SES and both periods as an interaction term, the T1 dummy can be interpreted as the change from T0 to T1 for individuals in the lowest SES category (ranging from 0 to 4). Hence, refugees living &#x0201c;well below the average&#x0201d; SES report better health in their current situation compared to their lives in Syria. The negative interaction term, however, reveals that the increase in health satisfaction is exclusively experienced by individuals at the lower end of the SES ladder. A nonsignificant change in health is already shown for those in the second lowest category, and our models predict that individuals with an &#x0201c;average&#x0201d; SES or above will be worse off compared to the pre-migration measurements.</p><table-wrap id="pmed.1003093.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Retrospective analysis of change in health satisfaction before (T0) and after migration (T1) by self-reported SES (OLS regression analysis).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pmed.1003093.t003g" xlink:href="pmed.1003093.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Independent variables</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLS</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLS</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLS</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OLS</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SES at T0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.53&#x02013;0.75]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.51&#x02013;0.74]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.52&#x02013;0.74]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.50&#x02013;0.73]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.17&#x02013;0.82]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.19&#x02013;0.86]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.19&#x02013;0.86]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.18&#x02013;0.85]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.16&#x02013;0.82]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SES &#x000d7; T1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.48<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn004">***</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.61 to &#x02212;0.35]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.62 to &#x02212;0.36]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.62 to &#x02212;0.36]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.62 to &#x02212;0.35]</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[&#x02212;0.60 to &#x02212;0.34]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sociodemographics</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Migration experience</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experience in Germany</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Number of observations</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,302</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,162</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,162</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,128</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,304</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">adjusted <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p>Coefficients are unstandardized regression coefficients. Dependent variable for all regression is health satisfaction. Results in columns 1&#x02013;4 are based on OLS. Covariates included in all regressions: sex, age, and age<sup>2</sup>. Sociodemographics: marital status, income at T0, educational attainment at T0, number of children, and Syrian birth region dummies. Migration experience: negative migration experience and duration of migration. Experience in Germany: employment status at T1, feeling of welcome, and year of arrival. Column 5 based on within-estimator accounting for individual FE. CIs (95%) based on heteroskedastic robust standard errors clustered on the individuum in brackets.</p></fn><fn id="t003fn002"><p>*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.1,</p></fn><fn id="t003fn003"><p>**<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05,</p></fn><fn id="t003fn004"><p>***<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01. A replication of this table with detailed covariates is provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s005">S5 Table</xref> and using an ordered-logit model is displayed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s006">S6 Table</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="t003fn005"><p>Abbreviations: FE, fixed effect; OLS, ordinary least squares; SES, socioeconomic status.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>This relationship is best understood when looking at <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003093.g001">Fig 1</xref>, in which we replicated the findings from the regression analysis shown in column 4 of <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, but modeled SES as a categorical rather than as a continuous variable. This nonparametric modeling approach graphically confirms that treating SES as linear is an appropriate functional form. We can also see that at T1, health satisfaction is less steep along the gradient of SES, with only minor differences being observed between the SES extremes.</p><fig id="pmed.1003093.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Health satisfaction before (T0) and after migration (T1) in relation to self-reported SES before migration.</title><p>Predictions derived from a linear model similar to column 4 of <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> but modelling SES as a categorical variable. Error bars indicate 95% CIs based on heteroskedastic robust standard errors clustered on the individuum. SES, socioeconomic status.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pmed.1003093.g001"/></fig><p>The other columns in <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> also show that our findings are robust when adding more control variables that could confound the observed pattern. Self-reported SES is correlated with other sociodemographic characteristics, such as objective SES measures (i.e., education and income) and family composition that we add in column 2. Additionally, we add a set of dummy variables to control for 14 different regions in Syria. With column 3, we enrich our model with information about the migration experience itself, which might also be correlated with SES and our health measure. As in column 2, the point estimates only change marginally. We add variables that describe the experience in Germany in column 4. This includes the current employment status and the experience of feeling welcome upon arrival. The latter shows a weakly significant positive relationship with health satisfaction. The overall SES&#x02013;health relationship, however, remains unchanged.</p><p>Column 5 reports the results from a model using individual fixed effects (FE). Given that all our covariates are time invariant and we have no specific temporal reference point for T0 (i.e., we cannot calculate age differences), the FE model is completely unconditional. Accounting for unobserved heterogeneity does not significantly change our estimates and underlines the robustness of our main findings.</p></sec><sec id="sec017"><title>Heterogeneity</title><p>The results presented in <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> are very robust between different model specifications and the addition of covariates. However, analyzing the data separately for men and women reveals some noteworthy differences. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003093.g002">Fig 2</xref> is a graphical representation of the model displayed in column 4 of <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> for the male sample only, while <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003093.g003">Fig 3</xref> reflects results for women (regression results provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s007">S7 Table</xref>). Even though the interaction term is similar in magnitude and statistically significant for both subgroups, the graphs differ remarkably. For men, we can see that satisfaction with health increases for refugees below the average SES, while those in the higher SES strata report lower health when compared to their time in Syria. For women, however, the levels of reported health satisfaction post-migration are not higher than at T0 for all SES strata. Women from the lowest SES strata show equal levels of health satisfaction, with increasing negative differences being observed for those with higher SES positions. For both men and women, the link between SES and health becomes substantially weaker compared to pre-migration measures.</p><fig id="pmed.1003093.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Health satisfaction before (T0) and after migration (T1) in relation to self-reported SES before migration among men.</title><p>Predictions derived from a linear model for men are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s007">S7 Table</xref>. Error bars indicate 95% CIs based on heteroskedastic robust standard errors clustered on the individuum. SES, socioeconomic status.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pmed.1003093.g002"/></fig><fig id="pmed.1003093.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Health satisfaction before (T0) and after migration (T1) in relation to self-reported SES before migration among women.</title><p>Predictions are derived from a linear model for women presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s007">S7 Table</xref>. Error bars indicate 95% CIs based on heteroskedastic robust standard errors clustered on the individuum. SES, socioeconomic status.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pmed.1003093.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>Life satisfaction</title><p>As the measure of life satisfaction is also available for both periods, we apply the same analytical approach used for health satisfaction for this more holistic well-being outcome measure (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s008">S8 Table</xref>). The pattern of life satisfaction is similar but shows more pronounced effects compared to the health domain. The interaction effect for SES is strongly negative and life satisfaction decreases by 1 point on an 11-point scale (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003093.g004">Fig 4</xref>). These stronger results might be linked to the fact that general life satisfaction directly encapsulates more life domains such as family, career, or wealth that were severely affected by the conflict and lost through migration. Such factors might affect health only indirectly, resulting in smaller changes in our main outcome, which is measured on the same 11-point scale. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003093.g004">Fig 4</xref> displays these results in a nonparametric way and is based on the same regression as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003093.g001">Fig 1</xref>, just using a different outcome variable.</p><fig id="pmed.1003093.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Life satisfaction before (T0) and after migration (T1) in relation to self-reported SES before migration.</title><p>Predictions derived from a linear model similar to column 4 of <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s008">S8 Table</xref> but modelling SES as a categorical variable. Error bars indicate 95% CIs based on heteroskedastic robust standard errors clustered on the individuum. SES, socioeconomic status.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pmed.1003093.g004"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec019"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study aimed to assess the effects of pre-migration and precrisis SES on health after migration in a sample of migrants from Syria who recently arrived in Germany. Adopting a life-course approach, the results of our study provide novel insights into the temporal relationship between SES and the health of refugees. Based on previous literature, we identified different pathways that could affect the health of refugees and therefore stipulated two competing hypotheses that might predict changes of health differences along the SES gradient.</p><p>Our main finding is that while pre-migration high SES in Syria has some remaining health benefits, differences in health satisfaction across SES while in Syria were reduced after migration. Health satisfaction improved among those with the lowest economic rank but became worse among those with an average or higher economic rank. This pattern remained robust after controlling for differences in migration experience and other potential confounders. Health satisfaction was highly correlated with self-rated health, which has proven to be a valid predictor of objective health measures. In addition, when using life satisfaction as an outcome variable, a similar pattern occurred. Furthermore, separated analyses for men and women revealed that health improvements were limited to those with the lowest health satisfaction before migration, i.e., men with the lowest SES. This is partly in line with mental health dynamics observed in migrant workers, where women showed a higher increase than men [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Sex heterogeneity has also been observed among refugees in Norway, where male refugees showed a higher likelihood to purchase antidepressants than non-refugee men, while differences among women were more pronounced for psychotropic medicine [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].</p><p>Other research has indicated that pre-migration SES may be positively related to post-migration health status. For example, a study among human trafficking returnees in Ethiopia reported that trafficked persons from families with a higher SES were less likely to display symptoms of posttraumatic stress disorders, indicating that financial resources of families were to some extent protective against the strict control of traffickers [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. In contrast, our results show that refugees with a high SES from Syria are hardly able to maintain their better health status after arrival in Germany. This provides evidence against the fundamental cause hypothesis stating that individuals with a higher SES are always better able to protect their health [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Our data suggest that individuals with a higher SES experience different hardships during migration compared to people from lower SES and suffer more from extortion and fraud. This is, however, not the major driving factor for the observed dynamic as the time-by-SES interaction terms remain almost the same after controlling for migration experience. Another explanation could be that healthcare provision was unevenly distributed in precrisis Syria, offering high-quality (private) care in rich urban areas but only basic care in poor rural areas [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. After arrival in Germany, Syrian refugees were exposed to the same restrictions in access to healthcare, regardless of their former SES. While this may have resulted in a loss in quality of care for those from higher SES, it could have meant an improvement in access to healthcare for those from the lowest SES. However, although access to healthcare may play a role, we do not believe that this can fully explain the leveling of the association between pre-migration SES and health satisfaction, because our study sample mainly consisted of middle-aged adults who may not require a lot of healthcare.</p><p>Apart from access to healthcare, one could argue that exposure to the same material living conditions in terms of housing and sanitation influences the leveling of the health gradient. Nevertheless, one could have expected that individuals from a formerly higher SES would be in a position to use their resources to improve their situation. Since this is not evident from our results, we would suggest that status inconsistency contributes to the explanation of our findings. Coming from a high SES in Syria may shape the expectations regarding living circumstances and position in society after migration. Finding themselves in refugee accommodations with limited access to the labor market, low levels of privacy, and unclear prospects about their residence permit may be experienced as a downward social mobility. According to the status inconsistency theory, this could result in increased levels of mental health and physical symptoms, such as elevated blood pressure [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Although we cannot provide direct evidence within this study about which mechanism explains the reduction in health differential across pre-migration social status, we argue that both material and psychosocial factors play a role.</p><p>Looking into the different health indicators, we observe that refugees show little to no differences in the mental health indicator post-migration along the SES gradient, while SES retained some predictive power for more holistic indicators. This observation suggests that leveling within the psychological domain of health is particularly pronounced. Similar effects were found among Tongans migrating for work to New Zealand. Evidence from a natural experiment suggests that migration produces mental health benefits that are particularly pronounced in those with low mental health [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Although this type of migration substantially differs from the situation of Syrian refugees, these dynamics might alleviate SES differences. Rasmussen and colleagues [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] compared differences in mental health dynamics between refugees and a sample of voluntary migrants. While refugees initially come with a higher burden of psychiatric issues, the development of post-migration mental health issues was found to be similar in both groups over time.</p><p>The strong differences regarding life satisfaction with a change by one point of the 11-point scale for each point of the 5-point SES question emphasizes the importance of SES when studying well-being dynamics of migrants. The explicit consideration of SES might be helpful to explain the unclear results observed by prior studies such as the one conducted by Stillman and colleagues [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>].</p><sec id="sec020"><title>Limitations</title><p>Despite the robust findings of this study, there are some limitations that need to be discussed. First, there is only a small proportion of older adults in our sample and (unaccompanied) minors&#x02014;a group that is perceived as particularly vulnerable&#x02014;were not included [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Therefore, the results of this study cannot be generalized to these groups.</p><p>Second, the quasi-longitudinal data are based on self-reported health measures at two time periods. As health satisfaction is measured on an 11-point scale, we have to consider potential ceiling effects. We can observe that 74% of individuals with the highest SES report the highest health satisfaction at T0. The share in the lowest SES level is only 34%. For these individuals, the measure does not allow the reporting of further increases in health satisfaction, which could introduce asymmetric bias of the change in the mean towards T1. This limitation is, however, unlikely to drive our results as we conduct several checks displayed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1003093.s009">S9 Table</xref>: (1) The results remain robust for a subsample excluding all observations reporting the highest and lowest level of health satisfaction at T0. (2) After following a suggestion from the literature using a Tobit model to account for potential ceiling and floor effects [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>], our main results remain robust for different specifications of the outcome variable.</p><p>Third, the retrospective assessment of precrisis health and SES does not refer to one specific point in time. Given a large set of controls, we have no indication that individual reference points might systematically differ along the levels of SES, which might introduce bias. According to validation work on survey questions about subjective welfare, reference points between the rich and the poor are not likely to differ [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].</p><p>The previous point also touches upon the final limitation regarding the issue of causality. In our analysis, we treat SES as exogenous and assess its influence on health trajectories. Previous research, however, suggests that SES can be affected by changes in health [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. As the core of this analysis is the change in health through migration and crisis, we are interested in the changes caused by this experience, rather than the question of whether precrisis health caused higher SES in Syrians. A potential issue might arise if temporary periods of good health would induce a rise in SES, which could then level over time following a regression to the mean. However, given the strong and persistent evidence of the relationship between SES and health, we do not think that this dynamic is a main driver of our results.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec021"><title>Conclusion and future research</title><p>The aim of this study was to assess the importance of SES in Syrians before becoming a refugee in Germany. Our results based on a uniquely rich refugee dataset are in line with the concept of status inconsistency, as we only observe a decline in health satisfaction for individuals from a relatively high economic rank. Hence, high SES in the precrisis provides limited protection against the adverse health effects of migration and is associated with a stronger decline in health.</p><p>These novel findings bear several practical and research-relevant implications. People from different SES face unique challenges and threats to their well-being and mental health. While people from poorer parts of the Syrian society seem to be less affected by migration and might even benefit from the current conditions as a refugee in Germany, the same conditions appear to be detrimental for individuals previously living in higher classes of the Syrian society. Overall, our data indicate a strong leveling of health indicators and life satisfaction through the cascade of events caused by the conflict in Syria.</p><p>Our results are based on data covering mostly a period of 1 to 2 years after migration. Future research should build on the next waves of this dataset to study the influence of pre-migration SES on health in the longer run, i.e., when most of the refugees enter the labor market or when the cumulative exposures translate into chronic diseases. The ensuing results might allow for additional insights into the set-point theory [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and the ability to adapt to novel situations under such extreme conditions [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>], which has been shown to be sensitive to the cultural context [<xref rid="pmed.1003093.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Future research could supplement our findings by focusing on the identification of further causal pathways underlying the observed dynamic between SES and health. Such deeper insights might guide policy makers in their search for better regulations for refugees.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec022"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s001"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Correlation between health indicators.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s001.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s002"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title>Descriptive statistics by SES.</title><p>SES, socioeconomic status.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s003"><label>S3 Table</label><caption><title>Mental health, SES, and migration experience.</title><p>SES, socioeconomic status.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s003.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s004"><label>S4 Table</label><caption><title>Replication of <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> using an ordered logit model.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s004.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s005"><label>S5 Table</label><caption><title>Replication of <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> presenting detailed results on covariates.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s005.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s006"><label>S6 Table</label><caption><title>Replication of <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> using an ordered logit model.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s006.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s007"><label>S7 Table</label><caption><title>Regression underlying Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003093.g003">3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed.1003093.g004">4</xref>.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s007.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s008"><label>S8 Table</label><caption><title>Life satisfaction similar to <xref rid="pmed.1003093.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s008.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s009"><label>S9 Table</label><caption><title>Tests for the importance of ceiling effects.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s009.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s010"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>Relationship between health satisfaction and other indicators.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s010.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s011"><label>S2 Fig</label><caption><title>Relationship between health worries and health satisfaction.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s011.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s012"><label>S1 STROBE Checklist</label><caption><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s012.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s013"><label>S1 Data</label><caption><title>Analyses.</title><p>(DO)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s013.do"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s014"><label>S2 Data</label><caption><title>Codebook.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s014.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank the following groups and individuals for their valuable comments on this manuscript, in no particular order: all participants of the CBS CBIG brown bag seminar on 22 May 2019; Alfonso Sousa-Poza, Florence Samkange-Zeeb, and Irwa Issa, particularly for his invaluable comments concerning the situation in Syria.</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>BAMF-FZ</term><def><p>Research Centre of the Federal Office for Migration and Refugees</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DIW</term><def><p>German Institute for Economic Research</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FE</term><def><p>fixed effect</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GSOEP</term><def><p>German Socio-Economic Panel</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IAB</term><def><p>Institute for Employment Research</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OLS</term><def><p>ordinary least squares</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PHQ-4</term><def><p>4-item Patient Health Questionnaire</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SES</term><def><p>socioeconomic status</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IOM. World Migration Report 2018 | International Organization for Migration. 2018 [cited 2020 Feb 24]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iom.int/wmr/world-migration-report-2018">http://www.iom.int/wmr/world-migration-report-2018</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United Nations, Department of Economic and Social Affairs, Population Division. International Migration Report 2017: Highlights. 2017 [cited 2020 Feb 24]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.un.org/development/desa/publications/international-migration-report-2017.html">https://www.un.org/development/desa/publications/international-migration-report-2017.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lindert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ehrenstein</surname><given-names>OS vo.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Priebe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mielck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Br&#x000e4;hler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Depression and anxiety in labor migrants and refugees&#x02014;A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>69</volume>: <fpage>246</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>257</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2009.04.032</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19539414?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19539414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brady H, Humphris R, Newall D, Phillimore J. Public health aspects of migrant health: a review of the evidence on health status for refugees and asylum seekers in the European Region. Copenhagen WHO Reg Off Eur (Health Evid Netw synth report 44). 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aloudat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bartolomei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carballo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durieux-Paillard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gabus</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Migrant and refugee populations: A public health and policy perspective on a continuing global crisis</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13756-017-0291-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29312658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">OECD. 2019 International Migration and Displacement Trends and Policies Report to the G20. 2019; 35 [cited 2020 Feb 24]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oecd.org/migration/mig/G20-migration-and-displacement-trends-and-policies-report-2019.pdf">http://www.oecd.org/migration/mig/G20-migration-and-displacement-trends-and-policies-report-2019.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>WHO</collab>. <article-title>Promoting the health of refugees and migrants (Resolution 70.15)</article-title>. <source>Seventieth World Heal Assem</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Commission</surname><given-names>EU</given-names></name>. <source>Communication from the Commission to the European Parliament, the European Council and the Council: Progress report on the implementation of the European Agenda on Migration</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>1689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1699</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Spallek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeeb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Razum</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>. <article-title>What do we have to know from migrants&#x02019; past exposures to understand their health status? A life course approach</article-title>. <source>Emerg Themes Epidemiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-7622-8-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21223568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Razum</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wenner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bozorgmehr</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>[When Chance Decides About Access to Health Care: The Case of Refugees in Germany]. Wenn Zufall &#x000fc;ber den Zugang zur Gesundheitsversorgung bestimmt: Gefl&#x000fc;chtete in Deutschland</article-title>. <source>Gesundheitswesen</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>78</volume>: <fpage>711</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>714</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0042-116231</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 27756088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27756088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pr&#x000e4;g</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wittek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Subjective socioeconomic status and health in cross-national comparison</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>149</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2015.11.044</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 26708244?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26708244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lleras-Muney</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Socioeconomic Status and Health: Dimensions and Mechanisms</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Glied</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> and <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, editors. <source>The Oxford Handbook of Health Economics</source>. <year>2012</year> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199238828.013.0007</pub-id>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al-Faisal</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alsaleh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Syria: Effects of conflict and sanctions on public health</article-title>. <source>J Public Heal (United Kingdom)</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ghobarah</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Russett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>The post-war public health effects of civil conflict</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>869</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>884</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2003.11.043</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15177842?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15177842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Justino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Br&#x000fc;ck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verwimp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Micro-Level Dynamics of Conflict, Violence, and Development: A New Analytical Framework</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Justino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Br&#x000fc;ck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verwimp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, editors. <source>A Micro-Level Perspective on the Dynamics of Conflict, Violence and Development</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>; <year>2013</year> pp. <fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bundervoet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Verwimp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akresh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Health and Civil War in Rural Burundi</article-title>. <source>J Hum Resour</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>536</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>563</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kristenson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Starrin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Status incongruence revisited: Associations with shame and mental wellbeing</article-title>. <source>Sociol Heal Illn</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>478</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>493</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aleksynska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tritah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Occupation-education mismatch of immigrant workers in Europe: Context and policies</article-title>. <source>Econ Educ Rev</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kroh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>K&#x000fc;hne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siegert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siegers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sampling, Nonresponse, and Integrated Weighting of the 2016 IAB-BAMF-SOEP Survey of Refugees (M3/M4), revised version</article-title>. <source>SOEP Surv Pap</source>. <year>2017</year>; <fpage>477</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>K&#x000fc;hne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kroh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sampling in Times of High Immigration: The Survey Process of the IAB-BAMF-SOEP Survey of Refugees</article-title>. <source>Surv Methods Insights from the Field</source>. <year>2019</year>; <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">DIW. IAB-BAMF-SOEP Survey of Refugees 2016. 2018. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5684/soep.iab-bamf-soep-mig.2016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>L&#x000f6;we</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glaesmer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wingenfeld</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A 4-item measure of depression and anxiety: Validation and standardization of the Patient Health Questionnaire-4 (PHQ-4) in the general population</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>122</volume>: <fpage>86</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2009.06.019</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19616305?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19616305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tibubos</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beutel</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Br&#x000e4;hler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Is assessment of depression equivalent for migrants of different cultural backgrounds? Results from the German population-based Gutenberg Health Study (GHS)</article-title>. <source>Depress Anxiety</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1178</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1189</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/da.22831</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30156742?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30156742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bardo</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Validity of Domain Satisfaction Across Cohorts in the US</article-title>. <source>Soc Indic Res</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>117</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>385</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Idler</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benyamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Self-Rated Health and Mortality: A Review of Twenty-Seven Community Studies</article-title>. <source>J Health Soc Behav</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9097506?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9097506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Epel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Casterllazzo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ickovics</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Relationship of subjective and objective social status with psychological and physical health in healthy white women</article-title>. <source>Heal Psychol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>592</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>MDR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Subjective Social Location: Data From 21 Nations</article-title>. <source>Int J Public Opin Res</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Demakakos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nazroo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Breeze</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marmot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Socioeconomic status and health: The role of subjective social status</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>67</volume>: <fpage>330</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>340</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2008.03.038</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18440111?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18440111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Elgar</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKinnon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Torsheim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schnohr</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cavallo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Patterns of Socioeconomic Inequality in Adolescent Health Differ According to the Measure of Socioeconomic Position</article-title>. <source>Soc Indic Res</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>127</volume>: <fpage>1169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1180</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nobles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Subjective socioeconomic status and health: Relationships reconsidered</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>82</volume>: <fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2013.01.021</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23453318?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23453318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoebel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maske</surname><given-names>UE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeeb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lampert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Social inequalities and depressive symptoms in adults: The role of objective and subjective socioeconomic status</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): e0169764. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0169764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoebel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lampert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Subjective social status and health: Multidisciplinary explanations and methodological challenges</article-title>. <source>J Health Psychol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>173</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1359105318800804</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30230391?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30230391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Macleod</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Is subjective social status a more important determinant of health than objective social status? Evidence from a prospective observational study of Scottish men</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>1916</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1929</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socscimed.2005.04.009</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 15916842?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15916842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cundiff</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Is subjective social status a unique correlate of physical health? A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Heal Psychol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1125</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ostrove</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuppermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Objective and subjective assessments of socioeconomic status and their relationship to self-rated health in an ethnically diverse sample of pregnant women</article-title>. <source>Heal Psychol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>618</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cundiff</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Uchino</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Subjective social status: Construct validity and associations with psychosocial vulnerability and self-rated health</article-title>. <source>Int J Behav Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>158</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12529-011-9206-1</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22200973?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22200973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Singh-Manoux</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marmot</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Subjective social status: Its determinants and its association with measures of ill-health in the Whitehall II study</article-title>. <source>Soc Sci Med</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1333</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0277-9536(02)00131-4</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 12600368?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12600368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ferrer-i-Carbonell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frijters</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>How Important is Methodology for the estimates of the determinants of Happiness?</article-title>
<source>Econ J</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>114</volume>: <fpage>641</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>659</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Migration and mental health: Evidence from a natural experiment</article-title>. <source>J Health Econ</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>677</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>687</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhealeco.2009.02.007</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19349087?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19349087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Straiton</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reneflot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mental Health of Refugees and Non-refugees from War-Conflict Countries: Data from Primary Healthcare Services and the Norwegian Prescription Database</article-title>. <source>J Immigr Minor Heal</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>582</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>589</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gezie</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yalew</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gete</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Azale</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeeb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Socio-economic, trafficking exposures and mental health symptoms of human trafficking returnees in Ethiopia: using a generalized structural equation modelling</article-title>. <source>Int J Ment Health Syst</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13033-018-0241-z</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 30386421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30386421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Phelan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tehranifar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Social Conditions as Fundamental Causes of Health Inequalities: Theory, Evidence, and Policy Implications</article-title>. <source>J Health Soc Behav</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>28</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kherallah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sahloul</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jamil</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alahfez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eddin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Health care in Syria before and during the crisis</article-title>. <source>Avicenna J Med</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/2231-0770.102275</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23826546?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23826546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#x000e4;ssler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Socioeconomic status, status inconsistency and risk of ischaemic heart disease: A prospective study among members of a statutory health insurance company</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>611</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech.2006.047340</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 17568052?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17568052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crager</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gany</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Onset of posttraumatic stress disorder and major depression among refugees and voluntary migrants to the United States</article-title>. <source>J Trauma Stress</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>705</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>712</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jts.21763</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23184423?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23184423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stillman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rohorua</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Miserable migrants? Natural experiment evidence on international migration and objective and subjective well-being</article-title>. <source>World Dev</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>von Werthern</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grigorakis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vizard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>The mental health and wellbeing of Unaccompanied Refugee Minors (URMs)</article-title>. <source>Child Abus Negl</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>98</volume>: <fpage>104146</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frangakis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Willke</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Addressing ceiling effects in health status measures: A comparison of techniques applied to measures for people with HIV disease</article-title>. <source>Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>339</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1475-6773.2007.00745.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18211533?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18211533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beegle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Himelein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ravallion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Frame-of-reference bias in subjective welfare</article-title>. <source>J Econ Behav Organ</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>81</volume>: <fpage>556</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>570</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Brickman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Hedonic relativism and planning the good society</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Appley</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, editor. <source>Adaptation level theory A symposium</source>. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Mass.</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>; <year>1971</year> pp. <fpage>287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luhmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Subjective well-being and adaptation to life events: A meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Pers Soc Psychol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>592</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>615</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0025948</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22059843?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22059843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pmed.1003093.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cords</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sellung</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sousa-Poza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of different life events on life satisfaction in the Russian Longitudinal Monitoring Survey</article-title>. <source>Econ Lett</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>129</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. </mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><sub-article id="pmed.1003093.r001" article-type="aggregated-review-documents"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.r001</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision Letter 0</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>Clare</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Clare Stone</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Clare Stone</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="rel-obj001" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093" related-article-type="reviewed-article"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">15 Jan 2020</named-content>
</p><p>Dear Dr. Zeeb,</p><p>Thank you very much for submitting your manuscript "Pre-migration socioeconomic status and post-migration health: evidence from Syrian refugees in Germany" (PMEDICINE-D-19-03328) for consideration at PLOS Medicine. </p><p>Your paper was evaluated by a senior editor and discussed among all the editors here. It was also discussed with an academic editor with relevant expertise, and sent to independent reviewers, including a statistical reviewer. The reviews are appended at the bottom of this email and any accompanying reviewer attachments can be seen via the link below:</p><p>[LINK]</p><p>In light of these reviews, I am afraid that we will not be able to accept the manuscript for publication in the journal in its current form, but we would like to consider a revised version that addresses the reviewers' and editors' comments. Obviously we cannot make any decision about publication until we have seen the revised manuscript and your response, and we plan to seek re-review by one or more of the reviewers. </p><p>In revising the manuscript for further consideration, your revisions should address the specific points made by each reviewer and the editors. Please also check the guidelines for revised papers at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/revising-your-manuscript">http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/revising-your-manuscript</ext-link> for any that apply to your paper. In your rebuttal letter you should indicate your response to the reviewers' and editors' comments, the changes you have made in the manuscript, and include either an excerpt of the revised text or the location (eg: page and line number) where each change can be found. Please submit a clean version of the paper as the main article file; a version with changes marked should be uploaded as a marked up manuscript.</p><p>In addition, we request that you upload any figures associated with your paper as individual TIF or EPS files with 300dpi resolution at resubmission; please read our figure guidelines for more information on our requirements: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/figures">http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/figures</ext-link>. While revising your submission, please upload your figure files to the PACE digital diagnostic tool, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/">https://pacev2.apexcovantage.com/</ext-link>. PACE helps ensure that figures meet PLOS requirements. To use PACE, you must first register as a user. Then, login and navigate to the UPLOAD tab, where you will find detailed instructions on how to use the tool. If you encounter any issues or have any questions when using PACE, please email us at <email>PLOSMedicine@plos.org</email>.</p><p>We expect to receive your revised manuscript by Jan 29 2020 11:59PM. Please email us (<email>plosmedicine@plos.org</email>) if you have any questions or concerns.</p><p>***Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.***</p><p>We ask every co-author listed on the manuscript to fill in a contributing author statement, making sure to declare all competing interests. If any of the co-authors have not filled in the statement, we will remind them to do so when the paper is revised. If all statements are not completed in a timely fashion this could hold up the re-review process. If new competing interests are declared later in the revision process, this may also hold up the submission. Should there be a problem getting one of your co-authors to fill in a statement we will be in contact. YOU MUST NOT ADD OR REMOVE AUTHORS UNLESS YOU HAVE ALERTED THE EDITOR HANDLING THE MANUSCRIPT TO THE CHANGE AND THEY SPECIFICALLY HAVE AGREED TO IT. You can see our competing interests policy here: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/competing-interests">http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/competing-interests</ext-link>.</p><p>Please use the following link to submit the revised manuscript: </p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pmedicine/">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pmedicine/</ext-link></p><p>Your article can be found in the "Submissions Needing Revision" folder. </p><p>To enhance the reproducibility of your results, we recommend that you deposit your laboratory protocols in protocols.io, where a protocol can be assigned its own identifier (DOI) such that it can be cited independently in the future. For instructions see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/submission-guidelines#loc-methods">http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/submission-guidelines#loc-methods</ext-link>.</p><p>Please ensure that the paper adheres to the PLOS Data Availability Policy (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/data-availability">http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/data-availability</ext-link>), which requires that all data underlying the study's findings be provided in a repository or as Supporting Information. For data residing with a third party, authors are required to provide instructions with contact information for obtaining the data. PLOS journals do not allow statements supported by "data not shown" or "unpublished results." For such statements, authors must provide supporting data or cite public sources that include it. </p><p>We look forward to receiving your revised manuscript. </p><p>Sincerely,</p><p>Clare Stone, PhD</p><p>Managing Editor </p><p>PLOS Medicine</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plosmedicine.org">plosmedicine.org</ext-link></p><p>-----------------------------------------------------------</p><p>Requests from the editors:</p><p>Please revise your title according to PLOS Medicine's style. Your title must be nondeclarative and not a question. It should begin with main concept if possible. "Effect of" should be used only if causality can be inferred, i.e., for an RCT. Please place the study design ("A randomized controlled trial," "A retrospective study," "A modelling study," etc.) in the subtitle (ie, after a colon).</p><p>Please structure your abstract using the PLOS Medicine headings (Background, Methods and Findings, Conclusions).</p><p>Abstract Background: Provide the context of why the study is important. The final sentence should clearly state the study question.</p><p>Abstract Methods and Findings:</p><p>* Please ensure that all numbers presented in the abstract are present and identical to numbers presented in the main manuscript text.</p><p>* Please include the study design, population and setting, number of participants, years during which the study took place, length of follow up, and main outcome measures.</p><p>* Please quantify the main results (with 95% CIs and p values).</p><p>* Please include the important dependent variables that are adjusted for in the analyses.</p><p>* Please include the actual amounts and/or absolute risk(s) of relevant outcomes (including NNT or NNH where appropriate), not just relative risks or correlation coefficients. (example for absolute risks: PMID: 28399126). </p><p>* Please include a summary of adverse events if these were assessed in the study.</p><p>* In the last sentence of the Abstract Methods and Findings section, please describe the main limitation(s) of the study's methodology.</p><p>Data &#x02013; the URL you provide does not seem to take one to a repository. All data needs to be made available &#x02013; and for referees to also assess. Please ensure this is available on resubmission. Noting an author cannot be a point of contact. Also remove the reference to data and on request from line 102.</p><p>At this stage, we ask that you include a short, non-technical Author Summary of your research to make findings accessible to a wide audience that includes both scientists and non-scientists. The Author Summary should immediately follow the Abstract in your revised manuscript. This text is subject to editorial change and should be distinct from the scientific abstract. Please see our author guidelines for more information: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/revising-your-manuscript#loc-author-summary">https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/revising-your-manuscript#loc-author-summary</ext-link></p><p>Please ensure all questionnaires are provided as Supp files (and translated into English, as needed). </p><p>Line 249 &#x02013; where (not were)</p><p>All of your Figs appear to have converted oddly and appear very small. Please do visit our guidleines on figures format and size. </p><p>Please ensure that the study is reported according to the [STROBE] guideline, and include the completed [STROBE or other] checklist as Supporting Information. When completing the checklist, please use section and paragraph numbers, rather than page numbers. Please add the following statement, or similar, to the Methods: "This study is reported as per the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) guideline (S1 Checklist)."</p><p>Please report your study according to the relevant guideline, which can be found here: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.equator-network.org/">http://www.equator-network.org/</ext-link></p><p>Comments from the reviewers:</p><p>Reviewer #1: "Pre-migration socioeconomic status and post-migration health: evidence from Syrian refugees in Germany" analyzes survey data of 2000-plus Syrian refugees that had entered Germany on or after 2013, using two main standard multivariate regression models - the first a cross-sectional analysis for five health measures for their current status in Germany (T1), and the second a longitudinal analysis also involving their condition when in Syria (T0).</p><p>The authors modify both main regression models with varying combinations of covariates (results summarized in Tables 2 &#x00026; 3) such as sex, age, sociodemographics, migration experience &#x00026; experience in Germany, which generally produce similar (robust) outcomes, with the major exception of sex (covered in the section on Heterogeneity). The key conclusion is that the main dependant variable of after-migration "health satisfaction" is strongly attentuated (significantly less strongly correlated) with reference to pre-migration SES, in contrast to pre-migration "health satisfaction" (expectedly?) being highly correlated with SES, as visually displayed in Figures 1 &#x00026; 2.</p><p>1) A first observation would be that the conclusions from the current analysis might more properly be claimed on "post-migration health satisfaction" rather than "post-migration health" (as in the manuscript title), as the relevant longitudinal analysis was performed on "health satisfaction" and not "(self-reported) health", notwithstanding the relatively high (~0.8) correlation between the two indicators as shown in Table A1. Moreover, the correlation with "mental distress (mental health?)" is weak.</p><p>The distinction between "health satisfaction" and (actual) "self-reported health" would appear to be important, because there likely remain interactions between expressed satisfaction and underlying health that are difficult to quantify (e.g. one's health is so-so, but he thinks it reasonable given his current state as a refugee, and thus expresses satisfaction). There might be latitude to visualize the typical relationship between "health satisfaction" and "self-reported health" in a manner similar to Figures 1 &#x00026; 2.</p><p>2) Following on, a possible approach for analyzing "self-reported health" longitudinally, might be to substitute the missing T0 "self-reported health" data, with values predicted using T0 "health satisfaction" and the relationship between T1 "health satisfaction" and T1 "self-reported health", assuming this relationship stays constant.</p><p>3) Is there a particular justification for adding the "sociodemographics", then "migration experience", then "experience in Germany" covariates in that order, for both the cross-sectional and longitudinal models?</p><p>4) The authors note possible ceiling effects of a finite scale in their discussion of limitations. It is known that individuals may subjectively treat the scales in different ways (e.g. some might use only the top few values, while others might use the full scale). Might any of the (possibly unused) survey responses be used to estimate such tendencies? The authors may wish to discuss this possible effect further.</p><p>5) In Equation 1, what does the Beta_1a term refer to?</p><p>6) There are some minor grammatical/phrasing issues, e.g. "...the fact that migrant often live" (Line 14), "During migration passage... but also their legal status, housing conditions, economic prospects and the contexts of reception." (Line 23-28); also there is an occasional inconsistency with citation practices, for example "Spallek and colleagues (2011)..." in Line 20, with appears without the standard bracketed reference to [8] and/or [9].</p><p>Reviewer #2: Review PLoS Medicine: Pre-migration socioeconomic status and post-migration health: evidence from Syrian refugees in Germany.</p><p>This is a paper that is of high interest for people in the field and policy-makers. It is well-written and well-conducted. I have some comments that could possibly ameliorate this paper.</p><p>Major Comments:</p><p>- Please add some references to the first paragraph.</p><p>- p. 2, line 51: please explain why did you then decide to use individual SES and not at the household level?</p><p>- Please explain the S&#x00026;W concerning the use of self-reported SES, e.g. over-or underestimation,&#x02026;</p><p>- p. 6: you include education as a covariate but isn't it a measure of SES?</p><p>- please explain why you didn't stratify all the analyses by gender as both self-reported SES and self-reported health may differ by gender.</p><p>- Please discuss the age limits of the study.</p><p>- p. 9: please explain the category of education 'certificate different'.</p><p>- p. 9: please discuss gender differences in the descriptives as well.</p><p>- The tables should be readable and easily interpretable on itself. Please explain in the titles and headings what numbers are shown.</p><p>- The figures are not readable.</p><p>- As the dependent variables are self-reported health variables, I personally think that these observed differences are not so much related to access to health care but more to experiences along the way. Please discuss this issue in the discussion paragraph.</p><p>- p. 17, line 352: as this is a cross-sectional study, please be careful when using words as 'influences'. </p><p>Minor Comments:</p><p>- p. 2, lines 28-30: please check the construction of this sentence.</p><p>- p. 2 line 34: please first write SES in full spell before using the abbreviation.</p><p>- p. 2, line 45: lead to.</p><p>- p. 3, line 58: pathways,</p><p>- p. 3, line 76: SES instead of SESs.</p><p>- p. 4, lines 96 and 100: data were instead of data was.</p><p>- p. 5, line 129: please check the construction of this sentence.</p><p>- p. 9, line 201: happened.</p><p>- p. 17, line 341: our data suggest.</p><p>- p. 19, line 390: specific points in time.</p><p>Reviewer #3: Overall this is a useful study using a large dataset, and provides novel findings on the complex relationship between SES and mental health. I have listed minor points below, the majority of which relate to a lack of polished language/descriptions and multiple typos. Once these are addressed, I think this study would be well worthy of publication. </p><p>Abstract</p><p>I would suggest avoiding using the word 'influx' as this has become a politicized word</p><p>Change 'on the top' to 'at the top'</p><p>Please name the study design</p><p>Line 8 amend 'their' to 'migrant'</p><p>I think it is misleading to refer to a longitudinal analysis when data was only collected at one time point? Could it be referred to as a retrospective analysis?</p><p>Introduction </p><p>P1 line 4 - can the authors define what 'top country' refers to? Country with the most migrants?</p><p>P1 line 14 - change migrant to migrants</p><p>P2 line 34 -please define the acronym in the first use</p><p>P2 line 45 - leads instead of lead</p><p>P3 line 57 - 'the' chronically ill</p><p>P4 line 80 - please state the study design </p><p>P4 line 81 - the question 'of'</p><p>P5 line 87 - 'a' scientific </p><p>P4 line 88-91 - the hypotheses could be clearer. What is meant by safeguard? As we don't know the study design or what kind of data will be used, it's hard to know what this means. The first hypothesis also seems to include two hypothesis within it.</p><p>Methods</p><p>P4 line 93 - again, the study design needs to be explicit from the start, before describing where the data comes from</p><p>P4 line 93 - international readers, like me, will not be familiar with the SOEP. Could the authors add a sentence to describe what it is? </p><p>P4 line 95 - why predominantly in these dates? Can the authors be specific about which dates are included?</p><p>P4 line 99 - change 'their' to migrant'</p><p>P4 line 103 the link is helpful but I think more detail should be in this section. How were the migrants identified by the system? How were they first contacted? How was an interpreter arranged? As it stands, it is quite unclear how these data was generated. It is also unclear what the overall pupose of data collection was, and exactly what was included. </p><p>P5 line 114 - as 'an' indicator</p><p>P5 line 120 - 'used' not 'use'</p><p>P5 line 124 - 'was' measured</p><p>P5 line 126 - it might be worth citing studies that show the PHQs validity in migrant populations too? <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30156742">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30156742</ext-link></p><p>P6 line 140 - sentence doesn't make sense</p><p>P6 line 155 - for a 'full' description</p><p>P7 line 157 - change 'their' to 'migrant'</p><p>Results</p><p>P9 table 1 - the table is a little unclear, what does Income N/A mean and why is the % so high? Given that income is a core part of SES it seems an important variable to be missing almost half of?</p><p>P10 line 210 - sentence does not make sense</p><p>P12 line 244 - rephrase 'lower levels of health' Its unclear what this means</p><p>P12 line 248 - rephrase pre-migration 'area'</p><p>Discussion</p><p>P17 line 335 - people who have been trafficked instead of traffic persons</p><p>P17 line 342-43 - rephrase as it does not make sense</p><p>P18 line 381 - the two time points seems misleading, isn't it retrospective? The wording here (and in thr abstract) implies to points of administration of measures? It's also unclear how missing data was handled. </p><p>P19 line 389 - 'a' point in time</p><p>P19 line 404 - 'Syrians' or 'Syrian migrants' not 'Syrian'</p><p>Any attachments provided with reviews can be seen via the following link:</p><p>[LINK]</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s015"><label>Attachment</label><caption><p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Review PLoS Medicine.docx</named-content></p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s015.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></body></sub-article><sub-article id="pmed.1003093.r002" article-type="author-comment"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.r002</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 0</article-title></title-group><related-article id="rel-obj002" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093" related-article-type="editor-report"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">31 Jan 2020</named-content>
</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s016"><label>Attachment</label><caption><p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Pointbypointreply.docx</named-content></p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s016.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></body></sub-article><sub-article id="pmed.1003093.r003" article-type="aggregated-review-documents"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.r003</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision Letter 1</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>Clare</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Clare Stone</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Clare Stone</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="rel-obj003" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093" related-article-type="reviewed-article"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>1</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">18 Feb 2020</named-content>
</p><p>Dear Dr. Zeeb,</p><p>Thank you very much for re-submitting your manuscript "Pre-migration socioeconomic status and post-migration health satisfaction among Syrian refugees in Germany: a retrospective analysis" (PMEDICINE-D-19-03328R1) for review by PLOS Medicine.</p><p>I have discussed the paper with my colleagues and the academic editor and it was also seen again by one of the original reviewers. I am pleased to say that provided the remaining editorial and production issues are dealt with we are planning to accept the paper for publication in the journal.</p><p>The remaining issues that need to be addressed are listed at the end of this email. Any accompanying reviewer attachments can be seen via the link below. Please take these into account before resubmitting your manuscript:</p><p>[LINK]</p><p>Our publications team (<email>plosmedicine@plos.org</email>) will be in touch shortly about the production requirements for your paper, and the link and deadline for resubmission. DO NOT RESUBMIT BEFORE YOU'VE RECEIVED THE PRODUCTION REQUIREMENTS.</p><p>***Please note while forming your response, if your article is accepted, you may have the opportunity to make the peer review history publicly available. The record will include editor decision letters (with reviews) and your responses to reviewer comments. If eligible, we will contact you to opt in or out.***</p><p>In revising the manuscript for further consideration here, please ensure you address the specific points made by each reviewer and the editors. In your rebuttal letter you should indicate your response to the reviewers' and editors' comments and the changes you have made in the manuscript. Please submit a clean version of the paper as the main article file. A version with changes marked must also be uploaded as a marked up manuscript file.</p><p>Please also check the guidelines for revised papers at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/revising-your-manuscript">http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/revising-your-manuscript</ext-link> for any that apply to your paper. If you haven't already, we ask that you provide a short, non-technical Author Summary of your research to make findings accessible to a wide audience that includes both scientists and non-scientists. The Author Summary should immediately follow the Abstract in your revised manuscript. This text is subject to editorial change and should be distinct from the scientific abstract.</p><p>We expect to receive your revised manuscript within 1 week. Please email us (<email>plosmedicine@plos.org</email>) if you have any questions or concerns.</p><p>We ask every co-author listed on the manuscript to fill in a contributing author statement. If any of the co-authors have not filled in the statement, we will remind them to do so when the paper is revised. If all statements are not completed in a timely fashion this could hold up the re-review process. Should there be a problem getting one of your co-authors to fill in a statement we will be in contact. YOU MUST NOT ADD OR REMOVE AUTHORS UNLESS YOU HAVE ALERTED THE EDITOR HANDLING THE MANUSCRIPT TO THE CHANGE AND THEY SPECIFICALLY HAVE AGREED TO IT.</p><p>Please ensure that the paper adheres to the PLOS Data Availability Policy (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/data-availability">http://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/s/data-availability</ext-link>), which requires that all data underlying the study's findings be provided in a repository or as Supporting Information. For data residing with a third party, authors are required to provide instructions with contact information for obtaining the data. PLOS journals do not allow statements supported by "data not shown" or "unpublished results." For such statements, authors must provide supporting data or cite public sources that include it.</p><p>If you have any questions in the meantime, please contact me or the journal staff on <email>plosmedicine@plos.org</email>. </p><p>We look forward to receiving the revised manuscript by Feb 25 2020 11:59PM. </p><p>Sincerely,</p><p>Clare Stone, PhD</p><p>Managing Editor </p><p>PLOS Medicine</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plosmedicine.org">plosmedicine.org</ext-link></p><p>------------------------------------------------------------</p><p>Requests from Editors:</p><p>Data- the link www.diw.de appears to be a general site. It is not clear how one can access data from this. Please provide a direct link to the data from your study. Also data on request (one presumes from the authors) does not comply with our open data policy where authors cannot be points of contact. Please provide the contact details of say a data committee where the method/ code can be accessed from. </p><p>Please substitute "cross-sectional" for "retrospective" in the title</p><p>- demographic details are needed in the abstract as well as mean age. </p><p>- p&#x0003c;0.01 -&#x0003e; exact value or p&#x0003c; 0.001 please</p><p>Please change gender to sex. The terms gender and sex are not interchangeable (as discussed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/gender/whatisgender/en/">http://www.who.int/gender/whatisgender/en/</ext-link> ); please use the appropriate term</p><p>- introduction is very long &#x02013; please shorten to improve accessibility</p><p>Did your study have a prospective protocol or analysis plan? Please state this (either way) early in the Methods section.</p><p>a) If a prospective analysis plan (from your funding proposal, IRB or other ethics committee submission, study protocol, or other planning document written before analyzing the data) was used in designing the study, please include the relevant prospectively written document with your revised manuscript as a Supporting Information file to be published alongside your study, and cite it in the Methods section. A legend for this file should be included at the end of your manuscript. </p><p>b) If no such document exists, please make sure that the Methods section transparently describes when analyses were planned, and when/why any data-driven changes to analyses took place. </p><p>c) In either case, changes in the analysis&#x02014;including those made in response to peer review comments&#x02014;should be identified as such in the Methods section of the paper, with rationale.</p><p>I cannot see a table with absolute numbers of participants and their demographic information. Please provide this in the main text and ideally this should be table 1 and re-order others tables accordingly. </p><p>STROBE &#x02013; please be accurate and provide sections instead of &#x02018;first part&#x02019;. </p><p>Comments from Reviewers:</p><p>Reviewer #1: The authors have addressed our original points satisfactorily; the additional clarifying analyses/charts were appreciated.</p><p>Given the emphasis on the 5 SES categories in the analysis (as also illustrated in Figures 1 to 4), it might be appropriate to include a breakdown of characteristics (as from Table 1) by these SES categories, including the number of subjects in each category.</p><p>The conflation of "health" and "health satisfaction" throughout the text remains slightly concerning; authors might consider re-emphasizing the use of health satisfaction from surveys as a proxy for health, at opportune points in the manuscript (e.g. the beginning of the discussion section)</p><p>Any attachments provided with reviews can be seen via the following link:</p><p>[LINK]</p></body></sub-article><sub-article id="pmed.1003093.r004" article-type="author-comment"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.r004</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response to Decision Letter 1</article-title></title-group><related-article id="rel-obj004" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093" related-article-type="editor-report"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>2</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="author-response-date">27 Feb 2020</named-content>
</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pmed.1003093.s017"><label>Attachment</label><caption><p>Submitted filename: <named-content content-type="submitted-filename">Pointbypointreply.docx</named-content></p></caption><media xlink:href="pmed.1003093.s017.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></body></sub-article><sub-article id="pmed.1003093.r005" article-type="editor-report"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093.r005</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision Letter 2</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>Clare</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Clare Stone</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Clare Stone</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="rel-obj005" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pmed.1003093" related-article-type="reviewed-article"/><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Submission Version</meta-name><meta-value>2</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></front-stub><body><p>
<named-content content-type="letter-date">28 Feb 2020</named-content>
</p><p>Dear Prof. Zeeb, </p><p>On behalf of my colleagues and the academic editor, Dr. Paul Spiegel, I am delighted to inform you that your manuscript entitled "Pre-migration socioeconomic status and post-migration health satisfaction among Syrian refugees in Germany: a cross-sectional analysis" (PMEDICINE-D-19-03328R2) has been accepted for publication in PLOS Medicine. </p><p>PRODUCTION PROCESS</p><p>Before publication you will see the copyedited word document (in around 1-2 weeks from now) and a PDF galley proof shortly after that. The copyeditor will be in touch shortly before sending you the copyedited Word document. We will make some revisions at the copyediting stage to conform to our general style, and for clarification. When you receive this version you should check and revise it very carefully, including figures, tables, references, and supporting information, because corrections at the next stage (proofs) will be strictly limited to (1) errors in author names or affiliations, (2) errors of scientific fact that would cause misunderstandings to readers, and (3) printer's (introduced) errors.</p><p>If you are likely to be away when either this document or the proof is sent, please ensure we have contact information of a second person, as we will need you to respond quickly at each point.</p><p>PRESS</p><p>A selection of our articles each week are press released by the journal. You will be contacted nearer the time if we are press releasing your article in order to approve the content and check the contact information for journalists is correct. If your institution or institutions have a press office, please notify them about your upcoming paper at this point, to enable them to help maximize its impact. </p><p>PROFILE INFORMATION</p><p>Now that your manuscript has been accepted, please log into EM and update your profile. Go to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.editorialmanager.com/pmedicine">https://www.editorialmanager.com/pmedicine</ext-link>, log in, and click on the "Update My Information" link at the top of the page. Please update your user information to ensure an efficient production and billing process.</p><p>Thank you again for submitting the manuscript to PLOS Medicine. We look forward to publishing it. </p><p>Best wishes, </p><p>Clare Stone, PhD</p><p>Managing Editor </p><p>PLOS Medicine</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plosmedicine.org">plosmedicine.org</ext-link></p></body></sub-article></article>